<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
<text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>Now King David was old,<a class='mr'></a> advanced in years,<a class='fn'></a> and although they would cover him with garments, he could not get warm. <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So his servants said to him: “Let a girl, a virgin, be found for my lord the king, and she will wait on the king as his nurse. She will lie in your arms so that my lord the king may feel warm.” <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>They searched throughout all the territory of Israel for a beautiful girl, and they found Ab′i·shag<a class='mr'></a> the Shu′nam·mite<a class='mr'></a> and brought her in to the king. <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>The girl was extremely beautiful, and she became the king’s nurse and waited on him, but the king did not have sexual relations with her.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Meanwhile, Ad·o·ni′jah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Hag′gith was exalting himself, saying: “I am going to be king!” He had a chariot made for himself with horsemen and 50 men to run before him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But his father had never confronted him<a class='fn'></a> by saying: “Why have you done this?” He was also very handsome, and his mother had given birth to him after Ab′sa·lom. <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>He conferred with Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah and A·bi′a·thar<a class='mr'></a> the priest, and they offered Ad·o·ni′jah help and support.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>But Za′dok<a class='mr'></a> the priest, Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da, Nathan<a class='mr'></a> the prophet, Shim′e·i,<a class='mr'></a> Re′i, and David’s mighty warriors<a class='mr'></a> did not support Ad·o·ni′jah.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Eventually Ad·o·ni′jah held a sacrifice<a class='mr'></a> of sheep, cattle, and fattened animals by the stone of Zo′he·leth, which is near En-ro′gel, and he invited all his brothers the king’s sons, and all the men of Judah the king’s servants. <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>But he did not invite Nathan the prophet, Be·nai′ah and the mighty warriors, or Sol′o·mon his brother. <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Nathan<a class='mr'></a> then said to Bath-she′ba,<a class='mr'></a> Sol′o·mon’s mother:<a class='mr'></a> “Have you not heard that Ad·o·ni′jah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Hag′gith has become king, and our lord David does not know anything about it? <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>So now come, please, and let me advise you, so that you may save your own life and the life of<a class='fn'></a> your son Sol′o·mon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Go in to King David and say to him, ‘Was it not you, my lord the king, who swore to your servant, saying: “Your son Sol′o·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne”?<a class='mr'></a> So why has Ad·o·ni′jah become king?’ <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>While you are still there speaking with the king, I will come in after you and confirm your words.”</p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>So Bath-she′ba went in to the king, into his private room. The king was very old, and Ab′i·shag<a class='mr'></a> the Shu′nam·mite was waiting on the king. <span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then Bath-she′ba bowed low and prostrated herself to the king, and the king said: “What is your request?” <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>She replied: “My lord, it was you who swore by Jehovah your God to your servant, ‘Your son Sol′o·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>But look! Ad·o·ni′jah has become king, and my lord the king does not know anything about it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>He sacrificed bulls, fattened animals, and sheep in great quantity and invited all the sons of the king and A·bi′a·thar the priest and Jo′ab the chief of the army;<a class='mr'></a> but he did not invite your servant Sol′o·mon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>And now, my lord the king, the eyes of all Israel are upon you to tell them who will sit on the throne of my lord the king after him. <span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Otherwise, as soon as my lord the king is laid to rest with his forefathers, I and also my son Sol′o·mon will be considered traitors.”</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And while she was still speaking to the king, Nathan the prophet came in.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>At once the king was told: “Here is Nathan the prophet!” He came in before the king and prostrated himself to the king with his face to the ground. <span id='dcv_1_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Then Nathan said: “My lord the king, did you say, ‘Ad·o·ni′jah will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne’?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>For today he has gone down to sacrifice<a class='mr'></a> bulls, fattened animals, and sheep in great quantity, and he has invited all the sons of the king and the chiefs of the army and A·bi′a·thar the priest.<a class='mr'></a> They are there eating and drinking with him, and they keep saying, ‘Long live King Ad·o·ni′jah!’ <span id='dcv_1_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>But he did not invite me, your servant, or Za′dok the priest, or Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da, or your servant Sol′o·mon. <span id='dcv_1_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Has my lord the king authorized this without telling your servant who should sit on the throne of my lord the king after him?”</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>King David now answered: “Call Bath-she′ba for me.” At that she came in and stood before the king. <span id='dcv_1_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>The king then swore an oath: “As surely as Jehovah is living, the one who rescued me<a class='fn'></a> out of all distress,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>just as I swore to you by Jehovah the God of Israel, saying, ‘Your son Sol′o·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne in my place!’ that is what I will bring about this day.” <span id='dcv_1_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Then Bath-she′ba bowed low with her face to the ground and prostrated herself to the king and said: “May my lord King David live forever!”</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Immediately King David said: “Call for me Za′dok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da.”<a class='mr'></a> So they came in before the king. <span id='dcv_1_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>The king said to them: “Take with you the servants of your lord, and have my son Sol′o·mon ride on my own mule,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and lead him down to Gi′hon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet will anoint him<a class='mr'></a> there as king over Israel; then blow the horn and say, ‘Long live King Sol′o·mon!’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Then follow him back, and he will come in and sit on my throne; and he will be king in my place, and I will commission him as leader over Israel and over Judah.” <span id='dcv_1_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>At once Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da said to the king: “Amen! May Jehovah the God of my lord the king confirm it. <span id='dcv_1_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>Just as Jehovah was with my lord the king, so let him be with Sol′o·mon,<a class='mr'></a> and may He make his throne greater than the throne of my lord King David.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>Then Za′dok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da, and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites<a class='mr'></a> went down and had Sol′o·mon ride on the mule of King David,<a class='mr'></a> and they brought him to Gi′hon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>Za′dok the priest now took the horn of oil<a class='mr'></a> out of the tent<a class='mr'></a> and anointed Sol′o·mon,<a class='mr'></a> and they began to blow the horn, and all the people began shouting: “Long live King Sol′o·mon!” <span id='dcv_1_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>After that all the people followed him and went up, playing flutes and rejoicing greatly, so that the earth was split open by their noise.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>Ad·o·ni′jah and all those invited by him heard it when they had finished eating.<a class='mr'></a> As soon as Jo′ab heard the sound of the horn, he said: “Why is there such a noisy uproar in the city?” <span id='dcv_1_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>While he was still speaking, Jon′a·than<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·bi′a·thar the priest came. Then Ad·o·ni′jah said: “Come in, for you are a good<a class='fn'></a> man, and you must bring good news.” <span id='dcv_1_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>But Jon′a·than answered Ad·o·ni′jah: “No! Our lord King David has made Sol′o·mon king. <span id='dcv_1_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>The king sent with him Za′dok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites, and they had him ride on the mule of the king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>Then Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him as king in Gi′hon. After that they came up from there rejoicing, and the city is in an uproar. That was the noise that you heard. <span id='dcv_1_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>Moreover, Sol′o·mon has sat down on the royal throne. <span id='dcv_1_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>Another thing, the servants of the king have come in to congratulate our lord King David, saying, ‘May your God make Sol′o·mon’s name more splendid than your name, and may He make his throne greater than your throne!’ At that the king bowed down on the bed. <span id='dcv_1_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>And the king also said, ‘May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, who today has granted someone to sit on my throne and has allowed my own eyes to see it!’”</p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_49' class='dv dp'><a>49 </a></span>And all those invited by Ad·o·ni′jah became terrified, and each of them rose up and went his own way. <span id='dcv_1_50' class='dv dp'><a>50 </a></span>Ad·o·ni′jah was also afraid because of Sol′o·mon, so he got up and went and grabbed hold of the horns of the altar.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_51' class='dv dp'><a>51 </a></span>The report was made to Sol′o·mon: “Here Ad·o·ni′jah has become afraid of King Sol′o·mon; and he has taken hold of the horns of the altar, saying, ‘Let King Sol′o·mon first swear to me that he will not put his servant to death by the sword.’” <span id='dcv_1_52' class='dv dx dp'><a>52 </a></span>To this Sol′o·mon said: “If he behaves in a worthy manner, not a single hair of his will fall to the ground; but if what is bad is found in him,<a class='mr'></a> he will have to die.” <span id='dcv_1_53' class='dv dp'><a>53 </a></span>So King Sol′o·mon sent for him to be brought down from the altar. Then he came in and bowed down to King Sol′o·mon, after which Sol′o·mon said to him: “Go to your own house.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dp'><a>2 </a></span>When the time of David’s death drew near, he gave his son Sol′o·mon these instructions: <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“I am about to die.<a class='fn'></a> Therefore, be strong<a class='mr'></a> and prove yourself a man.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>You must keep your obligation to Jehovah your God by walking in his ways and by observing his statutes, his commandments, his judgments, and his reminders as they are written in the Law of Moses;<a class='mr'></a> then you will succeed<a class='fn'></a> in everything you do and everywhere you turn. <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>And Jehovah will carry out his promise that he made concerning me: ‘If your sons pay attention to their way by walking faithfully before me with all their heart and soul,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> there will never fail to be a man of your line<a class='fn'></a> sitting on the throne of Israel.’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>“You also well know what Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah did to me, what he did to two chiefs of the armies of Israel—Ab′ner<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ner and A·ma′sa<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je′ther. He killed them, shedding the blood<a class='mr'></a> of war in peacetime, and he put the blood of war on the belt around his waist and on the sandals on his feet. <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>You must act according to your wisdom and not let his gray hairs go down in peace to the Grave.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>“But toward the sons of Bar·zil′lai<a class='mr'></a> the Gil′e·ad·ite, you should show loyal love, and they should be among those eating at your table, for that was how they stood by me<a class='mr'></a> when I ran away from your brother Ab′sa·lom.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>“There is also with you Shim′e·i the son of Ge′ra the Ben′ja·min·ite from Ba·hu′rim. He was the one who cursed me with a vicious curse<a class='mr'></a> on the day that I was going to Ma·ha·na′im;<a class='mr'></a> but when he came down to meet me at the Jordan, I swore to him by Jehovah: ‘I will not put you to death by the sword.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Now do not leave him unpunished,<a class='mr'></a> for you are a wise man and you know what you should do to him; you must bring his gray hairs down to the Grave<a class='fn'></a> with blood.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then David was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>The length<a class='fn'></a> of David’s reign over Israel was 40 years. In Heb′ron<a class='mr'></a> he reigned for 7 years, and in Jerusalem he reigned for 33 years.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Sol′o·mon then sat down on the throne of David his father, and gradually his kingship became firmly established.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>In time Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith came to Bath-she′ba, Sol′o·mon’s mother. She asked: “Is your coming peaceable?” He replied: “It is peaceable.” <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>He then said: “I have something to say to you.” So she said: “Speak.” <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He continued: “You well know that the kingship was to become mine, and all Israel expected<a class='fn'></a> me to become king;<a class='mr'></a> but the kingship eluded me and became my brother’s, for it was from Jehovah that it became his.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>But now there is just one request that I am making of you. Do not turn me away.” So she said to him: “Speak.” <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>He then said: “Please, ask Sol′o·mon the king—for he will not turn you away—to give me Ab′i·shag<a class='mr'></a> the Shu′nam·mite as a wife.” <span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>To this Bath-she′ba said: “Very well! I will speak for you to the king.”</p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So Bath-she′ba went in to King Sol′o·mon to speak to him for Ad·o·ni′jah. At once the king rose to meet her and bowed down to her. Then he sat down on his throne and had a throne set for the king’s mother, so that she could sit at his right. <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>She then said: “There is one small request that I am making of you. Do not turn me away.” So the king said to her: “Make it, my mother; for I will not turn you away.” <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>She said: “Let Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite be given as a wife to your brother Ad·o·ni′jah.” <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>At this King Sol′o·mon answered his mother: “Why are you requesting Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite for Ad·o·ni′jah? You may as well request the kingship for him,<a class='mr'></a> for he is my older brother,<a class='mr'></a> and supporting him are A·bi′a·thar the priest and Jo′ab<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ze·ru′iah.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>With that King Sol′o·mon swore by Jehovah: “So may God do to me and add to it if it was not at the cost of his own life<a class='fn'></a> that Ad·o·ni′jah made this request. <span id='dcv_2_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>And now, as surely as Jehovah is living, who has firmly established me<a class='mr'></a> and seated me on the throne of David my father and who made a house<a class='fn'></a> for me,<a class='mr'></a> just as he promised, Ad·o·ni′jah will be put to death<a class='mr'></a> today.” <span id='dcv_2_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon immediately sent Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da, who went out and struck Ad·o·ni′jah down,<a class='fn'></a> and he died.</p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>To A·bi′a·thar<a class='mr'></a> the priest, the king said: “Go to your fields in An′a·thoth!<a class='mr'></a> You deserve to die, but on this day I will not put you to death because you carried the Ark of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah before David my father<a class='mr'></a> and because you shared in all the hardships that my father suffered.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>So Sol′o·mon drove A·bi′a·thar out from serving as a priest of Jehovah, to fulfill Jehovah’s word against the house of E′li<a class='mr'></a> in Shi′loh.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>When the news reached Jo′ab—for Jo′ab had supported Ad·o·ni′jah<a class='mr'></a> but he had not supported Ab′sa·lom<a class='mr'></a>—Jo′ab fled to the tent of Jehovah<a class='mr'></a> and grabbed hold of the horns of the altar. <span id='dcv_2_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Then King Sol′o·mon was told: “Jo′ab has fled to the tent of Jehovah, and he is there beside the altar.” So Sol′o·mon sent Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, saying: “Go, strike him down!” <span id='dcv_2_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So Be·nai′ah went to the tent of Jehovah and said to him: “This is what the king says, ‘Come out!’” But he said: “No! I will die here.” Be·nai′ah brought word back to the king: “This is what Jo′ab said, and this is what he answered me.” <span id='dcv_2_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Then the king said to him: “Do just as he said; strike him down and bury him and remove from me and from the house of my father the blood that Jo′ab spilled without just cause.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Jehovah will bring his blood back on his own head, for without my father David’s knowledge, he struck down and killed with the sword two men more righteous and better than he was: Ab′ner<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ner, the chief of the army of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and A·ma′sa<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je′ther, the chief of the army of Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Their blood will come back on the head of Jo′ab and on the head of his offspring<a class='fn'></a> forever;<a class='mr'></a> but for David, his offspring,<a class='fn'></a> his house, and his throne, may there be peace from Jehovah forever.” <span id='dcv_2_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Then Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da went up and struck Jo′ab down and put him to death, and he was buried at his own house in the wilderness. <span id='dcv_2_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Then the king appointed Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da over the army in his place, and the king appointed Za′dok<a class='mr'></a> the priest in place of A·bi′a·thar.</p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>Then the king summoned Shim′e·i<a class='mr'></a> and said to him: “Build yourself a house in Jerusalem, and live there; do not go out from there to any other place. <span id='dcv_2_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>On the day you go out and cross the Kid′ron Valley,<a class='mr'></a> you can be sure that you will die. Your blood will be on your own head.” <span id='dcv_2_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>Shim′e·i replied to the king: “What you have said is fair. Your servant will do just as my lord the king has said.” So Shim′e·i stayed in Jerusalem for many days.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>But at the end of three years, two of Shim′e·i’s slaves ran away to A′chish<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ma′a·cah the king of Gath. When Shim′e·i was told: “Look! Your slaves are in Gath,” <span id='dcv_2_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>Shim′e·i immediately saddled his donkey and went to see A′chish in Gath to find his slaves. When Shim′e·i returned from Gath with his slaves, <span id='dcv_2_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>Sol′o·mon was told: “Shim′e·i has gone out of Jerusalem to Gath and has returned.” <span id='dcv_2_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>At that the king summoned Shim′e·i and said to him: “Did I not put you under oath by Jehovah and warn you: ‘On the day you go out from here to any other place, you can be sure that you will die’? And did you not say to me, ‘What you are saying is fair; I will obey’?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>Why, then, did you not keep the oath of Jehovah and the commandment that I imposed on you?” <span id='dcv_2_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>The king then said to Shim′e·i: “You know in your heart all the injury that you did to David my father,<a class='mr'></a> and Jehovah will bring back that injury on your own head.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>But King Sol′o·mon will be blessed,<a class='mr'></a> and the throne of David will be firmly established before Jehovah forever.” <span id='dcv_2_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>With that the king commanded Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, who went out and struck him down, and he died.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'>Thus the kingdom was firmly established in the hand of Sol′o·mon.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Sol′o·mon made a marriage alliance with Phar′aoh king of Egypt. He married<a class='fn'></a> Phar′aoh’s daughter<a class='mr'></a> and brought her to the City of David<a class='mr'></a> until he finished building his own house,<a class='mr'></a> and the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> and the wall around Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>But the people were still sacrificing on the high places,<a class='mr'></a> because until that time a house for the name of Jehovah had not yet been built.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Sol′o·mon continued to love Jehovah by walking in the statutes of David his father, except that he was sacrificing and making offerings smoke on the high places.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>The king went to Gib′e·on to sacrifice there, for that was the most prominent<a class='fn'></a> high place.<a class='mr'></a> Sol′o·mon offered 1,000 burnt sacrifices on that altar.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>In Gib′e·on Jehovah appeared to Sol′o·mon in a dream by night, and God said: “Ask what you would like me to give you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>At this Sol′o·mon said: “You have shown great loyal love toward your servant David my father as he walked before you in faithfulness and in righteousness and in uprightness of heart. You have continued to show him this great loyal love down to this day by giving him a son to sit on his throne.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>And now, Jehovah my God, you have made your servant king in the place of David my father, though I am just a youth<a class='fn'></a> and I am inexperienced.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Your servant is among your people whom you have chosen,<a class='mr'></a> a people so vast that they cannot be numbered or counted. <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>So grant your servant an obedient heart to judge your people,<a class='mr'></a> to discern between good and bad,<a class='mr'></a> for who is able to judge this numerous<a class='fn'></a> people of yours?”</p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>It was pleasing to Jehovah that Sol′o·mon had requested this.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>God then said to him: “Because you requested this and you did not request for yourself long life<a class='fn'></a> or riches or the death<a class='fn'></a> of your enemies, but you requested understanding to hear judicial cases,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>I will do what you asked.<a class='mr'></a> I will give you a wise and understanding heart,<a class='mr'></a> so that just as there has never been anyone like you before, there will never be anyone like you again.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Furthermore, what you have not requested I will give you,<a class='mr'></a> both riches and glory,<a class='mr'></a> so that there will be no other king like you in your lifetime.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>And if you walk in my ways by keeping my regulations and my commandments, just as David your father walked,<a class='mr'></a> I will also give you a long life.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>When Sol′o·mon awoke, he realized that it had been a dream. Then he went to Jerusalem and stood before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah and offered up burnt sacrifices and communion offerings<a class='mr'></a> and spread a feast for all his servants.</p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>At that time two prostitutes came in to the king and stood before him. <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>The first woman said: “Please, my lord, this woman and I live in one house, and I gave birth while she was in the house. <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>On the third day after I gave birth, this woman also gave birth. We were together, just the two of us; there was no one else with us in the house. <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>During the night this woman’s son died, because she lay on him. <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So she got up in the middle of the night and took my son from my side while your slave girl was asleep and laid him in her arms,<a class='fn'></a> and she laid her dead son in my arms. <span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>When I got up in the morning to nurse my son, I saw that he was dead. So I examined him closely in the morning and saw that it was not my son whom I had given birth to.” <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>But the other woman said: “No, my son is the living one, and your son is the dead one!” But the first woman was saying: “No, your son is the dead one, and my son is the living one.” That is how they argued before the king.</p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Finally the king said: “This one says, ‘This is my son, the living one, and your son is the dead one!’ and that one says, ‘No, your son is the dead one, and my son is the living one!’” <span id='dcv_3_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>The king said: “Bring me a sword.” So they brought a sword to the king. <span id='dcv_3_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>The king then said: “Cut the living child in two, and give half to one woman and half to the other.” <span id='dcv_3_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>At once the woman whose son was the living one pleaded with the king, for her compassions were stirred toward her son. She said: “Please, my lord! You should give her the living child! By no means put him to death!” But the other woman was saying: “He will be neither mine nor yours! Let them cut him in two!” <span id='dcv_3_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>At that the king answered: “Give the living child to the first woman! By no means put him to death, for she is his mother.”</p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>So all Israel heard about the judgment that the king had handed down, and they were in awe<a class='fn'></a> of the king,<a class='mr'></a> for they saw that the wisdom of God was with him to execute justice.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dp'><a>4 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon ruled over all Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>These were his high officials:<a class='fn'></a> Az·a·ri′ah the son of Za′dok<a class='mr'></a> was the priest; <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>El·i·hor′eph and A·hi′jah the sons of Shi′sha were secretaries;<a class='mr'></a> Je·hosh′a·phat<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·hi′lud was the recorder; <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Be·nai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hoi′a·da was in charge of the army; Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar<a class='mr'></a> were priests; <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Az·a·ri′ah the son of Nathan<a class='mr'></a> was over the deputies; Za′bud the son of Nathan was a priest and the king’s friend;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>A·hi′shar was over the household; and Ad·o·ni′ram<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ab′da was over those conscripted for forced labor.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Sol′o·mon had 12 deputies in charge of all Israel who provided the king and his household with food. Each one was responsible for providing the food for one month of the year.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>These were their names: The son of Hur, in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>the son of De′ker, in Ma′kaz, Sha·al′bim,<a class='mr'></a> Beth-she′mesh, and E′lon-beth-ha′nan; <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>the son of He′sed, in A·rub′both (he had So′coh and all the land of He′pher); <span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>the son of A·bin′a·dab, in all the slopes of Dor (Sol′o·mon’s daughter Ta′phath became his wife); <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Ba′a·na the son of A·hi′lud, in Ta′a·nach, Me·gid′do,<a class='mr'></a> and all Beth-she′an,<a class='mr'></a> which is beside Zar′e·than below Jez′re·el, from Beth-she′an to A′bel-me·ho′lah to the region of Jok′me·am;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>the son of Ge′ber, in Ra′moth-gil′e·ad<a class='mr'></a> (he had the tent villages of Ja′ir<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ma·nas′seh, which are in Gil′e·ad;<a class='mr'></a> he also had the region of Ar′gob,<a class='mr'></a> which is in Ba′shan:<a class='mr'></a> 60 large cities with walls and copper bars); <span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>A·hin′a·dab the son of Id′do, in Ma·ha·na′im;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>A·him′a·az, in Naph′ta·li (he took Bas′e·math, another of Sol′o·mon’s daughters, as his wife); <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Ba′a·na the son of Hu′shai, in Ash′er and Be·a′loth; <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Pa·ru′ah, in Is′sa·char; <span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Shim′e·i<a class='mr'></a> the son of E′la, in Benjamin;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Ge′ber the son of U′ri, in the land of Gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> the land of Si′hon<a class='mr'></a> king of the Am′or·ites and of Og<a class='mr'></a> king of Ba′shan. There was also one deputy in charge of all these other deputies in the land.</p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Judah and Israel were as numerous as the grains of sand by the sea;<a class='mr'></a> they were eating and drinking and rejoicing.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Sol′o·mon ruled over all the kingdoms from the River<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> to the land of the Phi·lis′tines and to the boundary of Egypt. They brought tribute and served Sol′o·mon all the days of his life.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Sol′o·mon’s food for each day was 30 cor measures<a class='fn'></a> of fine flour and 60 cor measures of flour, <span id='dcv_4_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>10 fattened cattle, 20 pastured cattle, and 100 sheep, besides some stags, gazelles, roebucks, and fattened cuckoos. <span id='dcv_4_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>For he controlled everything this side of the River,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> from Tiph′sah to Gaz′a,<a class='mr'></a> including all the kings on this side of the River; and he enjoyed peace in every region, all around him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Judah and Israel lived in security, everyone under his own vine and under his own fig tree, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba, all the days of Sol′o·mon.</p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>And Sol′o·mon had 4,000<a class='fn'></a> stalls of horses for his chariots and 12,000 horses.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>These deputies supplied food to King Sol′o·mon and to everyone who ate at the table of King Sol′o·mon. Each was responsible for his month and saw to it that nothing was lacking.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>They also brought barley and straw wherever it was needed for the horses and for the teams of horses, each according to his quota.</p></div><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>And God gave Sol′o·mon wisdom and discernment in very great measure and a broadness of heart<a class='fn'></a> like the sand on the seashore.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Sol′o·mon’s wisdom surpassed the wisdom of all the people of the East and all the wisdom of Egypt.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>He was wiser than any other man, wiser than E′than<a class='mr'></a> the Ez′ra·hite and He′man,<a class='mr'></a> Cal′col,<a class='mr'></a> and Dar′da, the sons of Ma′hol; his fame spread among all the surrounding nations.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>He composed<a class='fn'></a> 3,000 proverbs<a class='mr'></a> and his songs<a class='mr'></a> numbered 1,005. <span id='dcv_4_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>He would speak about the trees, from the cedar in Leb′a·non to the hyssop<a class='mr'></a> that grows on the wall; he would speak about the animals,<a class='mr'></a> the birds,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the creeping things,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and the fish. <span id='dcv_4_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>People from all the nations came to hear Sol′o·mon’s wisdom, including kings from all over the earth who had heard about his wisdom.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dp'><a>5 </a></span>When Hi′ram the king of Tyre<a class='mr'></a> heard that Sol′o·mon had been anointed as king in place of his father, he sent his servants to Sol′o·mon, for Hi′ram had always been a friend of David’s.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>In turn Sol′o·mon sent word to Hi′ram:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>“You well know that David my father was not able to build a house for the name of Jehovah his God because of the wars waged against him from every side until Jehovah put his enemies under the soles of his feet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>But now Jehovah my God has given me rest on all sides.<a class='mr'></a> There is no one opposing me and nothing bad happening.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So I intend to build a house for the name of Jehovah my God, just as Jehovah promised to David my father, saying: ‘Your son whom I will put on your throne in your place, he is the one who will build the house for my name.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Now command your people to cut cedars of Leb′a·non<a class='mr'></a> for me. My servants will work with your servants, and I will pay the wages of your servants according to the rate you set, for you are aware that not one of us knows how to cut trees like the Si·do′ni·ans.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>When Hi′ram heard Sol′o·mon’s words, he rejoiced greatly and said: “May Jehovah be praised today, for he has given David a wise son over this great<a class='fn'></a> people!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So Hi′ram sent word to Sol′o·mon: “I have heard the message you sent to me. I will do all you desire in providing the cedar and juniper timbers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>My servants will bring them down from Leb′a·non to the sea, and I will make them into log rafts to go by sea to the place that you designate to me. I will have them broken up there, and you can carry them away. In exchange, you will provide the food that I request for my household.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So Hi′ram supplied all the timbers of cedar and juniper that Sol′o·mon desired. <span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And Sol′o·mon gave Hi′ram 20,000 cor measures<a class='fn'></a> of wheat as food supplies for his household and 20 cor measures of very fine olive oil.<a class='fn'></a> That was what Sol′o·mon gave Hi′ram year after year.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>And Jehovah gave Sol′o·mon wisdom, just as He had promised him.<a class='mr'></a> And there was peace between Hi′ram and Sol′o·mon, and the two of them made a treaty.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon conscripted men for forced labor out of all Israel; 30,000 men were conscripted.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>He would send them to Leb′a·non in shifts of 10,000 each month. They would spend a month in Leb′a·non and two months at their homes; and Ad·o·ni′ram<a class='mr'></a> was over those conscripted for forced labor. <span id='dcv_5_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Sol′o·mon had 70,000 common laborers<a class='fn'></a> and 80,000 stonecutters<a class='mr'></a> in the mountains,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>as well as Sol′o·mon’s 3,300 princely deputies<a class='mr'></a> who served as foremen to supervise the workmen. <span id='dcv_5_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>At the king’s order, they quarried large stones, expensive stones,<a class='mr'></a> to lay the foundation<a class='mr'></a> of the house with hewn stones.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So Sol′o·mon’s builders and Hi′ram’s builders and the Ge′bal·ites<a class='mr'></a> did the cutting, and they prepared the timbers and the stones to build the house.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>In the 480th year after the Israelites<a class='fn'></a> came out of the land of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> in the fourth year after Sol′o·mon became king over Israel, in the month of Ziv<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> (that is, the second month), he began to build the house of Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The house that King Sol′o·mon built for Jehovah was 60 cubits<a class='fn'></a> long, 20 cubits wide, and 30 cubits high.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>The porch<a class='mr'></a> in front of the temple<a class='fn'></a> was 20 cubits long,<a class='fn'></a> corresponding to the width of the house.<a class='fn'></a> Its depth was ten cubits from the front of the house.</p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>He made windows of narrowing frames<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for the house. <span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Further, he built a side structure against the wall of the house; it went around the walls of the house, those of the temple<a class='fn'></a> and the innermost room,<a class='mr'></a> and he made side chambers all around.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The lowest level of the side chambers was five cubits wide, the middle level was six cubits wide, and the third level was seven cubits wide, for he made offsets<a class='fn'></a> all around the house, so that nothing was attached to the walls of the house.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>The house was built with quarry stone that had already been prepared,<a class='mr'></a> so that no hammers or axes or any iron tools were heard in the house while it was being built. <span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>The entrance of the lowest side chamber was on the south<a class='fn'></a> side of the house,<a class='mr'></a> and a winding staircase led up to the middle floor, and from the middle floor up to the third floor. <span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He continued building the house and finished it<a class='mr'></a> and covered the house with cedar beams and rows of cedar planks.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>He built the side chambers all around the house,<a class='mr'></a> each five cubits high, and they were joined to the house by cedar timbers.</p></div><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Meanwhile, the word of Jehovah came to Sol′o·mon, saying: <span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>“As for this house that you are building, if you walk in my statutes and carry out my judgments and observe all my commandments by walking in them,<a class='mr'></a> I will also carry out with you my promise that I made to David your father,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>and I will reside in the midst of the Israelites,<a class='mr'></a> and I will not forsake my people Israel.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Sol′o·mon continued building the house to finish it. <span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>He built the inside walls of the house with cedar boards. He paneled the inside walls with timber, from the floor of the house up to the rafters of the ceiling, and he overlaid the floor of the house with juniper boards.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>And he built a section of 20 cubits at the rear of the house with cedar boards, from the floor up to the rafters, and he built inside of it<a class='fn'></a> the innermost room,<a class='mr'></a> the Most Holy.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>And the temple<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a>—the part of the house in front of it—was 40 cubits. <span id='dcv_6_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>The cedar inside the house was carved with gourds<a class='mr'></a> and flowers in bloom.<a class='mr'></a> All of it was cedar; no stone was seen.</p></div><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>And he prepared the innermost room<a class='mr'></a> inside the house to put there the ark of the covenant of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>The innermost room was 20 cubits long, 20 cubits wide, and 20 cubits high;<a class='mr'></a> and he overlaid it with pure gold; he overlaid the altar<a class='mr'></a> with cedar. <span id='dcv_6_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Sol′o·mon overlaid the interior of the house with pure gold,<a class='mr'></a> and he stretched gold chains in front of the innermost room,<a class='mr'></a> which was overlaid with gold. <span id='dcv_6_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>He overlaid the whole house with gold until all the house was completed; he also overlaid with gold the entire altar<a class='mr'></a> near the innermost room.</p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>In the innermost room he made two cherubs<a class='mr'></a> of pinewood,<a class='fn'></a> each ten cubits high.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>One wing of the cherub measured five cubits, and the other wing was five cubits. From the tip of one wing to the tip of the other wing was ten cubits. <span id='dcv_6_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>The second cherub was also ten cubits. The two cherubs had the same size and shape. <span id='dcv_6_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>The height of the one cherub was ten cubits, as was that of the other cherub. <span id='dcv_6_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Then he put the cherubs<a class='mr'></a> inside the inner house.<a class='fn'></a> The wings of the cherubs were extended so that the wing of the one cherub reached to one wall and the wing of the other cherub reached to the other wall, and their wings extended toward the middle of the house, so that the wings touched. <span id='dcv_6_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>And he overlaid the cherubs with gold.</p></div><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>And on all the walls of the house all around both the inner and outer rooms,<a class='fn'></a> he carved figures of cherubs,<a class='mr'></a> palm trees,<a class='mr'></a> and flowers in bloom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>He overlaid the floor of the house with gold in the inner and outer rooms. <span id='dcv_6_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>And for the entrance of the innermost room he made doors of pinewood, side pillars, and doorposts, as a fifth part.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>The two doors were of pinewood, and he carved on them cherubs, palm trees, and flowers in bloom, and he overlaid them with gold; and he hammered the gold down over the cherubs and the palm trees. <span id='dcv_6_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>For the entrance of the temple,<a class='fn'></a> that was how he made the doorposts of pinewood, belonging to a fourth part.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>And he made two doors of juniper wood. The one door had two leaves that turned on pivots, and the other door had two leaves that turned on pivots.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>He carved cherubs, palm trees, and flowers in bloom, and overlaid gold foil on the carvings.</p></div><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>He built the inner courtyard<a class='mr'></a> with three rows of hewn stone and a row of cedar beams.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>In the 4th year, in the month of Ziv,<a class='fn'></a> the house of Jehovah had its foundation laid;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>and in the 11th year, in the month of Bul<a class='fn'></a> (that is, the eighth month), the house was finished in all its details and according to its plan.<a class='mr'></a> So he spent seven years building it.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dp'><a>7 </a></span>And it took Sol′o·mon 13 years to build his own house,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> until his whole house was completed.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>And he built the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non<a class='mr'></a> 100 cubits<a class='fn'></a> long, 50 cubits wide, and 30 cubits high on four rows of cedar pillars; and there were cedar beams<a class='mr'></a> on the pillars. <span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>It was paneled above with cedar on the girders that rested on the pillars; they numbered 45, with 15 to a row. <span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>There were three rows of framed windows, and each window was opposite another window in three tiers. <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>All the entrances and the doorposts had square<a class='fn'></a> frames, as did the front of the windows that were opposite each other in three tiers.</p></div><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>And he built the Hall<a class='fn'></a> of Pillars 50 cubits long and 30 cubits wide, and there was a porch in front of it with pillars and a canopy.</p></div><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>He also built the Hall<a class='fn'></a> of the Throne,<a class='mr'></a> where he would judge—the Hall of Judgment<a class='mr'></a>—and they paneled it with cedar from the floor to the rafters.</p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>The house<a class='fn'></a> where he was to live, at the other courtyard,<a class='mr'></a> was set back from the Hall,<a class='fn'></a> and it was similar in workmanship. He also built a house similar to this Hall for Phar′aoh’s daughter, whom Sol′o·mon had taken as a wife.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>All of these were made of expensive stones<a class='mr'></a> hewn according to measure, trimmed with stonesaws inside and out, from the foundation up to the coping, and outside as far as the great courtyard.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>And the foundation was laid with very large, expensive stones; some stones measured ten cubits, and other stones, eight cubits. <span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And above these were expensive stones, hewn according to measure, as well as cedar. <span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Around the great courtyard were three rows of hewn stone and a row of cedar beams, like that for the inner courtyard<a class='mr'></a> of the house of Jehovah and the porch of the house.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon sent for Hi′ram<a class='mr'></a> and brought him from Tyre. <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>He was the son of a widow from the tribe of Naph′ta·li, and his father was a Tyr′i·an coppersmith;<a class='mr'></a> and he had great skill, understanding,<a class='mr'></a> and experience for all kinds of work in copper.<a class='fn'></a> So he came to King Sol′o·mon and did all his work.</p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He cast the two pillars of copper;<a class='mr'></a> each pillar was 18 cubits high, and it took a measuring cord 12 cubits long to encircle each of the two pillars.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And he made two capitals cast in copper to put on the tops of the pillars. One capital was five cubits high, and the other capital was five cubits high. <span id='dcv_7_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>The capital on top of each pillar had mesh network with wreathed chains;<a class='mr'></a> seven for the one capital and seven for the other capital. <span id='dcv_7_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>And he made pomegranates in two rows around the one network to cover the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; he did the same for both capitals. <span id='dcv_7_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>The capitals on top of the pillars at the porch were of a lily pattern four cubits high. <span id='dcv_7_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>The capitals were on the two pillars, just above the rounded portion adjoining the network; and there were 200 pomegranates in rows all around on each capital.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>He set up the pillars of the porch of the temple.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> He set up the right-hand<a class='fn'></a> pillar and named it Ja′chin,<a class='fn'></a> and then he set up the left-hand<a class='fn'></a> pillar and named it Bo′az.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And the top of the pillars were of a lily pattern. So the work of the pillars was completed.</p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Then he made the Sea<a class='fn'></a> of cast metal.<a class='mr'></a> It was circular in shape, 10 cubits from brim to brim and 5 cubits high, and it took a measuring line 30 cubits long to encircle it.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>And there were ornamental gourds<a class='mr'></a> below its brim, completely encircling it, ten to a cubit all around the Sea, with two rows of the gourds cast in one piece with it. <span id='dcv_7_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>It stood on 12 bulls,<a class='mr'></a> 3 facing north, 3 facing west, 3 facing south, and 3 facing east; and the Sea rested on them, and all their hindquarters were toward the center. <span id='dcv_7_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>And its thickness was a handbreadth;<a class='fn'></a> and its brim was made like the brim of a cup, like a lily blossom. It would hold 2,000 bath measures.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Then he made the ten carriages<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> of copper. Each carriage was four cubits long, four cubits wide, and three cubits high. <span id='dcv_7_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>And this was how the carriages were constructed: They had side panels, and the side panels were between the crossbars. <span id='dcv_7_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>And on the side panels between the crossbars were lions,<a class='mr'></a> bulls, and cherubs,<a class='mr'></a> and the same design was above the crossbars. Above and beneath the lions and the bulls were wreaths in relief. <span id='dcv_7_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>And each carriage had four copper wheels and copper axles, and its four cornerpieces served as supports for them. Beneath the basin were the supports, cast with wreaths at the side of each. <span id='dcv_7_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Its opening was inside the crown, extending upward one cubit; and its opening was round, making up a stand of one and a half cubits, and on its mouth were engravings. And their side panels were square, not round. <span id='dcv_7_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>The four wheels were below the side panels, and the supports of the wheels were attached to the carriage, and the height of each wheel was one and a half cubits. <span id='dcv_7_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>And the wheels were made like chariot wheels. Their supports, rims,<a class='fn'></a> spokes, and hubs were all of cast metal. <span id='dcv_7_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>There were four supports on the four corners of each carriage; its supports were cast as part of<a class='fn'></a> the carriage. <span id='dcv_7_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>On top of the carriage was a circular band half a cubit high, and on the top of the carriage, its framing pieces and its side panels were cast as part of<a class='fn'></a> it. <span id='dcv_7_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>On the surfaces of its framing pieces and on its side panels he engraved cherubs, lions, and palm trees according to the amount of space on each, with wreaths all around.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>This is how he made the ten carriages;<a class='mr'></a> they were all cast alike,<a class='mr'></a> with the same measure and shape.</p></div><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>He made ten copper basins;<a class='mr'></a> each could hold 40 bath measures. Each basin measured four cubits.<a class='fn'></a> There was one basin for each of the ten carriages. <span id='dcv_7_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>Then he put five carriages on the right side of the house and five on the left side of the house, and he placed the Sea on the right side of the house, toward the southeast.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>Hi′ram<a class='mr'></a> also made the basins, the shovels,<a class='mr'></a> and the bowls.<a class='mr'></a> So Hi′ram finished all the work that he did for King Sol′o·mon on the house of Jehovah:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>the two pillars<a class='mr'></a> and the bowl-shaped capitals that were on top of the two pillars; the two networks<a class='mr'></a> to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were on top of the pillars; <span id='dcv_7_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>the 400 pomegranates<a class='mr'></a> for the two networks, two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were on the two pillars; <span id='dcv_7_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>the ten carriages<a class='mr'></a> and the ten basins<a class='mr'></a> on the carriages; <span id='dcv_7_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>the Sea<a class='mr'></a> and the 12 bulls beneath the Sea; <span id='dcv_7_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>and the cans, the shovels, the bowls, and all the utensils, which Hi′ram made of polished copper for King Sol′o·mon for the house of Jehovah. <span id='dcv_7_46' class='dv dx dp'><a>46 </a></span>The king cast them in clay molds in the district of the Jordan, between Suc′coth and Zar′e·than.</p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>Sol′o·mon left all the utensils unweighed because they were in such great quantities. The weight of the copper was not ascertained.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>Sol′o·mon made all the utensils for the house of Jehovah: the altar<a class='mr'></a> of gold; the gold table<a class='mr'></a> on which to put the showbread; <span id='dcv_7_49' class='dv dp'><a>49 </a></span>the lampstands<a class='mr'></a> of pure gold, five on the right and five on the left before the innermost room; and the blossoms,<a class='mr'></a> the lamps, and the snuffers,<a class='fn'></a> of gold;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_50' class='dv dx dp'><a>50 </a></span>the basins, the extinguishers,<a class='mr'></a> the bowls, the cups,<a class='mr'></a> and the fire holders,<a class='mr'></a> of pure gold; and the sockets for the doors of the inner house,<a class='mr'></a> that is, the Most Holy, and for the doors of the house of the temple,<a class='mr'></a> of gold.</p></div><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_51' class='dv dp'><a>51 </a></span>So King Sol′o·mon completed all the work he had to do for the house of Jehovah. Sol′o·mon then brought in the things that David his father had made holy,<a class='mr'></a> and he put the silver, the gold, and the articles into the treasuries of the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>At that time Sol′o·mon congregated<a class='mr'></a> the elders of Israel, all the heads of the tribes, the chieftains of the paternal houses of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> They came to King Sol′o·mon at Jerusalem to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah from the City of David,<a class='mr'></a> that is, Zion.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>All the men of Israel assembled before King Sol′o·mon at the festival<a class='fn'></a> in the month of Eth′a·nim,<a class='fn'></a> that is, the seventh month.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>So all the elders of Israel came, and the priests lifted up the Ark.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>They brought up the Ark of Jehovah, the tent of meeting,<a class='mr'></a> and all the holy utensils that were in the tent. The priests and the Levites brought them up. <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon and the entire assembly of Israel, who had been summoned to meet with him, were before the Ark. So many sheep and cattle were being sacrificed<a class='mr'></a> that they could not be counted or numbered.</p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then the priests brought the ark of the covenant of Jehovah to its place,<a class='mr'></a> into the innermost room of the house, the Most Holy, underneath the wings of the cherubs.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Thus the wings of the cherubs were spread out over the place of the Ark, so that the cherubs overshadowed the Ark and its poles.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>The poles<a class='mr'></a> were so long that the tips of the poles were visible from the Holy in front of the innermost room, but they were not visible from outside. And they are there to this day. <span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>There was nothing in the Ark but the two stone tablets<a class='mr'></a> that Moses placed there<a class='mr'></a> at Ho′reb, when Jehovah made a covenant<a class='mr'></a> with the people of Israel while they were coming out of the land of Egypt.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>When the priests came out from the holy place, the cloud<a class='mr'></a> filled the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>The priests were not able to stand to minister because of the cloud, for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>At that time Sol′o·mon said: “Jehovah said he would reside in the thick gloom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>I have successfully built a lofty house for you, an established place for you to dwell in forever.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then the king turned around and began to bless all the congregation of Israel while all the congregation of Israel stood.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>He said: “May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, the one who by his own mouth promised my father David, and by his own hand has given fulfillment, saying, <span id='dcv_8_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>‘From the day I brought my people Israel out of Egypt, I have not chosen a city out of all the tribes of Israel in which to build a house for my name to remain there,<a class='mr'></a> but I have chosen David to be over my people Israel.’ <span id='dcv_8_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>And it was the heart’s desire of my father David to build a house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>But Jehovah said to my father David, ‘It was your heart’s desire to build a house for my name, and you did well to desire this in your heart. <span id='dcv_8_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>However, you will not build the house, but your own son who is to be born to you<a class='fn'></a> is the one who will build the house for my name.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Jehovah has carried out the promise that he made, for I have succeeded my father David and I sit on the throne of Israel, just as Jehovah promised. I have also built the house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>and have set up a place there for the Ark containing the covenant<a class='mr'></a> that Jehovah made with our forefathers when he was bringing them out of the land of Egypt.”</p></div><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Then Sol′o·mon stood before the altar of Jehovah in front of all the congregation of Israel, and he spread his hands out to the heavens,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>and he said: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, there is no God like you<a class='mr'></a> in the heavens above or on the earth beneath, keeping the covenant and showing loyal love<a class='mr'></a> to your servants who are walking before you with all their heart.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>You have kept the promise that you made to your servant David my father. You made the promise with your own mouth, and this day you have fulfilled it with your own hand.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>And now, O Jehovah the God of Israel, keep the promise you made to your servant David my father when you said: ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line before me to sit on the throne of Israel, if only your sons will pay attention to their way by walking before me, just as you have walked before me.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>And now, O God of Israel, let the promise that you made to your servant David my father prove trustworthy, please.</p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>“But will God really dwell on the earth?<a class='mr'></a> Look! The heavens, yes, the heaven of the heavens, cannot contain you;<a class='mr'></a> how much less, then, this house that I have built!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Now pay attention to the prayer of your servant and to his request for favor, O Jehovah my God, and listen to the cry for help and to the prayer that your servant is praying before you today. <span id='dcv_8_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>May your eyes be open toward this house night and day, toward the place of which you said, ‘My name will be there,’<a class='mr'></a> to listen to the prayer that your servant prays toward this place.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>And listen to your servant’s request for favor and to the request by your people Israel that they pray toward this place, and may you hear from your dwelling place in the heavens;<a class='mr'></a> yes, may you hear and forgive.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>“When a man sins against his fellow man and is made to take an oath<a class='fn'></a> and is brought under liability to the oath,<a class='fn'></a> and while under the oath<a class='fn'></a> he comes before your altar in this house,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>may you then hear from the heavens and act and judge your servants by pronouncing the wicked one guilty<a class='fn'></a> and bringing what he did on his own head, and by pronouncing the righteous one innocent<a class='fn'></a> and rewarding him according to his own righteousness.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>“When your people Israel are defeated by an enemy because they kept sinning against you,<a class='mr'></a> and they return to you and glorify your name<a class='mr'></a> and pray and beg you for favor in this house,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>may you then hear from the heavens and forgive the sin of your people Israel and bring them back to the land that you gave to their forefathers.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>“When the heavens are shut up and there is no rain<a class='mr'></a> because they kept sinning against you,<a class='mr'></a> and they pray toward this place and glorify your name and turn back from their sin because you humbled<a class='fn'></a> them,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>may you then hear from the heavens and forgive the sin of your servants, of your people Israel, for you will instruct them<a class='mr'></a> about the good way in which they should walk; and bring rain on your land<a class='mr'></a> that you gave to your people as an inheritance.</p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>“If a famine occurs in the land,<a class='mr'></a> or a pestilence, a scorching blight, mildew,<a class='mr'></a> swarming locusts, or voracious locusts;<a class='fn'></a> or if their enemy besieges them in any of the cities of the land<a class='fn'></a> or if any other sort of plague or disease occurs,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>whatever prayer, whatever request for favor<a class='mr'></a> may be made by any man or by all your people Israel (for each one knows the plague of his own heart)<a class='mr'></a> when they spread out their hands toward this house, <span id='dcv_8_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>then may you hear from the heavens, your dwelling place,<a class='mr'></a> and may you forgive<a class='mr'></a> and take action; and reward each one according to all his ways,<a class='mr'></a> for you know his heart (you alone truly know every human heart),<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>so that they may fear you all the days they live on the land that you gave to our forefathers.</p></div><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>“Also concerning the foreigner who is not part of your people Israel and who comes from a distant land because of your name<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>(for they will hear about your great name<a class='mr'></a> and your mighty hand and your outstretched arm), and he comes and prays toward this house, <span id='dcv_8_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>may you then listen from the heavens, your dwelling place,<a class='mr'></a> and do all that the foreigner asks of you, so that all the peoples of the earth may know your name and fear you,<a class='mr'></a> as your people Israel do, and may know that your name has been called on this house that I have built.</p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>“If your people go to war against their enemy in the way that you send them,<a class='mr'></a> and they pray<a class='mr'></a> to Jehovah in the direction of the city that you have chosen<a class='mr'></a> and toward the house that I have built for your name,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>then hear from the heavens their prayer and their request for favor and execute judgment for them.</p></div><div id='p82' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>“If they sin against you (for there is no man who does not sin),<a class='mr'></a> and you are furious with them and you abandon them to an enemy, and their captors carry them off captive to the land of the enemy, far or near;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>and they come to their senses in the land where they were carried off captive,<a class='mr'></a> and they return to you<a class='mr'></a> and beg you for favor in the land of their captors,<a class='mr'></a> saying, ‘We have sinned and done wrong; we have acted wickedly,’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>and they return to you with all their heart<a class='mr'></a> and all their soul<a class='fn'></a> in the land of their enemies who carried them off captive, and they pray to you in the direction of their land that you gave to their forefathers and of the city that you have chosen and the house that I have built for your name,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_49' class='dv dp'><a>49 </a></span>then hear from the heavens, your dwelling place,<a class='mr'></a> their prayer and their request for favor, and execute judgment for them <span id='dcv_8_50' class='dv dx dp'><a>50 </a></span>and forgive your people who have sinned against you, forgiving all their transgressions they committed against you. You will make them objects of pity before their captors, and they will pity them<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_51' class='dv dp'><a>51 </a></span>(for they are your people and your inheritance,<a class='mr'></a> whom you brought out of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> from inside the iron-smelting furnace).<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_52' class='dv dp'><a>52 </a></span>May your eyes be opened to your servant’s request for favor<a class='mr'></a> and to the request for favor by your people Israel by listening whenever they call to you.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_53' class='dv dp'><a>53 </a></span>For you set them apart as your inheritance out of all the peoples of the earth,<a class='mr'></a> just as you declared through Moses your servant when you were bringing our forefathers out of Egypt, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”</p></div><div id='p83' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_54' class='dv dp'><a>54 </a></span>And as soon as Sol′o·mon finished offering to Jehovah this entire prayer and request for favor, he rose up from before the altar of Jehovah, where he had been kneeling with his hands spread out to the heavens.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_55' class='dv dp'><a>55 </a></span>He then stood and blessed all the congregation of Israel with a loud voice, saying: <span id='dcv_8_56' class='dv dp'><a>56 </a></span>“Praised be Jehovah, who has given a resting-place to his people Israel, just as he promised.<a class='mr'></a> Not one word of all his good promise that he made through Moses his servant has failed.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_57' class='dv dp'><a>57 </a></span>May Jehovah our God be with us just as he was with our forefathers.<a class='mr'></a> May he not abandon us nor forsake us.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_58' class='dv dp'><a>58 </a></span>May he draw our heart toward himself,<a class='mr'></a> to walk in all his ways and to keep his commandments, his regulations, and his judgments, which he commanded our forefathers to observe. <span id='dcv_8_59' class='dv dp'><a>59 </a></span>And may these words of mine with which I have begged Jehovah for favor be near to Jehovah our God by day and night, that he may execute judgment for his servant and for his people Israel as each day requires, <span id='dcv_8_60' class='dv dp'><a>60 </a></span>so that all the peoples of the earth may know that Jehovah is the true God.<a class='mr'></a> There is no other!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_61' class='dv dp'><a>61 </a></span>So let your heart be complete<a class='mr'></a> with<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah our God by walking in his regulations and by keeping his commandments as on this day.”</p></div><div id='p84' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_62' class='dv dp'><a>62 </a></span>Now the king and all Israel with him offered a grand sacrifice before Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_63' class='dv dp'><a>63 </a></span>Sol′o·mon offered the communion sacrifices<a class='mr'></a> to Jehovah: He offered 22,000 cattle and 120,000 sheep. Thus the king and all the Israelites inaugurated the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_64' class='dv dx dp'><a>64 </a></span>On that day the king had to sanctify the middle of the courtyard that is before the house of Jehovah, for there he had to offer up the burnt sacrifices, the grain offerings, and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices, because the copper altar<a class='mr'></a> that is before Jehovah was too small to contain the burnt sacrifices, the grain offerings, and the fat<a class='mr'></a> pieces of the communion sacrifices. <span id='dcv_8_65' class='dv dx dp'><a>65 </a></span>At that time Sol′o·mon held the festival<a class='mr'></a> together with all Israel, a great congregation from Le′bo-ha′math<a class='fn'></a> down to the Wadi<a class='fn'></a> of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> before Jehovah our God for 7 days and then another 7 days, 14 days in all. <span id='dcv_8_66' class='dv dp'><a>66 </a></span>On the following<a class='fn'></a> day, he sent the people away, and they blessed the king and went to their homes rejoicing and feeling glad of heart over all the goodness<a class='mr'></a> that Jehovah had shown to David his servant and Israel his people.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p85' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dp'><a>9 </a></span>As soon as Sol′o·mon had finished building the house of Jehovah, the house<a class='fn'></a> of the king,<a class='mr'></a> and everything Sol′o·mon desired to make,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Jehovah appeared to Sol′o·mon a second time, just as he had appeared to him in Gib′e·on.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Jehovah said to him: “I have heard your prayer and your request for favor that you made before me. I have sanctified this house that you built by permanently putting my name there,<a class='mr'></a> and my eyes and my heart will always be there.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>And you, if you walk before me as your father David walked,<a class='mr'></a> with integrity of heart<a class='mr'></a> and with uprightness,<a class='mr'></a> by doing everything I have commanded you,<a class='mr'></a> and you obey my regulations and my judgments,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>then I will establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel forever, just as I promised your father David, saying, ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line sitting on the throne of Israel.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But if you and your sons turn away from following me and do not keep my commandments and my statutes that I have put before you, and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>I will cut Israel off from the surface of the land that I have given to them,<a class='mr'></a> and the house that I have sanctified for my name I will cast out of my sight,<a class='mr'></a> and Israel will become an object of scorn<a class='fn'></a> and a cause for ridicule among all the peoples.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>And this house will become heaps of ruins.<a class='mr'></a> Everyone passing by it will stare in amazement and will whistle and say, ‘Why did Jehovah do that to this land and this house?’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then they will say, ‘It was because they abandoned Jehovah their God, who had brought their forefathers out of the land of Egypt, and they embraced other gods and bowed down to them and served them. That is why Jehovah brought all this calamity on them.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p86' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>At the end of 20 years, during which Sol′o·mon built the two houses, the house of Jehovah and the house<a class='fn'></a> of the king,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Hi′ram<a class='mr'></a> the king of Tyre had supplied Sol′o·mon with cedar and juniper timbers and with as much gold as he desired,<a class='mr'></a> and King Sol′o·mon gave to Hi′ram 20 cities in the land of Gal′i·lee. <span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>So Hi′ram went out from Tyre to see the cities that Sol′o·mon had given him, but he was not satisfied with them.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>He said: “What sort of cities are these that you have given me, my brother?” So they came to be called the Land of Ca′bul<a class='fn'></a> down to this day. <span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>In the meantime, Hi′ram sent to the king 120 talents<a class='fn'></a> of gold.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p87' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>This is the account of those whom King Sol′o·mon conscripted for forced labor<a class='mr'></a> to build the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> his own house,<a class='fn'></a> the Mound,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the wall of Jerusalem, Ha′zor,<a class='mr'></a> Me·gid′do,<a class='mr'></a> and Ge′zer.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>(Phar′aoh king of Egypt had come up and captured Ge′zer and had burned it with fire, and he had also killed the Ca′naan·ites<a class='mr'></a> dwelling in the city. So he gave it as a parting gift<a class='fn'></a> to his daughter,<a class='mr'></a> the wife of Sol′o·mon.) <span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Sol′o·mon built up<a class='fn'></a> Ge′zer, Lower Beth-ho′ron,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Ba′al·ath,<a class='mr'></a> and Ta′mar in the wilderness, within the land, <span id='dcv_9_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>as well as all of Sol′o·mon’s storage cities, the chariot cities,<a class='mr'></a> the cities for the horsemen, and whatever Sol′o·mon desired to build in Jerusalem, in Leb′a·non, and in all the land of his dominion. <span id='dcv_9_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>As for all the people who were left from the Am′or·ites, the Hit′tites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites, and the Jeb′u·sites,<a class='mr'></a> who were not part of the people of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>their descendants who were left in the land—those whom the Israelites had been unable to devote to destruction—were conscripted by Sol′o·mon for forced labor as slaves until this day.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>But Sol′o·mon did not make any of the Israelites slaves,<a class='mr'></a> for they were his warriors, servants, princes, adjutants, and the chiefs of his charioteers and horsemen. <span id='dcv_9_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>There were 550 chiefs of the deputies who were over the work of Sol′o·mon, the foremen over the people who were doing the work.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p88' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>But Phar′aoh’s daughter<a class='mr'></a> came up from the City of David<a class='mr'></a> to her own house that he had built for her; then he built the Mound.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p89' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Three times a year<a class='mr'></a> Sol′o·mon offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices on the altar that he had built for Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> also making sacrificial smoke on the altar, which was before Jehovah, so he completed the house.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p90' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon also made a fleet of ships in E′zi·on-ge′ber,<a class='mr'></a> which is by E′loth, on the shore of the Red Sea in the land of E′dom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Hi′ram sent his own servants with the fleet of ships,<a class='mr'></a> experienced seamen, to serve along with the servants of Sol′o·mon. <span id='dcv_9_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>They went to O′phir<a class='mr'></a> and took from there 420 talents of gold and brought it to King Sol′o·mon.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p91' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now the queen of She′ba heard the report about Sol′o·mon in connection with the name of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> so she came to test him with perplexing questions.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>She arrived in Jerusalem with a very impressive entourage,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> with camels carrying balsam oil<a class='mr'></a> and great quantities of gold and precious stones. She went in to Sol′o·mon and spoke to him about everything that was close to her heart. <span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Sol′o·mon then answered all her questions. There was nothing too difficult for<a class='fn'></a> the king to explain to her.</p></div><div id='p92' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>When the queen of She′ba had seen all the wisdom of Sol′o·mon,<a class='mr'></a> the house that he built,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>the food of his table,<a class='mr'></a> the seating of his servants, the table service of his waiters and their attire, his cupbearers, and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, she was left completely breathless.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So she said to the king: “The report that I heard in my own land about your achievements<a class='fn'></a> and about your wisdom was true. <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But I did not put faith in the reports until I had come and had seen it with my own eyes. And look! I had not been told the half. You have far surpassed in wisdom and prosperity the report that I heard. <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Happy are your men, and happy are your servants who stand before you constantly, listening to your wisdom!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>May Jehovah your God be praised,<a class='mr'></a> who has taken pleasure in you by putting you on the throne of Israel. Because of Jehovah’s everlasting love for Israel, he appointed you as king to administer justice and righteousness.”</p></div><div id='p93' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then she gave the king 120 talents<a class='fn'></a> of gold and a great amount of balsam oil<a class='mr'></a> and precious stones.<a class='mr'></a> Never again was such a quantity of balsam oil brought in as what the queen of She′ba gave to King Sol′o·mon.</p></div><div id='p94' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Hi′ram’s fleet of ships that carried gold from O′phir<a class='mr'></a> also brought from O′phir algum timbers<a class='mr'></a> in very great quantity, and precious stones.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>The king made from the algum timbers supports for the house of Jehovah and for the king’s house,<a class='fn'></a> as well as harps and stringed instruments for the singers.<a class='mr'></a> Such algum timbers have never again been brought in or seen down to this day.</p></div><div id='p95' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon also gave the queen of She′ba whatever she desired and asked for, in addition to what he gave her out of his own generosity.<a class='fn'></a> After that she left and returned to her own land, together with her servants.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p96' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>And the weight of the gold that came to Sol′o·mon in one year amounted to 666 talents of gold,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>besides that from the merchants and the profit from the traders and from all the kings of the Arabs and the governors of the land.</p></div><div id='p97' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>King Sol′o·mon made 200 large shields of alloyed gold<a class='mr'></a> (600 shekels<a class='fn'></a> of gold went on each shield)<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>and 300 bucklers<a class='fn'></a> of alloyed gold (three mi′nas<a class='fn'></a> of gold went on each buckler). Then the king put them in the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p98' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>The king also made a great ivory throne<a class='mr'></a> and overlaid it with refined gold.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>There were six steps to the throne, and the throne had a round canopy behind it, and there were armrests on both sides of the seat, and two lions<a class='mr'></a> were standing beside the armrests. <span id='dcv_10_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>And there were 12 lions standing on the six steps, one at each end of the six steps. No other kingdom had made anything like it.</p></div><div id='p99' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>All the drinking vessels of King Sol′o·mon were of gold, and all the utensils of the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non<a class='mr'></a> were of pure gold. There was nothing made of silver, for silver was considered as nothing in the days of Sol′o·mon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>For the king had a fleet of ships of Tar′shish<a class='mr'></a> on the sea along with Hi′ram’s fleet. Once every three years, the fleet of ships of Tar′shish would come loaded with gold and silver, ivory,<a class='mr'></a> apes, and peacocks.</p></div><div id='p100' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So King Sol′o·mon was greater than all the other kings of the earth in riches<a class='mr'></a> and wisdom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>And people of all the earth sought an audience with<a class='fn'></a> Sol′o·mon to hear his wisdom that God had put in his heart.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>They would each bring a gift—articles of silver, articles of gold, garments, armor, balsam oil, horses, and mules—and this continued year after year.</p></div><div id='p101' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>And Sol′o·mon kept accumulating chariots and horses;<a class='fn'></a> he had 1,400 chariots and 12,000 horses,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p102' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>The king made the silver in Jerusalem as plentiful as the stones, and cedarwood as plentiful as the sycamore trees in the She·phe′lah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p103' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>The horses of Sol′o·mon had been imported from Egypt, and the company of the king’s merchants would obtain the horses in droves<a class='fn'></a> for one price.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Each chariot imported from Egypt cost 600 silver pieces, and a horse cost 150; in turn, they would export them to all the kings of the Hit′tites<a class='mr'></a> and the kings of Syria.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p104' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But King Sol′o·mon loved many foreign women<a class='mr'></a> besides the daughter of Phar′aoh:<a class='mr'></a> Mo′ab·ite,<a class='mr'></a> Am′mon·ite,<a class='mr'></a> E′dom·ite, Si·do′ni·an,<a class='mr'></a> and Hit′tite<a class='mr'></a> women. <span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>They were from the nations about whom Jehovah had said to the Israelites: “You must not go in among them,<a class='fn'></a> and they should not come in among you, for they will surely incline your heart to follow their gods.”<a class='mr'></a> But Sol′o·mon clung to them and loved them. <span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>And he had 700 wives who were princesses and 300 concubines, and his wives gradually inclined his heart.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>In Sol′o·mon’s old age,<a class='mr'></a> his wives inclined<a class='fn'></a> his heart to follow other gods,<a class='mr'></a> and his heart was not complete with<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah his God like the heart of David his father. <span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And Sol′o·mon followed after Ash′to·reth,<a class='mr'></a> the goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans, and Mil′com,<a class='mr'></a> the disgusting god of the Am′mon·ites. <span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>And Sol′o·mon did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not follow Jehovah completely<a class='fn'></a> as David his father had done.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p105' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>It was then that Sol′o·mon built a high place<a class='mr'></a> to Che′mosh, the disgusting god of Mo′ab, on the mountain in front of Jerusalem and to Mo′lech,<a class='mr'></a> the disgusting god of the Am′mon·ites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>That was what he did for all his foreign wives who were making sacrificial smoke and sacrificing to their gods.</p></div><div id='p106' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Jehovah became furious at Sol′o·mon, because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah the God of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> who had appeared to him twice<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>and had warned him about this very thing, that he should not go after other gods.<a class='mr'></a> But he did not obey what Jehovah had commanded. <span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Jehovah now said to Sol′o·mon: “Because you have done this and you have not kept my covenant and my statutes as I commanded you, I will surely rip the kingdom away from you, and I will give it to one of your servants.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>However, for the sake of your father David, I will not do it in your lifetime. I will rip it out of the hand of your son,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>but I will not rip away the entire kingdom.<a class='mr'></a> One tribe I will give to your son,<a class='mr'></a> for the sake of David my servant and for the sake of Jerusalem, which I have chosen.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p107' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Jehovah then raised up a resister against Sol′o·mon,<a class='mr'></a> Ha′dad the E′dom·ite, of the royal family of E′dom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>When David defeated E′dom,<a class='mr'></a> Jo′ab the chief of the army went up to bury the slain, and he tried to strike down every male in E′dom. <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>(For Jo′ab and all Israel stayed there for six months until he had done away with<a class='fn'></a> every male in E′dom.) <span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But Ha′dad fled with some of his father’s E′dom·ite servants, and they went to Egypt; Ha′dad was then a young boy. <span id='dcv_11_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So they set out from Mid′i·an and came to Pa′ran. They took men with them from Pa′ran<a class='mr'></a> and came to Egypt, to Phar′aoh king of Egypt, who gave him a house, assigned him a food allowance, and gave him land. <span id='dcv_11_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Ha′dad found favor in the eyes of Phar′aoh, so much so that he gave him in marriage the sister of his own wife, Tah′pe·nes the queen.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_11_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>In time the sister of Tah′pe·nes bore him a son, Ge·nu′bath, and Tah′pe·nes brought him up<a class='fn'></a> in the house of Phar′aoh, and Ge·nu′bath remained in the house of Phar′aoh among the sons of Phar′aoh.</p></div><div id='p108' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Ha′dad heard in Egypt that David had been laid to rest with his forefathers<a class='mr'></a> and that Jo′ab the chief of the army had died.<a class='mr'></a> So Ha′dad said to Phar′aoh: “Send me away, so that I may go to my own land.” <span id='dcv_11_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>But Phar′aoh said to him: “What have you lacked with me that you now seek to go to your own land?” To this he said: “Nothing, but please send me away.”</p></div><div id='p109' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>God also raised up against Sol′o·mon another resister,<a class='mr'></a> Re′zon the son of E·li′a·da, who had fled from his lord, Had·ad·e′zer<a class='mr'></a> the king of Zo′bah. <span id='dcv_11_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>He gathered men to himself and became chief of a marauder band when David defeated<a class='fn'></a> them.<a class='mr'></a> So they went to Damascus<a class='mr'></a> and settled there and began reigning in Damascus. <span id='dcv_11_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>And he became a resister of Israel all the days of Sol′o·mon, adding to the harm done by Ha′dad, and he abhorred Israel while he reigned over Syria.</p></div><div id='p110' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>And there was Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ne′bat, an E′phra·im·ite from Zer′e·dah, a servant of Sol′o·mon’s<a class='mr'></a> whose mother’s name was Ze·ru′ah, a widow. He too began to rebel<a class='fn'></a> against the king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>This is why he rebelled against the king: Sol′o·mon had built the Mound<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and had closed up the gap of the City of David his father.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Now this Jer·o·bo′am was a capable man. When Sol′o·mon saw that the young man was a hard worker, he made him overseer<a class='mr'></a> over all the compulsory service of the house of Joseph. <span id='dcv_11_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>During that time Jer·o·bo′am went out from Jerusalem, and the prophet A·hi′jah<a class='mr'></a> the Shi′lo·nite found him on the road. A·hi′jah was wearing a new garment, and the two of them were by themselves in the field. <span id='dcv_11_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>A·hi′jah took hold of the new garment he was wearing and ripped it into 12 pieces. <span id='dcv_11_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Then he said to Jer·o·bo′am:</p></div><div id='p111' class='par'><p class='sb'>“Take ten pieces for yourself, for this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Here I am ripping the kingdom out of the hand of Sol′o·mon, and I will give you ten tribes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>But one tribe will remain his<a class='mr'></a> for the sake of my servant David<a class='mr'></a> and for the sake of Jerusalem, the city I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>I will do this because they have left me<a class='mr'></a> and are bowing down to Ash′to·reth the goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans, to Che′mosh the god of Mo′ab, and to Mil′com the god of the Am′mon·ites, and they have not walked in my ways by doing what is right in my eyes and observing my statutes and my judgments as his father David did. <span id='dcv_11_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>But I will not take the entire kingdom out of his hand, and I will keep him as a chieftain for all the days of his life, for the sake of David my servant whom I chose,<a class='mr'></a> because he obeyed my commandments and my statutes. <span id='dcv_11_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>But I will take the kingship out of the hand of his son and give it to you, that is, ten tribes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>To his son I will give one tribe, so that David my servant may always have a lamp before me in Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> the city that I have chosen for myself as the place to put my name. <span id='dcv_11_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>I will take you, and you will reign over all that you desire,<a class='fn'></a> and you will become king over Israel. <span id='dcv_11_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>And if you obey all that I command you and walk in my ways and do what is right in my eyes by obeying my statutes and my commandments, just as David my servant did,<a class='mr'></a> I will also be with you. I will build you a lasting house, just as I have built for David,<a class='mr'></a> and I will give you Israel. <span id='dcv_11_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>And I will humiliate the offspring of David because of this,<a class='mr'></a> but not always.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p112' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>So Sol′o·mon tried to put Jer·o·bo′am to death, but Jer·o·bo′am fled to Egypt, to Shi′shak<a class='mr'></a> the king of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> and he remained in Egypt until Sol′o·mon’s death.</p></div><div id='p113' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Sol′o·mon, all that he did and his wisdom, is it not written in the book of the history of Sol′o·mon?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>The length<a class='fn'></a> of Sol′o·mon’s reign in Jerusalem over all Israel was 40 years. <span id='dcv_11_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>Then Sol′o·mon was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David his father; and his son Re·ho·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p114' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Re·ho·bo′am went to She′chem, for all Israel had come to She′chem<a class='mr'></a> to make him king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>As soon as Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat heard of it (he was still in Egypt because he had run off on account of King Sol′o·mon and was living in Egypt),<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>they sent for him. After that Jer·o·bo′am and all the congregation of Israel came to Re·ho·bo′am and said: <span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>“Your father made our yoke harsh.<a class='mr'></a> But if you make the harsh service of your father easier and you lighten the heavy<a class='fn'></a> yoke he put on us, we will serve you.”</p></div><div id='p115' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>At this he said to them: “Go away for three days; then return to me.” So the people went away.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>King Re·ho·bo′am then consulted with the older men<a class='fn'></a> who had served his father Sol′o·mon while he was alive, saying: “What advice would you give on how to reply to this people?” <span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>They answered him: “If today you would become a servant to this people and submit to their request and give them a favorable answer, they will always be your servants.”</p></div><div id='p116' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>However, he rejected the advice that the older men<a class='fn'></a> gave him, and he consulted with the young men who had grown up with him and who were now his attendants.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He asked them: “What advice do you offer on how we should reply to this people who have said to me, ‘Make the yoke your father put on us lighter’?” <span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>The young men who had grown up with him said to him: “This is what you should say to this people who have said to you, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but you should make it lighter for us’; this is what you should tell them, ‘My little finger will be thicker than my father’s hips. <span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>My father imposed a heavy yoke on you, but I will add to your yoke. My father punished you with whips, but I will punish you with scourges.’”</p></div><div id='p117' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Jer·o·bo′am and all the people came to Re·ho·bo′am on the third day, just as the king had said: “Return to me on the third day.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>But the king answered the people harshly, rejecting the advice that the older men<a class='fn'></a> had given him. <span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>He spoke to them according to the advice of the young men, saying: “My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to your yoke. My father punished you with whips, but I will punish you with scourges.” <span id='dcv_12_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>So the king did not listen to the people, for this turn of events was caused by Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> in order to carry out the word that Jehovah had spoken through A·hi′jah<a class='mr'></a> the Shi′lo·nite to Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat.</p></div><div id='p118' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>When all Israel saw that the king refused to listen to them, the people replied to the king: “What share do we have in David? We have no inheritance in the son of Jes′se. To your gods, O Israel. Now look after your own house, O David!” With that Israel returned to their homes.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But Re·ho·bo′am continued to reign over the Israelites living in the cities of Judah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p119' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then King Re·ho·bo′am sent A·do′ram,<a class='mr'></a> who was in charge of those conscripted for forced labor, but all Israel stoned him to death. King Re·ho·bo′am managed to mount his chariot to flee to Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>And the Israelites have been in revolt<a class='mr'></a> against the house of David down to this day.</p></div><div id='p120' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>As soon as all Israel heard that Jer·o·bo′am had returned, they summoned him to the assembly and made him king over all Israel.<a class='mr'></a> None of the people followed the house of David except the tribe of Judah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p121' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>When Re·ho·bo′am arrived in Jerusalem, he immediately congregated all the house of Judah and the tribe of Benjamin, 180,000 trained<a class='fn'></a> warriors, to fight against the house of Israel in order to restore the kingship to Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Then the word of the true God came to She·mai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the man of the true God, saying: <span id='dcv_12_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>“Say to Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon the king of Judah and to all the house of Judah and Benjamin and the rest of the people, <span id='dcv_12_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>‘This is what Jehovah says: “You must not go up and fight against your Israelite brothers. Each one of you must return to his house, for I have caused this to happen.”’”<a class='mr'></a> So they obeyed the word of Jehovah and went back home, as Jehovah had told them.</p></div><div id='p122' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Jer·o·bo′am then built up<a class='fn'></a> She′chem<a class='mr'></a> in the mountainous region of E′phra·im and lived there. From there he went out and built up<a class='fn'></a> Pe·nu′el.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>Jer·o·bo′am said in his heart: “Now the kingdom will return to the house of David.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>If this people continues to go up to offer sacrifices at the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> the heart of this people will also return to their lord, King Re·ho·bo′am of Judah. Yes, they will kill me and return to King Re·ho·bo′am of Judah.” <span id='dcv_12_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>After consultation, the king made two golden calves<a class='mr'></a> and said to the people: “It is too much for you to go up to Jerusalem. Here is your God, O Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Then he placed one in Beth′el,<a class='mr'></a> and the other he put in Dan.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>And this caused them to sin,<a class='mr'></a> and the people went as far as Dan to worship the one there.</p></div><div id='p123' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>And he made houses of worship on the high places and appointed priests from the people in general, those who were not Levites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>Jer·o·bo′am also established a festival in the eighth month, on the 15th day of the month, like the festival in Judah.<a class='mr'></a> On the altar that he made at Beth′el,<a class='mr'></a> he sacrificed to the calves he had made, and at Beth′el he assigned priests for the high places that he had made. <span id='dcv_12_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>And he began to make offerings on the altar that he had made at Beth′el on the 15th day in the eighth month, in the month that he had devised on his own; and he established a festival for the people of Israel, and he ascended the altar to make offerings and sacrificial smoke.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p124' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>By the word of Jehovah, a man of God<a class='mr'></a> came from Judah to Beth′el while Jer·o·bo′am was standing by the altar<a class='mr'></a> to make sacrificial smoke. <span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then he called out against the altar by the word of Jehovah and said: “O altar, altar! This is what Jehovah says: ‘Look! A son named Jo·si′ah<a class='mr'></a> will be born to the house of David! He will sacrifice on you the priests of the high places, those making sacrificial smoke on you, and he will burn human bones on you.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He gave a sign<a class='fn'></a> on that day, saying: “This is the sign<a class='fn'></a> that Jehovah has declared: Look! The altar will be ripped apart, and the ashes<a class='fn'></a> that are on it will be spilled out.”</p></div><div id='p125' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>As soon as the king heard the word that the man of the true God had called out against the altar at Beth′el, Jer·o·bo′am stretched out his hand from the altar and said: “Seize him!”<a class='mr'></a> Immediately, the hand that he had stretched out against him dried up,<a class='fn'></a> and he could not draw it back.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then the altar was ripped apart and the ashes were spilled out from the altar according to the sign<a class='fn'></a> that the man of the true God had given by the word of Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p126' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The king now said to the man of the true God: “Please, beg for the favor<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah your God, and pray in my behalf that my hand may be restored to me.”<a class='mr'></a> At this the man of the true God begged for the favor of Jehovah, and the king’s hand was restored to its former condition. <span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>The king then said to the man of the true God: “Come home with me and take some food, and let me give you a gift.” <span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>But the man of the true God said to the king: “Even if you gave me half your house, I would not come with you and eat bread or drink water in this place. <span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>For this is what I was commanded by the word of Jehovah: ‘You must not eat bread or drink water, and you must not return by the way you came.’” <span id='dcv_13_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So he left by another way, and he did not return by the way he had come to Beth′el.</p></div><div id='p127' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>There was a certain old prophet dwelling in Beth′el, and his sons came home and related to him all the things that the man of the true God had done that day in Beth′el and the words he had spoken to the king. After they related this to their father, <span id='dcv_13_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>their father asked them: “Which way did he go?” So his sons showed him the way that the man of the true God from Judah had gone. <span id='dcv_13_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>He now said to his sons: “Saddle the donkey for me.” They saddled the donkey for him, and he mounted it.</p></div><div id='p128' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>He followed the man of the true God and found him sitting under a big tree. Then he said to him: “Are you the man of the true God who came from Judah?”<a class='mr'></a> He replied: “I am.” <span id='dcv_13_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>He said to him: “Come home with me and eat bread.” <span id='dcv_13_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>But he said: “I cannot go back with you or accept your invitation, nor may I eat bread or drink water with you in this place. <span id='dcv_13_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>For I was told by the word of Jehovah, ‘You must not eat bread or drink water there. You must not return by the way you came.’” <span id='dcv_13_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>At this he said to him: “I too am a prophet like you, and an angel told me by the word of Jehovah, ‘Have him come back with you to your house so that he may eat bread and drink water.’” (He deceived him.) <span id='dcv_13_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So he went back with him to eat bread and drink water in his house.</p></div><div id='p129' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>While they were sitting at the table, the word of Jehovah came to the prophet who had brought him back, <span id='dcv_13_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>and he called out to the man of the true God from Judah, saying, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Because you rebelled against the order of Jehovah and did not keep the commandment that Jehovah your God gave you, <span id='dcv_13_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>but you went back to eat bread and drink water in the place about which you were told, “Do not eat bread or drink water,” your dead body will not come into the tomb of your forefathers.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p130' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>After the man of the true God ate bread and drank, the old prophet saddled the donkey for the prophet whom he had brought back. <span id='dcv_13_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Then he got on his way, but a lion came across him on the road and killed him.<a class='mr'></a> His dead body was thrown onto the road, and the donkey stood beside it; the lion was also standing beside the dead body. <span id='dcv_13_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>There were men passing by who saw the dead body thrown onto the road and the lion standing beside the dead body. They came in and told about it in the city where the old prophet lived.</p></div><div id='p131' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>When the prophet who had brought him back from the road heard of it, he immediately said: “It is the man of the true God who rebelled against the order of Jehovah;<a class='mr'></a> so Jehovah gave him over to the lion, to maul and to kill him, according to the word of Jehovah that he spoke to him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>He then said to his sons: “Saddle the donkey for me.” So they saddled it. <span id='dcv_13_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then he went on his way and found the dead body thrown onto the road, with the donkey and the lion standing beside it. The lion had not eaten the dead body, nor had it mauled the donkey. <span id='dcv_13_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>The prophet lifted up the dead body of the man of the true God and put him on the donkey, and he brought him back into his own city to mourn and bury him. <span id='dcv_13_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So he laid the dead body in his own tomb, and they kept crying out over him: “Too bad, my brother!” <span id='dcv_13_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>After burying him, he told his sons: “When I die, you must bury me in the place where the man of the true God is buried. Lay my bones next to his bones.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>The word that he called out by the word of Jehovah against the altar in Beth′el and against all the houses of worship on the high places<a class='mr'></a> in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a is sure to take place.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p132' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Even after this happened, Jer·o·bo′am did not turn back from his bad way, but he kept appointing priests for the high places from the people in general.<a class='mr'></a> He would install as priests<a class='fn'></a> anyone who so desired, saying: “Let him become one of the priests for the high places.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>This sin on the part of the household of Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> led to their destruction and annihilation from the face of the earth.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="14"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p133' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_1' class='dc dp'><a>14 </a></span>At that time A·bi′jah the son of Jer·o·bo′am fell sick. <span id='dcv_14_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>So Jer·o·bo′am said to his wife: “Rise up, please, and disguise yourself so that they will not know that you are Jer·o·bo′am’s wife, and go to Shi′loh. Look! A·hi′jah the prophet is there. He is the one who spoke of me becoming king over this people.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Take with you ten loaves of bread, sprinkled cakes, and a flask of honey, and go to him. He will then tell you what is going to happen to the boy.”</p></div><div id='p134' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Jer·o·bo′am’s wife did what he said. She rose up and went to Shi′loh<a class='mr'></a> and came to the house of A·hi′jah. A·hi′jah’s eyes stared straight ahead, and he could not see because of his age.</p></div><div id='p135' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But Jehovah had told A·hi′jah: “Here is the wife of Jer·o·bo′am coming to inquire of you regarding her son, for he is sick. I will tell you what to say to her.<a class='fn'></a> When she arrives, she will conceal her identity.”</p></div><div id='p136' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>As soon as A·hi′jah heard the sound of her footsteps as she was coming into the entrance, he said: “Come in, wife of Jer·o·bo′am. Why are you concealing your identity? I have been assigned to give you a harsh message. <span id='dcv_14_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Go, tell Jer·o·bo′am, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: “I raised you up from among your people to make you a leader over my people Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then I ripped the kingdom away from the house of David and gave it to you.<a class='mr'></a> But you have not become like my servant David, who kept my commandments and who walked after me with all his heart, doing only what was right in my eyes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>But you have done worse than all those who were prior to you, and you made for yourself another god and metal images<a class='fn'></a> to offend me,<a class='mr'></a> and it is I whom you have turned your back on.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>For that reason I am bringing calamity on the house of Jer·o·bo′am, and I will annihilate<a class='fn'></a> from Jer·o·bo′am every male,<a class='fn'></a> including the helpless and weak in Israel, and I will make a clean sweep of the house of Jer·o·bo′am,<a class='mr'></a> just as one clears away the dung until it is all gone! <span id='dcv_14_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Anyone belonging to Jer·o·bo′am who dies in the city, the dogs will eat; and anyone who dies in the field, the birds of the heavens will eat, for Jehovah has spoken it.”’</p></div><div id='p137' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>“Now rise up; go to your house. When you set foot in the city, the child will die. <span id='dcv_14_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>All Israel will mourn him and bury him, for he alone of Jer·o·bo′am’s family will be laid in a grave, because he is the only one of the house of Jer·o·bo′am in whom Jehovah the God of Israel has found something good. <span id='dcv_14_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Jehovah will raise up for himself a king over Israel who will do away with<a class='fn'></a> the house of Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> from that day forward, yes, even now. <span id='dcv_14_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Jehovah will strike Israel down like a reed that sways in the water, and he will uproot Israel off this good land that he gave to their forefathers,<a class='mr'></a> and he will scatter them beyond the River,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> because they made their sacred poles,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> offending Jehovah. <span id='dcv_14_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>And he will abandon Israel because of the sins that Jer·o·bo′am has committed and has caused Israel to commit.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p138' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>At that Jer·o·bo′am’s wife rose up and went on her way and came to Tir′zah. As she came to the threshold of the house, the boy died. <span id='dcv_14_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So they buried him, and all Israel mourned him, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servant A·hi′jah the prophet.</p></div><div id='p139' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>And the rest of the history of Jer·o·bo′am, how he waged war<a class='mr'></a> and how he reigned, is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. <span id='dcv_14_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>And the length<a class='fn'></a> of Jer·o·bo′am’s reign was 22 years, after which he was laid to rest with his forefathers;<a class='mr'></a> and his son Na′dab became king in his place.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p140' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Meanwhile, Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon had become king in Judah. Re·ho·bo′am was 41 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 17 years in Jerusalem, the city that Jehovah had chosen<a class='mr'></a> out of all the tribes of Israel as the place to put his name.<a class='mr'></a> The name of Re·ho·bo′am’s mother was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And Judah was doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> and by the sins they committed they provoked him more than their forefathers had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>They too kept building for themselves high places, sacred pillars, and sacred poles<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> on every high hill<a class='mr'></a> and under every luxuriant tree.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>There were also male temple prostitutes in the land.<a class='mr'></a> They acted according to all the detestable things of the nations that Jehovah had driven out before the Israelites.</p></div><div id='p141' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>In the fifth year of King Re·ho·bo′am, King Shi′shak<a class='mr'></a> of Egypt came up against Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>He took the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> He took everything, including all the gold shields that Sol′o·mon had made.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>So King Re·ho·bo′am made copper shields to replace them, and he entrusted them to the chiefs of the guard,<a class='fn'></a> who guarded the entrance of the king’s house. <span id='dcv_14_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Whenever the king came to the house of Jehovah, the guards would carry them, and then they would return them to the guard chamber.</p></div><div id='p142' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>And the rest of the history of Re·ho·bo′am, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>There was constant warfare between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Then Re·ho·bo′am was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David.<a class='mr'></a> His mother’s name was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess.<a class='mr'></a> And his son A·bi′jam<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="15"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p143' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_1' class='dc dp'><a>15 </a></span>In the 18th year of King Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ne′bat, A·bi′jam became king over Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He reigned for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ma′a·cah<a class='mr'></a> the granddaughter of A·bish′a·lom. <span id='dcv_15_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He went on walking in all the sins that his father committed prior to him, and his heart was not complete with<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah his God like the heart of David his forefather. <span id='dcv_15_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>However, on account of David,<a class='mr'></a> Jehovah his God gave him a lamp in Jerusalem<a class='mr'></a> by raising up his son after him and keeping Jerusalem in existence. <span id='dcv_15_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>For David did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not turn aside from anything that He had commanded him all the days of his life, except in the matter of U·ri′ah the Hit′tite.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>And there was warfare between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am all the days of his life.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p144' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of A·bi′jam, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah?<a class='mr'></a> There was also war between A·bi′jam and Jer·o·bo′am.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then A·bi′jam was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in the City of David; and his son A′sa<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p145' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>In the 20th year of King Jer·o·bo′am of Israel, A′sa began to reign over Judah. <span id='dcv_15_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>He reigned in Jerusalem for 41 years. His grandmother’s name was Ma′a·cah<a class='mr'></a> the granddaughter of A·bish′a·lom. <span id='dcv_15_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>A′sa did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> like David his forefather. <span id='dcv_15_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>He expelled the male temple prostitutes from the land<a class='mr'></a> and removed all the disgusting idols<a class='fn'></a> that his forefathers had made.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>He even removed Ma′a·cah<a class='mr'></a> his grandmother from her position as queen mother,<a class='fn'></a> because she had made an obscene idol for the worship of the sacred pole.<a class='fn'></a> A′sa cut down her obscene idol<a class='mr'></a> and burned it in the Kid′ron Valley.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>But the high places were not removed.<a class='mr'></a> Nevertheless, A′sa’s heart was complete with<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah all his life.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_15_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>And he brought the things that he and his father had made holy into the house of Jehovah—silver, gold, and various utensils.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p146' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>There was constant warfare between A′sa and Ba′a·sha<a class='mr'></a> the king of Israel. <span id='dcv_15_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>So King Ba′a·sha of Israel came up against Judah and began to build up<a class='fn'></a> Ra′mah<a class='mr'></a> to prevent anyone from going out or coming in to<a class='fn'></a> King A′sa of Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>At that A′sa took all the silver and the gold that were left in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah and the treasuries of the house<a class='fn'></a> of the king and handed them over to his servants. King A′sa then sent them to Ben-ha′dad the son of Tab·rim′mon the son of He′zi·on, the king of Syria,<a class='mr'></a> who was dwelling in Damascus, saying: <span id='dcv_15_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>“There is a treaty<a class='fn'></a> between me and you and between my father and your father. I am sending you a gift of silver and gold. Come, break your treaty<a class='fn'></a> with King Ba′a·sha of Israel, so that he will withdraw from me.” <span id='dcv_15_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Ben-ha′dad listened to King A′sa and sent the chiefs of his armies against the cities of Israel, and they struck down I′jon,<a class='mr'></a> Dan,<a class='mr'></a> A′bel-beth-ma′a·cah, all Chin′ne·reth, and all the land of Naph′ta·li. <span id='dcv_15_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>When Ba′a·sha heard of it, he immediately quit building<a class='fn'></a> Ra′mah and continued dwelling in Tir′zah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>King A′sa then summoned all Judah—no one was exempt—and they carried off the stones and timbers of Ra′mah that Ba′a·sha had been building with, and with them King A′sa built up<a class='fn'></a> Ge′ba<a class='mr'></a> in Benjamin, and Miz′pah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p147' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>As for all the rest of the history of A′sa, all his mightiness and all that he did and the cities that he built,<a class='fn'></a> is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? But in his old age he suffered from a disease in his feet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Then A′sa was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with them in the City of David his forefather; and his son Je·hosh′a·phat<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p148' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Na′dab<a class='mr'></a> the son of Jer·o·bo′am became king over Israel in the second year of King A′sa of Judah, and he reigned over Israel for two years. <span id='dcv_15_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>He kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and walked in the way of his father<a class='mr'></a> and in his sin that he caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah of the house of Is′sa·char conspired against him, and Ba′a·sha struck him down at Gib′be·thon,<a class='mr'></a> which belonged to the Phi·lis′tines, while Na′dab and all Israel were besieging Gib′be·thon. <span id='dcv_15_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>So Ba′a·sha put him to death in the third year of King A′sa of Judah and became king in his place. <span id='dcv_15_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>And as soon as he became king, he struck down all the house of Jer·o·bo′am. He did not let remain anyone breathing who belonged to Jer·o·bo′am; he had them annihilated according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servant A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>This was because of the sins that Jer·o·bo′am had committed and had caused Israel to commit and because he had greatly offended Jehovah the God of Israel. <span id='dcv_15_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Na′dab, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_15_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>And there was constant warfare between A′sa and King Ba′a·sha of Israel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p149' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>In the third year of King A′sa of Judah, Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah became king in Tir′zah over all Israel and reigned for 24 years.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>But he kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> and he walked in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and in his sin that he caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="16"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p150' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_1' class='dc dp'><a>16 </a></span>The word of Jehovah against Ba′a·sha then came to Je′hu<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ha·na′ni,<a class='mr'></a> saying: <span id='dcv_16_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“I raised you up out of the dust and made you leader over my people Israel,<a class='mr'></a> but you kept walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and caused my people Israel to sin so that they offended me with their sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>So I am making a clean sweep of Ba′a·sha and his house, and I will make his house like the house of Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ne′bat. <span id='dcv_16_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Anyone belonging to Ba′a·sha who dies in the city the dogs will eat; and anyone belonging to him who dies in the field the birds of the heavens will eat.”</p></div><div id='p151' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Ba′a·sha, what he did and his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_16_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then Ba′a·sha was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Tir′zah;<a class='mr'></a> and E′lah his son became king in his place. <span id='dcv_16_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Also through the prophet Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni, Jehovah’s word came against Ba′a·sha and his house, both because of all the badness that he committed in the eyes of Jehovah by offending him with the work of his hands, becoming like the house of Jer·o·bo′am, and also because of his striking him<a class='fn'></a> down.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p152' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>In the 26th year of King A′sa of Judah, E′lah the son of Ba′a·sha became king over Israel in Tir′zah, and he reigned for two years. <span id='dcv_16_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>His servant Zim′ri, the chief of half of his chariot forces, conspired against him while he was in Tir′zah drinking himself drunk at the house of Ar′za, who was over the household in Tir′zah. <span id='dcv_16_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Zim′ri came in and struck him down<a class='mr'></a> and put him to death in the 27th year of King A′sa of Judah, and he became king in his place. <span id='dcv_16_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>When he became king, as soon as he sat down on his throne, he struck down all the house of Ba′a·sha. He did not spare a single male,<a class='fn'></a> whether of his relatives<a class='fn'></a> or of his friends. <span id='dcv_16_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Thus Zim′ri annihilated the whole house of Ba′a·sha, according to the word that Jehovah had spoken against Ba′a·sha through Je′hu the prophet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>This was for all the sins that Ba′a·sha and his son E′lah had committed and the sins they had caused Israel to commit by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their worthless idols.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of E′lah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?</p></div><div id='p153' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>In the 27th year of King A′sa of Judah, Zim′ri became king for seven days in Tir′zah while the troops were camped against Gib′be·thon,<a class='mr'></a> which belonged to the Phi·lis′tines. <span id='dcv_16_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>In time the troops who were encamped heard it being said: “Zim′ri has conspired and has also struck down the king.” So all Israel made Om′ri,<a class='mr'></a> the chief of the army, king over Israel on that day in the camp. <span id='dcv_16_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Om′ri and all Israel with him went up from Gib′be·thon and laid siege to Tir′zah. <span id='dcv_16_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>When Zim′ri saw that the city had been captured, he went into the fortified tower of the king’s house<a class='fn'></a> and burned the house down over himself, and he died.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>This was for his own sins that he had committed by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah by walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and for the sin he had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Zim′ri and his conspiracy, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?</p></div><div id='p154' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>It was then that the people of Israel were divided into two factions. One part of the people became followers of Tib′ni the son of Gi′nath, wanting to make him king, and the other part followed Om′ri. <span id='dcv_16_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>But the people who were following Om′ri prevailed over the people following Tib′ni the son of Gi′nath. So Tib′ni died, and Om′ri became king.</p></div><div id='p155' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>In the 31st year of King A′sa of Judah, Om′ri became king over Israel, and he reigned for 12 years. In Tir′zah he reigned for six years. <span id='dcv_16_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>He bought the mountain of Sa·mar′i·a from She′mer for two talents<a class='fn'></a> of silver, and he built a city on the mountain. He named the city that he built Sa·mar′i·a,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> after She′mer the owner<a class='fn'></a> of the mountain. <span id='dcv_16_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Om′ri kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he was worse than all who were prior to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>He walked in all the ways of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat and in the sin he had caused Israel to commit by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their worthless idols.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Om′ri, what he did and his mighty exploits, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_16_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then Om′ri was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·mar′i·a; and his son A′hab<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p156' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>A′hab the son of Om′ri became king over Israel in the 38th year of King A′sa of Judah, and A′hab the son of Om′ri reigned over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a<a class='mr'></a> for 22 years. <span id='dcv_16_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>A′hab the son of Om′ri was worse in the eyes of Jehovah than all those who were prior to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>As if it were a trivial thing for him to walk in the sins of Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ne′bat, he also took as wife Jez′e·bel<a class='mr'></a> the daughter of Eth·ba′al, the king of the Si·do′ni·ans,<a class='mr'></a> and began to serve Ba′al<a class='mr'></a> and to bow down to him. <span id='dcv_16_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Further, he set up an altar to Ba′al at the house<a class='fn'></a> of Ba′al<a class='mr'></a> that he built in Sa·mar′i·a. <span id='dcv_16_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>A′hab also made the sacred pole.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> A′hab did more to offend Jehovah the God of Israel than all the kings of Israel prior to him.</p></div><div id='p157' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>In his days, Hi′el the Beth′el·ite rebuilt Jer′i·cho. At the cost of A·bi′ram his firstborn he laid its foundation, and at the cost of Se′gub his youngest he put up its doors, according to the word of Jehovah spoken through Joshua the son of Nun.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="17"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p158' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Now E·li′jah<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the Tish′bite, an inhabitant of Gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> said to A′hab: “As surely as Jehovah the God of Israel whom I serve<a class='fn'></a> is living, during these years there will be no dew or rain except by my word!”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p159' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The word of Jehovah came to him, saying: <span id='dcv_17_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>“Leave here, and turn eastward and hide at the Valley of Che′rith,<a class='fn'></a> east of the Jordan. <span id='dcv_17_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>You should drink from the stream, and I will command the ravens to supply you food there.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>He immediately went and did according to the word of Jehovah; he went and stayed by the Valley of Che′rith,<a class='fn'></a> east of the Jordan. <span id='dcv_17_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>And the ravens were bringing him bread and meat in the morning and bread and meat in the evening, and he drank from the stream.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But after some days, the stream ran dry,<a class='mr'></a> because there was no rain in the land.</p></div><div id='p160' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>The word of Jehovah then came to him: <span id='dcv_17_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>“Rise up, go to Zar′e·phath, which belongs to Si′don, and stay there. Look! I will command a widow there to supply you with food.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So he rose up and went to Zar′e·phath. When he came to the entrance of the city, there was a widow gathering pieces of wood. So he called to her and said: “Please, bring me a little water in a cup so that I may drink.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>As she went to get it, he called to her: “Please, bring me a piece of bread in your hand.” <span id='dcv_17_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>At this she said: “As surely as Jehovah your God is living, I have no bread, only a handful of flour in the large jar and a little oil in the small jar.<a class='mr'></a> Now I am gathering a few pieces of wood, and I will go in and make something for me and my son. After we have eaten, we will die.”</p></div><div id='p161' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then E·li′jah said to her: “Do not be afraid. Go in and do as you said. But first make me a small round loaf of bread with what is there, and bring it out to me. Then you can make something afterward for you and your son. <span id='dcv_17_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>For this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘The large jar of flour will not run out, and the small jar of oil will not run dry until the day Jehovah makes it rain on the surface of the ground.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>So she went and did as E·li′jah said, and she together with him and her household ate for many days.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>The large jar of flour did not run out, and the small jar of oil did not run dry, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through E·li′jah.</p></div><div id='p162' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>After these things, the son of the woman who owned the house fell sick, and his sickness became so severe that he stopped breathing.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>At this she said to E·li′jah: “What do you have against me,<a class='fn'></a> O man of the true God? Have you come to remind me of my guilt and to put my son to death?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>But he said to her: “Give me your son.” Then he took him from her arms and carried him up to the roof chamber, where he was staying, and he laid him on his own bed.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>He called out to Jehovah: “O Jehovah my God,<a class='mr'></a> are you also bringing harm to the widow with whom I am staying by putting her son to death?” <span id='dcv_17_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then he stretched himself out over the child three times and called out to Jehovah: “O Jehovah my God, please, let this child’s life<a class='fn'></a> come back into him.” <span id='dcv_17_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Jehovah listened to E·li′jah’s request,<a class='mr'></a> and the life<a class='fn'></a> of the child came back into him, and he revived.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>E·li′jah took the child and brought him down from the roof chamber into the house and gave him to his mother; and E·li′jah said: “See, your son is alive.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>At that the woman said to E·li′jah: “Now I know that you truly are a man of God<a class='mr'></a> and that Jehovah’s word in your mouth is truth.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="18"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p163' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>After some time, in the third year,<a class='mr'></a> Jehovah’s word came to E·li′jah, saying: “Go, present yourself to A′hab, and I will send rain on the surface of the ground.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>So E·li′jah went to present himself to A′hab, while the famine was severe<a class='mr'></a> in Sa·mar′i·a.</p></div><div id='p164' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Meanwhile, A′hab called O·ba·di′ah, who was over the household. (Now O·ba·di′ah greatly feared Jehovah, <span id='dcv_18_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>and when Jez′e·bel<a class='mr'></a> was doing away with<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah’s prophets, O·ba·di′ah took 100 prophets and hid them 50 to a cave, and he supplied them with bread and water.) <span id='dcv_18_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>A′hab then said to O·ba·di′ah: “Go through the land to all the springs of water and to all the valleys.<a class='fn'></a> Perhaps we can find enough grass to keep the horses and mules alive and not have all our animals die.” <span id='dcv_18_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So they divided between themselves the land they were going to pass through. A′hab went alone by one way, and O·ba·di′ah went alone by another way.</p></div><div id='p165' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>As O·ba·di′ah was on his way, E·li′jah was there to meet him. At once he recognized him and fell facedown and said: “Is this you, my lord E·li′jah?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>He replied to him: “It is I. Go and tell your lord: ‘E·li′jah is here.’” <span id='dcv_18_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>But he said: “What sin have I committed that you should hand your servant over to A′hab to put me to death? <span id='dcv_18_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>As surely as Jehovah your God is living, there is not a nation or a kingdom where my lord has not sent to look for you. After they said, ‘He is not here,’ he made the kingdom and the nation swear that they could not find you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Now you are saying, ‘Go and tell your lord: “E·li′jah is here.”’ <span id='dcv_18_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>When I depart from you, the spirit of Jehovah will carry you away<a class='mr'></a> to a place I will not know, and when I tell A′hab and he does not find you, he will surely kill me. Yet, your servant has feared Jehovah from his youth. <span id='dcv_18_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Has my lord not been told what I did when Jez′e·bel was killing the prophets of Jehovah, how I hid 100 of the prophets of Jehovah by groups of 50 in a cave and kept supplying them bread and water?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But now you are saying, ‘Go and tell your lord: “E·li′jah is here.”’ He will certainly kill me.” <span id='dcv_18_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>However, E·li′jah said: “As surely as Jehovah of armies whom I serve<a class='fn'></a> is living, today I will present myself to him.”</p></div><div id='p166' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>So O·ba·di′ah went off to meet A′hab and told him, and A′hab went to meet E·li′jah.</p></div><div id='p167' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>As soon as A′hab saw E·li′jah, he said to him: “Is this you, the one bringing great trouble<a class='fn'></a> on Israel?”</p></div><div id='p168' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>To this he said: “I have not brought trouble on Israel, but you and the house of your father have, by abandoning the commandments of Jehovah and by following the Ba′als.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>And now summon all Israel to me at Mount Car′mel,<a class='mr'></a> as well as the 450 prophets of Ba′al and the 400 prophets of the sacred pole,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> who are eating at the table of Jez′e·bel.” <span id='dcv_18_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So A′hab sent word among all the people of Israel and collected the prophets together at Mount Car′mel.</p></div><div id='p169' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then E·li′jah approached all the people and said: “How long will you be limping between two different opinions?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> If Jehovah is the true God, follow him;<a class='mr'></a> but if Ba′al is, follow him!” But the people did not say a word in answer to him. <span id='dcv_18_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>E·li′jah then said to the people: “I am the only prophet of Jehovah left,<a class='mr'></a> while the prophets of Ba′al are 450 men. <span id='dcv_18_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Let them give us two young bulls, and let them choose one young bull and cut it into pieces and put it on the wood, but they should not put fire to it. I will prepare the other young bull, and I will place it on the wood, but I will not put fire to it. <span id='dcv_18_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Then you must call on the name of your god,<a class='mr'></a> and I will call on the name of Jehovah. The God who answers by fire will show that he is the true God.”<a class='mr'></a> To this all the people answered: “What you say is good.”</p></div><div id='p170' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>E·li′jah now said to the prophets of Ba′al: “Choose one young bull and prepare it first, because you are the majority. Then call on the name of your god, but you must not put fire to it.” <span id='dcv_18_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>So they took the young bull that was given to them, prepared it, and kept calling on the name of Ba′al from morning until noon, saying: “O Ba′al, answer us!” But there was no voice and no one answering.<a class='mr'></a> They kept limping around the altar that they had made. <span id='dcv_18_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>About noon E·li′jah began to mock them and say: “Call out at the top of your voice! After all, he is a god!<a class='mr'></a> Perhaps he is deep in thought or he has gone to relieve himself.<a class='fn'></a> Or maybe he is asleep and someone needs to wake him up!” <span id='dcv_18_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>They were calling out at the top of their voice and cutting themselves with daggers and lances, according to their custom, until their blood gushed out all over them. <span id='dcv_18_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Noon was past and they continued in a frenzy<a class='fn'></a> until the time the evening grain offering is presented, but there was no voice and no one answering; no one was paying attention.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p171' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>At length E·li′jah said to all the people: “Approach me.” So all the people approached him. Then he repaired the altar of Jehovah that had been torn down.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>E·li′jah then took 12 stones, corresponding to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, to whom Jehovah’s word had come, saying: “Israel will be your name.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>With the stones he built an altar<a class='mr'></a> in the name of Jehovah. Then he made a trench all around the altar, an area large enough to sow with two seah measures<a class='fn'></a> of seed. <span id='dcv_18_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>After that he put the pieces of wood in order, cut the young bull into pieces, and placed it on the wood.<a class='mr'></a> He now said: “Fill four large jars with water and pour it on the burnt offering and on the pieces of wood.” <span id='dcv_18_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Then he said: “Do it again.” So they did it again. Once more he said: “Do it a third time.” So they did it a third time. <span id='dcv_18_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>And the water ran all around the altar, and he also filled the trench with water.</p></div><div id='p172' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>About the time when the evening grain offering is presented,<a class='mr'></a> E·li′jah the prophet stepped forward and said: “O Jehovah, the God of Abraham,<a class='mr'></a> Isaac,<a class='mr'></a> and Israel, today let it be known that you are God in Israel and that I am your servant and that it is by your word that I have done all these things.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>Answer me, O Jehovah! Answer me so that this people may know that you, Jehovah, are the true God and that you are turning their hearts back to you.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p173' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>At that the fire of Jehovah fell from above and consumed the burnt offering,<a class='mr'></a> the pieces of wood, the stones, and the dust, and it licked up the water from the trench.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>When all the people saw it, they immediately fell facedown and said: “Jehovah is the true God! Jehovah is the true God!” <span id='dcv_18_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>Then E·li′jah said to them: “Seize the prophets of Ba′al! Do not let a single one of them escape!” At once they seized them, and E·li′jah brought them down to the stream<a class='fn'></a> of Ki′shon<a class='mr'></a> and slaughtered them there.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p174' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>E·li′jah now said to A′hab: “Go up, eat and drink, for there is the sound of a heavy downpour.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_42' class='dv dx dp'><a>42 </a></span>So A′hab went up to eat and drink, while E·li′jah went up to the top of Car′mel and crouched on the ground, keeping his face between his knees.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>Then he said to his attendant: “Go up, please, and look toward the sea.” So he went up and looked and said: “There is nothing at all.” Seven times E·li′jah said, “Go back.” <span id='dcv_18_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>The seventh time his attendant said: “Look! There is a small cloud like a man’s hand ascending out of the sea.” He now said: “Go, say to A′hab, ‘Hitch up the chariot! Go down so that the downpour may not detain you!’” <span id='dcv_18_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>Meanwhile, the sky grew dark with clouds, the wind blew, and a heavy downpour fell;<a class='mr'></a> and A′hab kept riding and made his way to Jez′re·el.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_46' class='dv dx dp'><a>46 </a></span>But the hand of Jehovah came on E·li′jah, and he wrapped his garment around<a class='fn'></a> his hips and ran ahead of A′hab all the way to Jez′re·el.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="19"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p175' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Then A′hab<a class='mr'></a> told Jez′e·bel<a class='mr'></a> all that E·li′jah had done and how he had killed all the prophets with the sword.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>At that Jez′e·bel sent a messenger to E·li′jah, saying: “So may the gods do to me and add to it if by this time tomorrow I do not make you like each one<a class='fn'></a> of them!” <span id='dcv_19_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>At that he became afraid, so he got up and ran for his life.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> He came to Be′er-she′ba,<a class='mr'></a> which belongs to Judah,<a class='mr'></a> and he left his attendant there. <span id='dcv_19_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>He went a day’s journey into the wilderness and came and sat down under a broom tree, and he asked that he<a class='fn'></a> might die. He said: “It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my life<a class='fn'></a> away,<a class='mr'></a> for I am no better than my forefathers.”</p></div><div id='p176' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then he lay down and fell asleep under the broom tree. But suddenly an angel touched him<a class='mr'></a> and said to him: “Get up and eat.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>When he looked, there at his head was a round loaf on heated stones and a jug of water. He ate and drank and lay down again. <span id='dcv_19_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Later the angel of Jehovah came back a second time and touched him and said: “Get up and eat, for the journey will be too much for you.” <span id='dcv_19_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>So he got up and ate and drank, and in the strength of that nourishment he went on for 40 days and 40 nights until he reached Ho′reb, the mountain of the true God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p177' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>There he entered a cave<a class='mr'></a> and spent the night; and look! Jehovah’s word came to him, telling him: “What are you doing here, E·li′jah?” <span id='dcv_19_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies;<a class='mr'></a> for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant,<a class='mr'></a> your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword,<a class='mr'></a> and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life<a class='fn'></a> away.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But He said: “Go out and stand on the mountain before Jehovah.” And look! Jehovah was passing by,<a class='mr'></a> and a great and strong wind was splitting mountains and breaking crags before Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> but Jehovah was not in the wind. After the wind, there was an earthquake,<a class='mr'></a> but Jehovah was not in the earthquake. <span id='dcv_19_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>After the earthquake, there was a fire,<a class='mr'></a> but Jehovah was not in the fire. After the fire, there was a calm, low voice.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>As soon as E·li′jah heard it, he wrapped his face in his official garment<a class='mr'></a> and went out and stood at the entrance of the cave. Then a voice asked him: “What are you doing here, E·li′jah?” <span id='dcv_19_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant,<a class='mr'></a> your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life<a class='fn'></a> away.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p178' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Jehovah said to him: “Return, and go to the wilderness of Damascus. When you arrive, anoint Haz′a·el<a class='mr'></a> as king over Syria. <span id='dcv_19_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And you should anoint Je′hu<a class='mr'></a> the grandson of Nim′shi as king over Israel, and you should anoint E·li′sha<a class='fn'></a> the son of Sha′phat from A′bel-me·ho′lah as prophet to take your place.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Anyone escaping from Haz′a·el’s sword,<a class='mr'></a> Je′hu will put to death;<a class='mr'></a> and anyone escaping from Je′hu’s sword, E·li′sha will put to death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>And I still have left 7,000 in Israel,<a class='mr'></a> all whose knees have not bent down to Ba′al<a class='mr'></a> and whose mouths have not kissed him.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p179' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>So he went from there and found E·li′sha the son of Sha′phat while he was plowing with 12 pairs of bulls ahead of him, and he was with the 12th pair. So E·li′jah went over to him and threw his official garment<a class='mr'></a> on him. <span id='dcv_19_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>At that he left the bulls and ran after E·li′jah and said: “Please, let me kiss my father and my mother. Then I will follow you.” He replied to him: “Go, return, for what have I done to stop you?” <span id='dcv_19_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>So he went back and took a pair of bulls and sacrificed them, and he used the plowing gear to boil the meat of the bulls and gave it to the people, and they ate. After that he rose up and followed E·li′jah and began to minister to him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="20"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p180' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Now King Ben-ha′dad<a class='mr'></a> of Syria<a class='mr'></a> gathered his whole army together along with 32 other kings and their horses and chariots; he went up and laid siege<a class='mr'></a> to Sa·mar′i·a<a class='mr'></a> and fought against it. <span id='dcv_20_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then he sent messengers to King A′hab<a class='mr'></a> of Israel at the city and said to him: “This is what Ben-ha′dad says, <span id='dcv_20_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>‘Your silver and your gold are mine, as well as the best of your wives and your sons.’” <span id='dcv_20_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>To this the king of Israel answered: “According to your word, my lord the king, I am yours along with all that belongs to me.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p181' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>The messengers later came back and said: “This is what Ben-ha′dad says, ‘I sent this message to you: “Your silver, your gold, your wives, and your sons you will give me.” <span id='dcv_20_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But about this time tomorrow I will send my servants to you, and they will carefully search your house and the houses of your servants, and all your desirable things they will seize and take away.’”</p></div><div id='p182' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>At that the king of Israel called all the elders of the land and said: “Take note, please, and see that this man is bent on bringing calamity, for he demanded my wives, my sons, my silver, and my gold, and I did not refuse him.” <span id='dcv_20_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then all the elders and all the people said to him: “Do not obey, and do not consent.” <span id='dcv_20_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So he said to the messengers of Ben-ha′dad: “Say to my lord the king, ‘All that you first demanded of your servant I will do, but this I cannot do.’” With that the messengers went off and brought word back to him.</p></div><div id='p183' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Ben-ha′dad now sent him this message: “So may the gods do to me and add to it if there is enough dust in Sa·mar′i·a to give each of the people following me a handful!” <span id='dcv_20_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>The king of Israel answered: “Tell him, ‘The one who puts on his armor should not boast about himself like one who takes it off.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>As soon as he heard this reply, while he and the kings were drinking in their tents,<a class='fn'></a> he said to his servants: “Get ready to attack!” So they got ready to attack the city.</p></div><div id='p184' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>But a prophet approached King A′hab<a class='mr'></a> of Israel and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Have you seen all this large crowd? Here I am giving it into your hand today, and then you will know that I am Jehovah.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>A′hab asked: “By whom?” to which he said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘By the attendants of the princes of the provinces.’”<a class='fn'></a> So he asked: “Who will start the battle?” to which he said: “You!”</p></div><div id='p185' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>A′hab then counted the attendants of the princes of the provinces, and they were 232; after that, he counted all the Israelite men, 7,000. <span id='dcv_20_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>They went out at noon while Ben-ha′dad was drinking himself drunk in the tents<a class='fn'></a> along with the 32 kings who were helping him. <span id='dcv_20_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>When the attendants of the princes of the provinces came out first, Ben-ha′dad at once sent messengers. They reported to him: “Men have come out from Sa·mar′i·a.” <span id='dcv_20_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>At that he said: “If they have come out for peace, take them alive; or if they have come out for battle, you should still take them alive.” <span id='dcv_20_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But when these came out of the city—the attendants of the princes of the provinces and the armies that were following them— <span id='dcv_20_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>each one struck down his opponent. Then the Syrians fled,<a class='mr'></a> and Israel pursued them, but King Ben-ha′dad of Syria escaped on a horse with some of the horsemen. <span id='dcv_20_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>But the king of Israel went out and kept striking down the horses and the chariots, and he inflicted a great defeat<a class='fn'></a> on the Syrians.</p></div><div id='p186' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Later the prophet<a class='mr'></a> approached the king of Israel and said to him: “Go, strengthen yourself and consider what you are going to do,<a class='mr'></a> for at the start of the next year<a class='fn'></a> the king of Syria will come up against you.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p187' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Now the servants of the king of Syria said to him: “Their God is a God of mountains. That is why they overpowered us. But if we fight against them on level land, we will overpower them. <span id='dcv_20_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Also do this: Remove all the kings<a class='mr'></a> from their places, and replace them with governors. <span id='dcv_20_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Then gather<a class='fn'></a> an army equal to the army you lost, horse for horse and chariot for chariot. Let us fight against them on level land, and we will surely overpower them.” So he listened to their advice and did just that.</p></div><div id='p188' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>At the start of the year,<a class='fn'></a> Ben-ha′dad mustered the Syrians and went up to A′phek<a class='mr'></a> for battle against Israel. <span id='dcv_20_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>The people of Israel were also mustered and supplied, and they went out to meet them. When the people of Israel camped in front of them, they were like two tiny flocks of goats, while the Syrians filled the whole land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then the man of the true God approached the king of Israel and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Because the Syrians have said: “Jehovah is a God of mountains, and he is not a God of plains,” I will give all this large crowd into your hand,<a class='mr'></a> and you will certainly know that I am Jehovah.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p189' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>They remained encamped opposite each other for seven days, and on the seventh day the battle began. The people of Israel struck down 100,000 Syrian foot soldiers in one day. <span id='dcv_20_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>And the rest fled to A′phek,<a class='mr'></a> into the city. But the wall fell down on 27,000 of the men who were left. Ben-ha′dad also fled and came into the city, and he hid in an inner room.</p></div><div id='p190' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>So his servants said to him: “Look, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel are merciful kings.<a class='fn'></a> Please, let us wear sackcloth on our hips and put ropes on our heads and go out to the king of Israel. Perhaps he will spare your life.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>So they wore sackcloth around their hips and ropes on their heads and came in to the king of Israel and said: “Your servant Ben-ha′dad says, ‘Please, let me<a class='fn'></a> live.’” He replied: “Is he still alive? He is my brother.” <span id='dcv_20_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>The men took it as an omen and quickly took him at his word, so they said: “Ben-ha′dad is your brother.” At that he said: “Go and get him.” Then Ben-ha′dad went out to him, and he had him get up into the chariot.</p></div><div id='p191' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Ben-ha′dad now said to him: “The cities that my father took from your father I will return, and you may establish markets<a class='fn'></a> for yourself in Damascus, just as my father did in Sa·mar′i·a.”</p></div><div id='p192' class='par'><p class='sb'>A′hab replied: “On the basis of this agreement,<a class='fn'></a> I will let you go.”</p></div><div id='p193' class='par'><p class='sb'>With that he made an agreement with him and let him go.</p></div><div id='p194' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>By the word of Jehovah, one of the sons of the prophets<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> said to his companion: “Strike me, please.” But the man refused to strike him. <span id='dcv_20_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>So he said to him: “Because you did not listen to the voice of Jehovah, as soon as you leave me, a lion will kill you.”<a class='fn'></a> After he left him, a lion came upon him and killed him.</p></div><div id='p195' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>He found another man and said: “Strike me, please.” So the man struck him and wounded him.</p></div><div id='p196' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>Then the prophet went and waited for the king by the road, disguising himself with a bandage over his eyes. <span id='dcv_20_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>As the king was passing by, he cried out to the king: “Your servant went into the thick of the battle, and there was a man coming out who brought a man to me and said, ‘Guard this man. If he is found missing, your life will have to take the place of his life,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> or else you will pay a talent<a class='fn'></a> of silver.’ <span id='dcv_20_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>And while your servant was busy here and there, suddenly the man was gone.” The king of Israel said to him: “So your own judgment will be; you have decided it yourself.” <span id='dcv_20_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>Then he quickly removed the bandage from his eyes, and the king of Israel recognized that he was one of the prophets.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>He said to him: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Because you have let the man whom I said should be destroyed escape from your hand,<a class='mr'></a> your life must take the place of his life,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and your people the place of his people.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>At that the king of Israel went home to Sa·mar′i·a,<a class='mr'></a> sullen and dejected.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="21"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p197' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>After these things, an incident took place concerning a vineyard that belonged to Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite; it was in Jez′re·el,<a class='mr'></a> next to the palace of A′hab the king of Sa·mar′i·a. <span id='dcv_21_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>A′hab said to Na′both: “Give me your vineyard for me to use as a vegetable garden, for it is near my house. Then I will give you a better vineyard to replace it. Or if you prefer, I will give you its value in money.” <span id='dcv_21_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But Na′both said to A′hab: “It is unthinkable, from Jehovah’s standpoint, for me to give you the inheritance of my forefathers.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So A′hab came into his house, sullen and dejected over the answer that Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite had given him when he said: “I will not give you the inheritance of my forefathers.” Then he lay down on his bed, kept his face turned away, and refused to eat.</p></div><div id='p198' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>His wife Jez′e·bel<a class='mr'></a> came in to him and asked him: “Why are you<a class='fn'></a> so sad that you refuse to eat?” <span id='dcv_21_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>He replied to her: “Because I said to Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite, ‘Give me your vineyard for money. Or if you prefer, let me give you another vineyard to replace it.’ But he said, ‘I will not give you my vineyard.’” <span id='dcv_21_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>His wife Jez′e·bel said to him: “Are you not the one ruling as king over Israel? Get up, eat something, and let your heart be cheerful. I will give you the vineyard of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So she wrote letters in A′hab’s name and sealed them with his seal<a class='mr'></a> and sent the letters to the elders<a class='mr'></a> and the nobles who lived in Na′both’s city. <span id='dcv_21_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>She wrote in the letters: “Proclaim a fast, and have Na′both sit at the head of the people. <span id='dcv_21_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>And have two good-for-nothing men sit in front of him and testify against him,<a class='mr'></a> saying, ‘You have cursed God and the king!’<a class='mr'></a> Then bring him out and stone him to death.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p199' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So the men of his city, the elders and the nobles who lived in his city, did just as was written in the letters that Jez′e·bel sent to them. <span id='dcv_21_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>They proclaimed a fast and had Na′both sit at the head of the people. <span id='dcv_21_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then two of the good-for-nothing men came in and sat down in front of him and began to testify against Na′both in front of the people, saying: “Na′both has cursed God and the king!”<a class='mr'></a> After that they brought him to the outskirts of the city and stoned him to death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>They now sent word to Jez′e·bel, saying: “Na′both has been stoned to death.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p200' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>As soon as Jez′e·bel heard that Na′both had been stoned to death, she said to A′hab: “Get up, take possession of the vineyard of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite,<a class='mr'></a> which he refused to give you for money, for Na′both is no longer alive. He is dead.” <span id='dcv_21_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>As soon as A′hab heard that Na′both was dead, A′hab got up to go down to the vineyard of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite to take possession of it.</p></div><div id='p201' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But Jehovah’s word came to E·li′jah<a class='mr'></a> the Tish′bite, saying: <span id='dcv_21_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>“Get up, go down to meet A′hab the king of Israel, who is in Sa·mar′i·a.<a class='mr'></a> There he is in the vineyard of Na′both, where he has gone to take possession of it. <span id='dcv_21_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>You must tell him, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Have you murdered a man<a class='mr'></a> and also taken his property?”’<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> Then say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “In the place where the dogs licked up the blood of Na′both, the dogs will lick up your own blood.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p202' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>A′hab said to E·li′jah: “So you have found me, O my enemy!”<a class='mr'></a> He replied: “I have found you. ‘Because you are determined<a class='fn'></a> to do what is bad in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>here I am bringing calamity upon you, and I will make a clean sweep after you and will annihilate from A′hab every male,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> including the helpless and weak in Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And I will make your house like the house of Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ne′bat and like the house of Ba′a·sha<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·hi′jah, for you have provoked my anger and have caused Israel to sin.’ <span id='dcv_21_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Also concerning Jez′e·bel, Jehovah has said: ‘The dogs will eat up Jez′e·bel in the plot of land of Jez′re·el.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Anyone belonging to A′hab who dies in the city the dogs will eat up, and anyone who dies in the field the birds of the heavens will eat up.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Indeed, there has never been anyone like A′hab,<a class='mr'></a> who was so determined<a class='fn'></a> to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, egged on by his wife Jez′e·bel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>He acted in the most detestable way by going after the disgusting idols,<a class='fn'></a> just as all the Am′or·ites had done, whom Jehovah drove out from before the Israelites.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p203' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>As soon as A′hab heard these words, he ripped his garments apart and put sackcloth on his body; and he went on a fast and kept lying down in sackcloth and walking despondently. <span id='dcv_21_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Jehovah’s word then came to E·li′jah the Tish′bite: <span id='dcv_21_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>“Have you seen how A′hab has humbled himself on my account?<a class='mr'></a> Because he has humbled himself before me, I will not bring the calamity during his lifetime. I will bring the calamity upon his house in the days of his son.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="22"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p204' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_1' class='dc dp'><a>22 </a></span>For three years there was no war between Syria and Israel. <span id='dcv_22_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>In the third year King Je·hosh′a·phat<a class='mr'></a> of Judah went down to the king of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then the king of Israel said to his servants: “Do you know that Ra′moth-gil′e·ad<a class='mr'></a> belongs to us? And yet we are hesitating to take it back from the king of Syria.” <span id='dcv_22_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>He then said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “Will you go with me to fight at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad?” Je·hosh′a·phat replied to the king of Israel: “I am the same as you. My people are the same as your people. My horses are the same as your horses.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p205' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But Je·hosh′a·phat said to the king of Israel: “First inquire,<a class='mr'></a> please, for the word of Jehovah.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, about 400 men, and said to them: “Should I go to war against Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, or should I refrain?” They said: “Go up, and Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.”</p></div><div id='p206' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Je·hosh′a·phat then said: “Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah? Let us also inquire through him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>At that the king of Israel said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “There is still one more man through whom we can inquire of Jehovah;<a class='mr'></a> but I hate him,<a class='mr'></a> for he never prophesies good things concerning me, only bad.<a class='mr'></a> He is Mi·cai′ah the son of Im′lah.” However, Je·hosh′a·phat said: “The king should not say such a thing.”</p></div><div id='p207' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So the king of Israel called a court official and said: “Bring Mi·cai′ah the son of Im′lah quickly.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now the king of Israel and Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah were each sitting on his throne, dressed in royal attire, at the threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Sa·mar′i·a, and all the prophets were prophesying before them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Then Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Che·na′a·nah made for himself iron horns and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘With these you will gore<a class='fn'></a> the Syrians until you exterminate them.’” <span id='dcv_22_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>All the other prophets were prophesying the same way, saying: “Go up to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad and you will be successful; Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.”</p></div><div id='p208' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>So the messenger who went to call Mi·cai′ah said to him: “Look! The words of the prophets are unanimously favorable to the king. Let your word, please, become like their words, and speak favorably.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But Mi·cai′ah said: “As surely as Jehovah is living, whatever Jehovah says to me is what I will speak.” <span id='dcv_22_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Then he came in to the king, and the king asked him: “Mi·cai′ah, should we go to war against Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, or should we refrain?” At once he replied: “Go up and you will be successful; Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.” <span id='dcv_22_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>At that the king said to him: “How many times must I put you under oath not to speak to me anything but the truth in the name of Jehovah?” <span id='dcv_22_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>So he said: “I see all the Israelites scattered on the mountains,<a class='mr'></a> like sheep that have no shepherd. Jehovah said: ‘These have no master. Let each one go back to his house in peace.’”</p></div><div id='p209' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then the king of Israel said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “Did I not tell you, ‘He will not prophesy good things concerning me, only bad’?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p210' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Mi·cai′ah then said: “Therefore, hear the word of Jehovah: I saw Jehovah sitting on his throne<a class='mr'></a> and all the army of the heavens standing by him, to his right and to his left.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Jehovah then said, ‘Who will fool A′hab, so that he will go up and fall at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad?’ And one was saying one thing while another said something else. <span id='dcv_22_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then a spirit<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> came forward and stood before Jehovah and said, ‘I will fool him.’ Jehovah asked him, ‘How will you do it?’ <span id='dcv_22_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>He replied, ‘I will go out and become a deceptive spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’<a class='mr'></a> So he said, ‘You will fool him, and what is more, you will be successful. Go out and do that.’ <span id='dcv_22_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>And now Jehovah has put a deceptive spirit in the mouth of all these prophets of yours,<a class='mr'></a> but Jehovah has declared calamity for you.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p211' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Che·na′a·nah now approached and struck Mi·cai′ah on the cheek and said: “Which way did the spirit of Jehovah pass from me to speak with you?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Mi·cai′ah replied: “Look! You will see which way on the day when you will enter the innermost room to hide.” <span id='dcv_22_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Then the king of Israel said: “Take Mi·cai′ah and turn him over to A′mon the chief of the city and to Jo′ash the king’s son. <span id='dcv_22_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Tell them, ‘This is what the king says: “Put this fellow in the prison<a class='mr'></a> and feed him with a reduced allowance of bread and water until I return in peace.”’” <span id='dcv_22_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>But Mi·cai′ah said: “If you do return in peace, Jehovah has not spoken with me.”<a class='mr'></a> Then he added: “Take note, all you peoples.”</p></div><div id='p212' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>So the king of Israel and Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah went up to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>The king of Israel now said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “I will disguise myself and will go into the battle, but you should put on your royal attire.” So the king of Israel disguised himself<a class='mr'></a> and entered the battle. <span id='dcv_22_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>Now the king of Syria had ordered his 32 chariot commanders:<a class='mr'></a> “Do not fight with anyone, small or great, except the king of Israel.” <span id='dcv_22_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>And as soon as the chariot commanders saw Je·hosh′a·phat, they said to themselves: “Surely it is the king of Israel.” So they turned to fight against him; and Je·hosh′a·phat began to cry for help. <span id='dcv_22_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>When the chariot commanders saw that it was not the king of Israel, they immediately turned back from following him.</p></div><div id='p213' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>But one man shot his bow at random,<a class='fn'></a> and he struck the king of Israel between the joints of his coat of mail. So the king said to his charioteer: “Turn around and take me out of the battle,<a class='fn'></a> for I have been badly wounded.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>The fighting raged throughout that day, and the king had to be propped up in the chariot, facing the Syrians. The blood of the wound poured out into the interior of the war chariot, and he died in the evening.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>Around sunset a cry passed through the camp, saying: “Everyone to his city! Everyone to his land!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>Thus the king died, and he was brought to Sa·mar′i·a; they buried the king in Sa·mar′i·a. <span id='dcv_22_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>When they washed off the war chariot by the pool of Sa·mar′i·a, the dogs licked up his blood and the prostitutes bathed there,<a class='fn'></a> according to the word that Jehovah had spoken.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p214' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of A′hab, all that he did and the house<a class='fn'></a> of ivory<a class='mr'></a> that he built and all the cities that he built, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_22_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>Then A′hab was laid to rest with his forefathers;<a class='mr'></a> and his son A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p215' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>Je·hosh′a·phat<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′sa had become king over Judah in the fourth year of King A′hab of Israel. <span id='dcv_22_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>Je·hosh′a·phat was 35 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 25 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was A·zu′bah the daughter of Shil′hi. <span id='dcv_22_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>He kept walking in all the way of A′sa<a class='mr'></a> his father. He did not deviate from it, and he did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes.<a class='mr'></a> However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>Je·hosh′a·phat kept peaceful relations with the king of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Je·hosh′a·phat, his mighty exploits and how he waged war, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_22_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>He also cleared out of the land the rest of the male temple prostitutes<a class='mr'></a> who had been left over in the days of A′sa his father.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p216' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_47' class='dv dx dp'><a>47 </a></span>Then there was no king in E′dom;<a class='mr'></a> a deputy was acting as king.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p217' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_48' class='dv dx dp'><a>48 </a></span>Je·hosh′a·phat also made Tar′shish ships<a class='fn'></a> to go to O′phir for gold,<a class='mr'></a> but they did not go because the ships were wrecked at E′zi·on-ge′ber.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_49' class='dv dx dp'><a>49 </a></span>It was then that A·ha·zi′ah the son of A′hab said to Je·hosh′a·phat: “Let my servants go with your servants in the ships,” but Je·hosh′a·phat did not consent.</p></div><div id='p218' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_50' class='dv dx dp'><a>50 </a></span>Then Je·hosh′a·phat was laid to rest with his forefathers<a class='mr'></a> and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather; and his son Je·ho′ram<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p219' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_51' class='dv dp'><a>51 </a></span>A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′hab became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a in the 17th year of King Je·hosh′a·phat of Judah, and he reigned over Israel for two years. <span id='dcv_22_52' class='dv dp'><a>52 </a></span>And he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes and walking in the way of his father<a class='mr'></a> and his mother<a class='mr'></a> and in the way of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, who had caused Israel to sin.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_53' class='dv dp'><a>53 </a></span>He continued serving Ba′al<a class='mr'></a> and bowing down to him and kept offending Jehovah the God of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> just as his father had done.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>