<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>Long ago God spoke to our forefathers by means of the prophets on many occasions and in many ways.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Now at the end of these days he has spoken to us by means of a Son,<a class='mr'></a> whom he appointed heir of all things,<a class='mr'></a> and through whom he made the systems of things.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>He is the reflection of God’s glory<a class='mr'></a> and the exact representation of his very being,<a class='mr'></a> and he sustains all things by the word of his power. And after he had made a purification for our sins,<a class='mr'></a> he sat down at the right hand of the Majesty on high.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>So he has become better than the angels<a class='mr'></a> to the extent that he has inherited a name more excellent than theirs.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>For example, to which one of the angels did God ever say: “You are my son; today I have become your father”?<a class='mr'></a> And again: “I will become his father, and he will become my son”?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>But when he again brings his Firstborn<a class='mr'></a> into the inhabited earth, he says: “And let all of God’s angels do obeisance to him.”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Also, he says about the angels: “He makes his angels spirits, and his ministers<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> a flame of fire.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But about the Son, he says: “God is your throne<a class='mr'></a> forever and ever, and the scepter of your Kingdom is the scepter of uprightness.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>You loved righteousness, and you hated lawlessness. That is why God, your God, anointed you<a class='mr'></a> with the oil of exultation more than your companions.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>And: “At the beginning, O Lord, you laid the foundations of the earth, and the heavens are the works of your hands. <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>They will perish, but you will remain; and just like a garment, they will all wear out, <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>and you will wrap them up just as a cloak, as a garment, and they will be changed. But you are the same, and your years will never come to an end.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>But about which of the angels has he ever said: “Sit at my right hand until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet”?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Are they not all spirits for holy service,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> sent out to minister for those who are going to inherit salvation?</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>That is why it is necessary for us to pay more than the usual attention to the things we have heard,<a class='mr'></a> so that we never drift away.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>For if the word spoken through angels<a class='mr'></a> proved to be sure, and every transgression and disobedient act received a punishment in harmony with justice,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>how will we escape if we have neglected so great a salvation?<a class='mr'></a> For it began to be spoken through our Lord<a class='mr'></a> and was verified for us by those who heard him, <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>while God joined in bearing witness with signs and wonders<a class='fn'></a> and various powerful works<a class='mr'></a> and with the holy spirit distributed according to his will.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>For it is not to angels that he has subjected the inhabited earth to come,<a class='mr'></a> about which we are speaking. <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But in one place a certain witness said: “What is man that you keep him in mind, or a son of man that you take care of him?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>You made him a little lower than angels; you crowned him with glory and honor, and appointed him over the works of your hands. <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>All things you subjected under his feet.”<a class='mr'></a> By subjecting all things to him,<a class='mr'></a> God left nothing that is not subject to him.<a class='mr'></a> Now, though, we do not yet see all things in subjection to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But we do see Jesus, who was made a little lower than angels,<a class='mr'></a> now crowned with glory and honor for having suffered death,<a class='mr'></a> so that by God’s undeserved kindness he might taste death for everyone.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For it was fitting that the one for whom and through whom all things exist, in bringing many sons to glory,<a class='mr'></a> should make the Chief Agent of their salvation<a class='mr'></a> perfect through sufferings.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For both the one who is sanctifying and those who are being sanctified<a class='mr'></a> all stem from one,<a class='mr'></a> and for this reason he is not ashamed to call them brothers,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>as he says: “I will declare your name to my brothers; in the midst of the congregation I will praise you with song.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>And again: “I will put my trust in him.”<a class='mr'></a> And again: “Look! I and the young children, whom Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> gave me.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Therefore, since the “young children” are sharers of blood and flesh, he also similarly shared in the same things,<a class='mr'></a> so that through his death he might bring to nothing the one having the means to cause death,<a class='mr'></a> that is, the Devil,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>and that he might set free<a class='fn'></a> all those who were held in slavery all their lives by their fear of death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>For it is not really angels he is assisting, but he is assisting Abraham’s offspring.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Consequently, he had to become like his “brothers” in all respects,<a class='mr'></a> so that he could become a merciful and faithful high priest in things relating to God, in order to offer a propitiatory sacrifice<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for the sins of the people.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Since he himself has suffered when being put to the test,<a class='mr'></a> he is able to come to the aid of those who are being put to the test.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Consequently, holy brothers, partakers of the heavenly calling,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> consider the apostle and high priest whom we acknowledge<a class='fn'></a>—Jesus.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>He was faithful to the One who appointed him,<a class='mr'></a> just as Moses also was in all the house of that One.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For he<a class='fn'></a> is counted worthy of more glory<a class='mr'></a> than Moses, since the one who constructs a house has more honor than the house itself. <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Of course, every house is constructed by someone, but the one who constructed all things is God. <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Now Moses was faithful as an attendant in all the house of that One as a testimony<a class='fn'></a> of the things that were to be spoken afterward, <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>but Christ was faithful as a son<a class='mr'></a> over God’s house. We are His house<a class='mr'></a> if, indeed, we hold on firmly to our freeness of speech and the hope of which we boast down to the end.</p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Therefore, just as the holy spirit says,<a class='mr'></a> “Today if you listen to his voice, <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>do not harden your hearts as on the occasion of provoking to bitter anger, as in the day of testing in the wilderness,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>where your forefathers put me to the test and tried me, despite seeing my works for 40 years.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>This is why I became disgusted with this generation and said: ‘They always go astray in their hearts, and they have not come to know my ways.’ <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>So I swore in my anger: ‘They will not enter into my rest.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Beware, brothers, for fear there should ever develop in any one of you a wicked heart lacking faith by drawing away from the living God;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>but keep on encouraging one another each day, as long as it is called “Today,”<a class='mr'></a> so that none of you should become hardened by the deceptive power of sin. <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>For we actually become partakers of<a class='fn'></a> the Christ only if we hold firmly down to the end the confidence we had at the beginning.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>As it is said, “Today if you listen to his voice, do not harden your hearts as on the occasion of provoking to bitter anger.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>For who heard and yet provoked him to bitter anger? Was it not, in fact, all those who went out of Egypt under Moses?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Moreover, with whom did God become disgusted for 40 years?<a class='mr'></a> Was it not with those who sinned, whose dead bodies fell in the wilderness?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>And to whom did he swear that they would not enter into his rest? Was it not to those who acted disobediently? <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>So we see that they could not enter in because of lack of faith.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Therefore, since a promise of entering into his rest remains, let us be on guard<a class='fn'></a> for fear someone among you seems to fall short of it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For we have also had the good news declared to us,<a class='mr'></a> just as they had; but the word that they heard did not benefit them, because they were not united by faith with those who listened. <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For we who have exercised faith do enter into the rest, just as he has said: “So I swore in my anger, ‘They will not enter into my rest,’”<a class='mr'></a> although his works were finished from the founding of the world.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>For in one place he has said of the seventh day as follows: “And God rested on the seventh day from all his works,”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>and here again he says: “They will not enter into my rest.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Therefore, since it remains for some to enter into it, and those to whom the good news was first declared did not enter in because of disobedience,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>he again marks off a certain day by saying long afterward in David’s psalm, “Today”; just as it has been said above, “Today if you listen to his voice, do not harden your hearts.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>For if Joshua<a class='mr'></a> had led them into a place of rest, God would not afterward have spoken of another day. <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>So there remains a sabbath-rest for the people of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For the man who has entered into God’s rest has also rested from his own works, just as God did from his own.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Let us therefore do our utmost to enter into that rest, so that no one may fall into the same pattern of disobedience.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>For the word of God is alive and exerts power<a class='mr'></a> and is sharper than any two-edged sword<a class='mr'></a> and pierces even to the dividing of soul<a class='fn'></a> and spirit,<a class='fn'></a> and of joints from the marrow, and is able to discern thoughts and intentions of the heart. <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight,<a class='mr'></a> but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Therefore, since we have a great high priest who has passed through the heavens, Jesus the Son of God,<a class='mr'></a> let us hold on to our public declaration of him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>For we do not have a high priest who cannot sympathize with our weaknesses,<a class='mr'></a> but we have one who has been tested in all respects as we have, but without sin.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Let us, then, approach the throne of undeserved kindness with freeness of speech,<a class='mr'></a> so that we may receive mercy and find undeserved kindness to help us at the right time.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>For every high priest taken from among men is appointed in their behalf over the things relating to God,<a class='mr'></a> so that he may offer gifts and sacrifices for sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>He is able to deal compassionately<a class='fn'></a> with the ignorant and erring<a class='fn'></a> ones, since he too is confronted with<a class='fn'></a> his own weakness, <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>and because of that he must make offerings for his own sins just as he does for those of the people.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>A man does not take this honor of his own accord, but he receives it only when he is called by God, just as Aaron was.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So, too, the Christ did not glorify himself<a class='mr'></a> by becoming a high priest, but was glorified by the One who said to him: “You are my son; today I have become your father.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>As he also says in another place, “You are a priest forever in the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>During his life on earth,<a class='fn'></a> Christ offered up supplications and also petitions, with strong outcries and tears,<a class='mr'></a> to the One who was able to save him out of death, and he was favorably heard for his godly fear. <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Although he was a son, he learned obedience from the things he suffered.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And after he had been made perfect,<a class='mr'></a> he became responsible for everlasting salvation to all those obeying him,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>because he has been designated by God a high priest in the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>We have much to say about him, and it is difficult to explain, because you have become dull in your hearing. <span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>For although by now<a class='fn'></a> you should be teachers, you again need someone to teach you from the beginning the elementary things<a class='mr'></a> of the sacred pronouncements of God, and you have gone back to needing milk, not solid food. <span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>For everyone who continues to feed on milk is unacquainted with the word of righteousness, for he is a young child.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment<a class='fn'></a> trained to distinguish both right and wrong.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Therefore, now that we have moved beyond the primary doctrine<a class='mr'></a> about the Christ, let us press on to maturity,<a class='mr'></a> not laying a foundation again, namely, repentance from dead works and faith in God, <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>the teaching on baptisms and the laying on of the hands,<a class='mr'></a> the resurrection of the dead<a class='mr'></a> and everlasting judgment. <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>And this we will do, if God indeed permits.</p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>For as regards those who were once enlightened<a class='mr'></a> and who have tasted the heavenly free gift and who have become partakers of holy spirit <span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>and who have tasted the fine word of God and powers of the coming system of things,<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>but have fallen away,<a class='mr'></a> it is impossible to revive them again to repentance, because they nail the Son of God to the stake again for themselves and expose him to public shame.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>For the ground receives a blessing from God when it drinks in the rain that frequently falls on it and then produces vegetation useful to those for whom it is cultivated. <span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But if it produces thorns and thistles, it is rejected and is near to being cursed, and in the end it will be burned.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>But in your case, beloved ones, we are convinced of better things, things related to salvation, even though we are speaking in this way. <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name<a class='mr'></a> by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones. <span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But we desire each one of you to show the same industriousness so as to have the full assurance of the hope<a class='mr'></a> down to the end,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>so that you may not become sluggish,<a class='mr'></a> but be imitators of those who through faith and patience inherit the promises.</p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>For when God made his promise to Abraham, since he could not swear by anyone greater, he swore by himself,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>saying: “I will surely bless you and I will surely multiply you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>So after Abraham had shown patience, he obtained this promise. <span id='dcv_6_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>For men swear by someone greater, and their oath is the end of every dispute, since it is a legal guarantee to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>In this same way, when God decided to demonstrate more clearly to the heirs of the promise<a class='mr'></a> the unchangeableness of his purpose,<a class='fn'></a> he guaranteed it<a class='fn'></a> with an oath, <span id='dcv_6_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>in order that through two unchangeable things in which it is impossible for God to lie,<a class='mr'></a> we who have fled to the refuge may have strong encouragement to take firm hold of the hope set before us. <span id='dcv_6_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>We have this hope<a class='mr'></a> as an anchor for the soul,<a class='fn'></a> both sure and firm, and it enters in within the curtain,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>where a forerunner has entered in our behalf, Jesus,<a class='mr'></a> who has become a high priest in the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek forever.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dp'><a>7 </a></span>For this Mel·chiz′e·dek, king of Sa′lem, priest of the Most High God, met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>and Abraham gave<a class='fn'></a> him a tenth of everything. First, his name is translated “King of Righteousness,” and then also king of Sa′lem, that is, “King of Peace.” <span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>In being fatherless, motherless, without genealogy, having neither a beginning of days nor an end of life, but being made like the Son of God, he remains a priest for all time.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>See how great this man was to whom Abraham, the family head,<a class='fn'></a> gave a tenth out of the best spoils.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>True, according to the Law, those of the sons of Le′vi<a class='mr'></a> who receive their priestly office have a commandment to collect tithes from the people,<a class='mr'></a> that is, from their brothers, even though these are descendants<a class='fn'></a> of Abraham. <span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But this man who did not trace his genealogy from them took tithes from Abraham and blessed the one who had the promises.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Now it is undeniable that the lesser one is blessed by the greater. <span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>And in the one case, it is men who are dying who receive tithes, but in the other case, it is someone of whom witness is given that he lives.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And it could be said that even Le′vi, who receives tithes, has paid tithes through Abraham, <span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>for he was still a future descendant<a class='fn'></a> of his forefather when Mel·chiz′e·dek met him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>If, then, perfection was attainable through the Levitical priesthood<a class='mr'></a> (for it was a feature of the Law that was given to the people), what further need would there be for another priest to arise who is said to be in the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek<a class='mr'></a> and not in the manner of Aaron? <span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>For since the priesthood is being changed, it becomes necessary to change the Law as well.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>For the man about whom these things are said came from another tribe, from which no one has officiated at the altar.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>For it is clear that our Lord has descended from Judah,<a class='mr'></a> yet Moses said nothing about priests coming from that tribe.</p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>And this becomes even clearer when another priest<a class='mr'></a> arises who is like Mel·chiz′e·dek,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>who has become such, not by the legal requirement that depends on fleshly descent, but by the power of an indestructible life.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>For it is said in witness of him: “You are a priest forever in the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So, then, the former commandment is set aside because it is weak and ineffective.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For the Law made nothing perfect,<a class='mr'></a> but the introduction of a better hope<a class='mr'></a> did, through which we are drawing near to God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Also, inasmuch as this was not done without an oath being sworn <span id='dcv_7_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>(for, indeed, there are men who have become priests without a sworn oath, but this one has become so through an oath sworn respecting him by the One who said: “Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> has sworn, and he will not change his mind,<a class='fn'></a> ‘You are a priest forever’”),<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Jesus has accordingly become the guarantee<a class='fn'></a> of a better covenant.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Furthermore, many had to become priests in succession<a class='mr'></a> because death prevented them from continuing as such, <span id='dcv_7_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>but because he continues alive forever,<a class='mr'></a> his priesthood has no successors. <span id='dcv_7_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>So he is able also to save completely those who are approaching God through him, because he is always alive to plead for them.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>For it is fitting for us to have such a high priest who is loyal, innocent, undefiled,<a class='mr'></a> separated from the sinners, and exalted above the heavens.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Unlike those high priests, he does not need to offer up sacrifices daily,<a class='mr'></a> first for his own sins and then for those of the people,<a class='mr'></a> because he did this once for all time when he offered himself up.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>For the Law appoints as high priests men who have weaknesses,<a class='mr'></a> but the word of the oath<a class='mr'></a> sworn after the Law appoints a son, who has been made perfect<a class='mr'></a> forever.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Now this is the main point of what we are saying: We have such a high priest as this,<a class='mr'></a> and he has sat down at the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>a minister<a class='fn'></a> of the holy place<a class='mr'></a> and of the true tent, which Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> set up, and not man. <span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For every high priest is appointed to offer both gifts and sacrifices; so it was necessary for this one also to have something to offer.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>If he were on earth, he would not be a priest,<a class='mr'></a> since there are already men who offer the gifts according to the Law. <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>These men are offering sacred service in a typical representation and a shadow<a class='mr'></a> of the heavenly things;<a class='mr'></a> just as Moses, when about to construct the tent, was given the divine command: For He says: “See that you make all things after their pattern that was shown to you in the mountain.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>But now Jesus has obtained a more excellent ministry<a class='fn'></a> because he is also the mediator<a class='mr'></a> of a correspondingly better covenant,<a class='mr'></a> which has been legally established on better promises.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>If that first covenant had been faultless, there would have been no need for a second.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>For he does find fault with the people when he says: “‘Look! The days are coming,’ says Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a> ‘when I will make with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah a new covenant. <span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>It will not be like the covenant that I made with their forefathers on the day I took hold of their hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> because they did not remain in my covenant, so I stopped caring for them,’ says Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>“‘For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days,’ says Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a> ‘I will put my laws in their mind, and in their hearts I will write them.<a class='mr'></a> And I will become their God, and they will become my people.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>“‘And they will no longer teach each one his fellow citizen and each one his brother, saying: “Know Jehovah!”<a class='fn'></a> For they will all know me, from the least to the greatest of them. <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>For I will be merciful toward their unrighteous deeds, and I will no longer call their sins to mind.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>In his saying “a new covenant,” he has made the former one obsolete.<a class='mr'></a> Now what is obsolete and growing old is near to vanishing away.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>For its part, the former covenant used to have legal requirements for sacred service and its holy place<a class='mr'></a> on earth. <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For a first tent compartment was constructed, in which were the lampstand<a class='mr'></a> and the table and the display of the loaves of presentation;<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and it is called the Holy Place.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>But behind the second curtain<a class='mr'></a> was the tent compartment called the Most Holy.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>This had a golden censer<a class='mr'></a> and the ark of the covenant<a class='mr'></a> completely overlaid with gold,<a class='mr'></a> in which were the golden jar containing the manna<a class='mr'></a> and Aaron’s rod that budded<a class='mr'></a> and the tablets<a class='mr'></a> of the covenant; <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>and above it were the glorious cherubs overshadowing the propitiatory cover.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> But now is not the time to speak of these things in detail.</p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>After these things were constructed this way, the priests enter the first tent compartment regularly to perform the sacred services;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>but the high priest enters alone into the second compartment once a year,<a class='mr'></a> not without blood,<a class='mr'></a> which he offers for himself<a class='mr'></a> and for the sins that the people<a class='mr'></a> committed in ignorance. <span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Thus the holy spirit makes it clear that the way into the holy place had not yet been revealed while the first tent was standing.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>This tent is an illustration for the present time,<a class='mr'></a> and according to this arrangement, both gifts and sacrifices are offered.<a class='mr'></a> However, these are not able to make the conscience of the man doing sacred service perfect.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>They have to do only with foods and drinks and various ceremonial washings.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> They were legal requirements concerning the body<a class='mr'></a> and were imposed until the appointed time to set things straight.</p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>However, when Christ came as a high priest of the good things that have already taken place, he passed through the greater and more perfect tent not made with hands, that is, not of this creation. <span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>He entered into the holy place, not with the blood of goats and of young bulls, but with his own blood,<a class='mr'></a> once for all time, and obtained an everlasting deliverance<a class='fn'></a> for us.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>For if the blood of goats and of bulls<a class='mr'></a> and the ashes of a heifer<a class='fn'></a> sprinkled on those who have been defiled sanctifies for the cleansing of the flesh,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>how much more will the blood of the Christ,<a class='mr'></a> who through an everlasting spirit offered himself without blemish to God, cleanse our consciences from dead works<a class='mr'></a> so that we may render sacred service to the living God?<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>That is why he is a mediator of a new covenant,<a class='mr'></a> in order that because a death has occurred for their release by ransom<a class='mr'></a> from the transgressions under the former covenant, those who have been called may receive the promise of the everlasting inheritance.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>For where there is a covenant, the death of the human covenanter needs to be established, <span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>because a covenant is valid at death, since it is not in force as long as the human covenanter is living. <span id='dcv_9_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Consequently, neither was the former covenant put into effect<a class='fn'></a> without blood. <span id='dcv_9_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For when Moses had spoken every commandment of the Law to all the people, he took the blood of the young bulls and of the goats, with water, scarlet wool, and hyssop, and sprinkled the book<a class='fn'></a> and all the people, <span id='dcv_9_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>saying: “This is the blood of the covenant that God has commanded you to keep.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>He likewise sprinkled the tent and all the vessels of the holy service<a class='fn'></a> with the blood.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Yes, according to the Law nearly all things are cleansed with blood,<a class='mr'></a> and unless blood is poured out no forgiveness takes place.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Therefore, it was necessary for the typical representations<a class='mr'></a> of the things in the heavens to be cleansed by these means,<a class='mr'></a> but the heavenly things require far better sacrifices. <span id='dcv_9_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>For Christ did not enter into a holy place made with hands,<a class='mr'></a> which is a copy of the reality,<a class='mr'></a> but into heaven itself,<a class='mr'></a> so that he now appears before<a class='fn'></a> God on our behalf.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>This was not done to offer himself often, as when the high priest enters into the holy place from year to year<a class='mr'></a> with blood that is not his own. <span id='dcv_9_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Otherwise, he would have to suffer often from the founding of the world. But now he has manifested himself once for all time at the conclusion of the systems of things<a class='fn'></a> to do away with sin through the sacrifice of himself.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>And just as it is reserved for men to die once for all time, but after this to receive a judgment, <span id='dcv_9_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>so also the Christ was offered once for all time to bear the sins of many;<a class='mr'></a> and the second time that he appears it will be apart from sin,<a class='fn'></a> and he will be seen by those earnestly looking for him for their salvation.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For since the Law has a shadow<a class='mr'></a> of the good things to come,<a class='mr'></a> but not the very substance of the things, it<a class='fn'></a> can never, by the same sacrifices that are continually offered year after year, make those who approach perfect.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Otherwise, would not the sacrifices have stopped being offered, because those rendering sacred service once cleansed would have no consciousness of sins anymore? <span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>On the contrary, these sacrifices are a reminder of sins year after year,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>for it is not possible for the blood of bulls and of goats to take sins away.</p></div><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So when he comes into the world, he says: “‘Sacrifice and offering you did not want, but you prepared a body for me. <span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>You did not approve of whole burnt offerings and sin offerings.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then I said: ‘Look! I have come (in the scroll<a class='fn'></a> it is written about me) to do your will, O God.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>After first saying: “You did not want nor did you approve of sacrifices and offerings and whole burnt offerings and sin offerings”—sacrifices that are offered according to the Law— <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>then he says: “Look! I have come to do your will.”<a class='mr'></a> He does away with what is first in order to establish what is second. <span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>By this “will”<a class='mr'></a> we have been sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all time.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Also, every priest takes his station day after day to offer holy service<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and to make the same sacrifices often,<a class='mr'></a> which can never take sins away completely.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>But this man offered one sacrifice for sins for all time and sat down at the right hand of God,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>from then on waiting until his enemies should be placed as a stool for his feet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>For it is by one sacrificial offering that he has made those who are being sanctified perfect<a class='mr'></a> for all time. <span id='dcv_10_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Moreover, the holy spirit also bears witness to us, for after it has said: <span id='dcv_10_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>“‘This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days,’ says Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a> ‘I will put my laws in their hearts, and in their minds I will write them.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then it says: “And I will no longer call their sins and their lawless deeds to mind.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Now where there is forgiveness of these, there is no longer an offering for sin.</p></div><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Therefore, brothers, since we have boldness<a class='fn'></a> for the way of entry into the holy place<a class='mr'></a> by the blood of Jesus, <span id='dcv_10_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>which he opened up<a class='fn'></a> for us as a new and living way through the curtain,<a class='mr'></a> that is, his flesh, <span id='dcv_10_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>and since we have a great priest over the house of God,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>let us approach with sincere hearts and complete faith, having had our hearts sprinkled clean from a wicked conscience<a class='mr'></a> and our bodies bathed with clean water.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Let us hold firmly the public declaration of our hope without wavering,<a class='mr'></a> for the one who promised is faithful. <span id='dcv_10_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>And let us consider<a class='fn'></a> one another so as to incite<a class='fn'></a> to love and fine works,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>not forsaking our meeting together,<a class='mr'></a> as some have the custom, but encouraging one another,<a class='mr'></a> and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>For if we practice sin willfully after having received the accurate knowledge of the truth,<a class='mr'></a> there is no longer any sacrifice for sins left,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>but there is a certain fearful expectation of judgment and a burning indignation that is going to consume those in opposition.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Anyone who has disregarded the Law of Moses dies without compassion on the testimony of two or three.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>How much greater punishment do you think a person will deserve who has trampled on the Son of God and who has regarded as of ordinary value the blood of the covenant<a class='mr'></a> by which he was sanctified, and who has outraged the spirit of undeserved kindness with contempt?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>For we know the One who said: “Vengeance is mine; I will repay.” And again: “Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> will judge his people.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</p></div><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>However, keep remembering the former days in which, after you were enlightened,<a class='mr'></a> you endured a great struggle along with sufferings. <span id='dcv_10_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>At times you were publicly exposed<a class='fn'></a> both to reproaches and to tribulations, and at times you shared<a class='fn'></a> with those who were having such an experience. <span id='dcv_10_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>For you expressed sympathy for those in prison and you accepted joyfully the plundering of your belongings,<a class='mr'></a> knowing that you yourselves have a better and an enduring possession.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Therefore, do not throw away your boldness,<a class='fn'></a> which will be richly rewarded.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>For you need endurance,<a class='mr'></a> so that after you have done the will of God, you may receive the fulfillment of the promise. <span id='dcv_10_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>For yet “a very little while,”<a class='mr'></a> and “the one who is coming will arrive and will not delay.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>“But my righteous one will live by reason of faith,”<a class='mr'></a> and “if he shrinks back, I have<a class='fn'></a> no pleasure in him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>Now we are not the sort who shrink back to destruction,<a class='mr'></a> but the sort who have faith for the preserving of our lives.<a class='fn'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Faith is the assured expectation of what is hoped for,<a class='mr'></a> the evident demonstration<a class='fn'></a> of realities that are not seen. <span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For by means of it, the men of ancient times<a class='fn'></a> had witness borne to them.</p></div><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>By faith we perceive that the systems of things<a class='fn'></a> were put in order by God’s word, so that what is seen has come into existence from things that are not visible.</p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>By faith Abel offered God a sacrifice of greater worth than that of Cain,<a class='mr'></a> and through that faith he received the witness that he was righteous, for God approved<a class='fn'></a> his gifts,<a class='mr'></a> and although he died, he still speaks<a class='mr'></a> through his faith.</p></div><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>By faith E′noch<a class='mr'></a> was transferred so as not to see death, and he was nowhere to be found because God had transferred him;<a class='mr'></a> for before he was transferred he received the witness that he had pleased God well. <span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please God well, for whoever approaches God must believe that he is<a class='fn'></a> and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>By faith Noah,<a class='mr'></a> after receiving divine warning of things not yet seen,<a class='mr'></a> showed godly fear and constructed an ark<a class='mr'></a> for the saving of his household; and through this faith he condemned the world,<a class='mr'></a> and he became an heir of the righteousness that results from faith.</p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>By faith Abraham,<a class='mr'></a> when he was called, obeyed by going out to a place he was to receive as an inheritance; he went out, although not knowing where he was going.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>By faith he lived as a foreigner in the land of the promise as in a foreign land,<a class='mr'></a> living in tents<a class='mr'></a> with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the very same promise.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For he was awaiting the city having real foundations, whose designer<a class='fn'></a> and builder is God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>By faith also Sarah received power to conceive offspring,<a class='fn'></a> even when she was past the age,<a class='mr'></a> since she considered Him faithful<a class='fn'></a> who made the promise. <span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>For this reason, from one man who was as good as dead,<a class='mr'></a> there were born children,<a class='mr'></a> as many as the stars of heaven in number and as innumerable as the sands by the seaside.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>In faith all of these died, although they did not receive the fulfillment of the promises;<a class='mr'></a> but they saw them from a distance<a class='mr'></a> and welcomed them and publicly declared that they were strangers and temporary residents in the land. <span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>For those who speak in such a way make it evident that they are earnestly seeking a place of their own. <span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>And yet, if they had kept remembering the place from which they had departed,<a class='mr'></a> they would have had opportunity to return. <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>But now they are reaching out for a better place, that is, one belonging to heaven. Therefore, God is not ashamed of them, to be called on as their God,<a class='mr'></a> for he has prepared a city for them.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>By faith Abraham, when he was tested,<a class='mr'></a> as good as offered up Isaac—the man who had gladly received the promises attempted to offer up his only-begotten son<a class='mr'></a>— <span id='dcv_11_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>although it had been said to him: “What will be called your offspring<a class='fn'></a> will be through Isaac.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>But he reasoned that God was able to raise him up even from the dead, and he did receive him from there in an illustrative way.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>By faith also Isaac blessed Jacob<a class='mr'></a> and E′sau<a class='mr'></a> concerning things to come.</p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>By faith Jacob, when about to die,<a class='mr'></a> blessed each of the sons of Joseph<a class='mr'></a> and worshipped while leaning on the top of his staff.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>By faith Joseph, nearing his end, spoke of the exodus of the sons of Israel, and he gave instructions<a class='fn'></a> concerning his bones.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>By faith Moses was hid by his parents for three months after his birth,<a class='mr'></a> because they saw that the young child was beautiful<a class='mr'></a> and they did not fear the order of the king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>By faith Moses, when grown up,<a class='mr'></a> refused to be called the son of Phar′aoh’s daughter,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>choosing to be mistreated with the people of God rather than to have the temporary enjoyment of sin, <span id='dcv_11_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>because he considered the reproach of the Christ to be riches greater than the treasures of Egypt, for he looked intently toward the payment of the reward. <span id='dcv_11_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>By faith he left Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> but not fearing the anger of the king,<a class='mr'></a> for he continued steadfast as seeing the One who is invisible.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>By faith he observed the Passover and the splashing of the blood, so that the destroyer might not harm<a class='fn'></a> their firstborn.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>By faith they passed through the Red Sea as on dry land,<a class='mr'></a> but when the Egyptians attempted it, they were swallowed up.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>By faith the walls of Jer′i·cho fell down after the people had marched around them for seven days.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>By faith Ra′hab the prostitute did not perish with those who acted disobediently, because she received the spies in a peaceable way.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>And what more will I say? For time will fail me if I go on to relate about Gid′e·on,<a class='mr'></a> Ba′rak,<a class='mr'></a> Samson,<a class='mr'></a> Jeph′thah,<a class='mr'></a> David,<a class='mr'></a> as well as Samuel<a class='mr'></a> and the other prophets. <span id='dcv_11_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>Through faith they defeated kingdoms,<a class='mr'></a> brought about righteousness, obtained promises,<a class='mr'></a> stopped the mouths of lions,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>quenched the force of fire,<a class='mr'></a> escaped the edge of the sword,<a class='mr'></a> from a weak state were made powerful,<a class='mr'></a> became mighty in war,<a class='mr'></a> routed invading armies.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>Women received their dead by resurrection,<a class='mr'></a> but other men were tortured because they would not accept release by some ransom, in order that they might attain a better resurrection. <span id='dcv_11_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>Yes, others received their trial by mockings and scourgings, indeed, more than that, by chains<a class='mr'></a> and prisons.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>They were stoned,<a class='mr'></a> they were tried, they were sawn in two,<a class='fn'></a> they were slaughtered by the sword,<a class='mr'></a> they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins,<a class='mr'></a> while they were in need, in tribulation,<a class='mr'></a> mistreated;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>and the world was not worthy of them. They wandered about in deserts and mountains and caves<a class='mr'></a> and dens of the earth.</p></div><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>And yet all of these, although they received a favorable witness because of their faith, did not obtain the fulfillment of the promise, <span id='dcv_11_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>because God had foreseen something better for us,<a class='mr'></a> so that they might not be made perfect apart from us.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>So, then, because we have such a great cloud of witnesses surrounding us, let us also throw off every weight and the sin that easily entangles us,<a class='mr'></a> and let us run with endurance the race that is set before us,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>as we look intently at the Chief Agent and Perfecter of our faith, Jesus.<a class='mr'></a> For the joy that was set before him he endured a torture stake,<a class='fn'></a> despising shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Indeed, consider closely the one who has endured such hostile speech from sinners<a class='mr'></a> against their own interests, so that you may not get tired and give up.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>In your struggle against that sin, you have never yet resisted to the point of having your blood shed. <span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>And you have entirely forgotten the exhortation that addresses you as sons: “My son, do not belittle the discipline from Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a> nor give up when you are corrected by him; <span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>for those whom Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> loves he disciplines, in fact, he scourges<a class='fn'></a> everyone whom he receives as a son.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>You need to endure as part of your discipline.<a class='fn'></a> God is treating you as sons.<a class='mr'></a> For what son is not disciplined by his father?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But if you have not all shared in receiving this discipline, you are really illegitimate children, and not sons. <span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Furthermore, our human fathers<a class='fn'></a> used to discipline us, and we gave them respect. Should we not more readily submit ourselves to the Father of our spiritual life and live?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>For they disciplined us for a short time according to what seemed good to them, but he does so for our benefit so that we may partake of his holiness.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>True, no discipline seems for the present to be joyous, but it is painful;<a class='fn'></a> yet afterward, it yields the peaceable fruit of righteousness to those who have been trained by it.</p></div><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Therefore, strengthen the hands that hang down and the feeble knees,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>and keep making straight paths for your feet,<a class='mr'></a> so that what is lame may not be put out of joint but, rather, may be healed. <span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Pursue peace with all people<a class='mr'></a> and the sanctification<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> without which no man will see the Lord. <span id='dcv_12_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Carefully watch that no one fails to obtain the undeserved kindness of God, so that no poisonous root springs up to cause trouble and many are defiled by it;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>and watch that among you there is no one who is sexually immoral<a class='fn'></a> nor anyone who does not appreciate sacred things, like E′sau, who gave up his rights as firstborn in exchange for one meal.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>For you know that afterward when he wanted to inherit the blessing, he was rejected; for although he earnestly tried to bring about a change of mind<a class='fn'></a> with tears,<a class='mr'></a> it was to no avail.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>For you have not approached something that can be felt<a class='mr'></a> and that has been set aflame with fire,<a class='mr'></a> and a dark cloud and thick darkness and a storm,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>and the blast of a trumpet<a class='mr'></a> and the voice speaking words,<a class='mr'></a> which on hearing, the people begged that nothing further should be spoken to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>For they could not bear the command: “If even a beast touches the mountain, it must be stoned.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Also, the display was so terrifying that Moses said: “I am afraid and trembling.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>But you have approached a Mount Zion<a class='mr'></a> and a city of the living God, heavenly Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> and myriads<a class='fn'></a> of angels <span id='dcv_12_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>in general assembly,<a class='mr'></a> and the congregation of the firstborn who have been enrolled in the heavens, and God the Judge of all,<a class='mr'></a> and the spiritual lives<a class='mr'></a> of righteous ones who have been made perfect,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>and Jesus the mediator<a class='mr'></a> of a new covenant,<a class='mr'></a> and the sprinkled blood, which speaks in a better way than Abel’s blood.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>See that you do not refuse to listen to<a class='fn'></a> the one who is speaking. For if those who refused to listen to the one giving divine warning on earth did not escape, how much more will we not escape if we turn away from him who speaks from the heavens!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>At that time his voice shook the earth,<a class='mr'></a> but now he has promised: “Yet once more I will shake not only the earth but also the heaven.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Now the expression “yet once more” indicates the removal of the things that are shaken, things that have been made, in order that the things not shaken may remain. <span id='dcv_12_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Therefore, seeing that we are to receive a Kingdom that cannot be shaken, let us continue to receive undeserved kindness, through which we may acceptably offer God sacred service with godly fear and awe. <span id='dcv_12_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>For our God is a consuming fire.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Let your brotherly love continue.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Do not forget hospitality,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for through it some unknowingly entertained angels.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Keep in mind those in prison,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> as though you were imprisoned with them,<a class='mr'></a> and those being mistreated, since you yourselves also are in the body.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Let marriage be honorable among all, and let the marriage bed be without defilement,<a class='mr'></a> for God will judge sexually immoral people<a class='fn'></a> and adulterers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Let your way of life be free of the love of money,<a class='mr'></a> while you are content with the present things.<a class='mr'></a> For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Remember those who are taking the lead among you,<a class='mr'></a> who have spoken the word of God to you, and as you contemplate how their conduct turns out, imitate their faith.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and today, and forever.</p></div><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Do not be led astray by various and strange teachings, for it is better for the heart to be strengthened by undeserved kindness than by foods,<a class='fn'></a> which do not benefit those occupied with them.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>We have an altar from which those who offer sacred service at the tent have no authority to eat.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For the bodies of those animals whose blood is taken into the holy place as a sin offering by the high priest are burned up outside the camp.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Therefore, Jesus also suffered outside the city gate<a class='mr'></a> in order to sanctify the people with his own blood.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Let us, then, go to him outside the camp, bearing the reproach he bore,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>for we do not have here a city that remains, but we are earnestly seeking the one to come.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Through him let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise,<a class='mr'></a> that is, the fruit of our lips<a class='mr'></a> that make public declaration to his name.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Moreover, do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others,<a class='mr'></a> for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Be obedient to those who are taking the lead among you<a class='mr'></a> and be submissive,<a class='mr'></a> for they are keeping watch over you<a class='fn'></a> as those who will render an account,<a class='mr'></a> so that they may do this with joy and not with sighing, for this would be damaging to you.</p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Keep praying for us, for we trust we have an honest<a class='fn'></a> conscience, as we wish to conduct ourselves honestly in all things.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>But I especially urge you to pray so that I may be restored to you the sooner.</p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Now may the God of peace, who brought up from the dead the great shepherd<a class='mr'></a> of the sheep, our Lord Jesus, with the blood of an everlasting covenant, <span id='dcv_13_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>equip you with every good thing to do his will, working in us through Jesus Christ what is well-pleasing in his sight, to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen.</p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Now I urge you, brothers, to listen patiently to this word of encouragement, for I have written you a short letter. <span id='dcv_13_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>I want you to know that our brother Timothy has been released. If he comes soon, I will be with him when I see you.</p></div><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Give my greetings to all those who are taking the lead among you and to all the holy ones. Those in Italy<a class='mr'></a> send you their greetings.</p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>The undeserved kindness be with all of you.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>
