<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have observed and our hands have felt, concerning the word of life,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>(yes, the life was made manifest, and we have seen and are bearing witness<a class='mr'></a> and reporting to you the everlasting life<a class='mr'></a> that was with the Father and was made manifest to us), <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>that which we have seen and heard we are reporting also to you,<a class='mr'></a> so that you too may have fellowship<a class='fn'></a> with us. And this fellowship of ours is with the Father and with his Son Jesus Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>And we are writing these things so that our joy may be complete.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>This is the message that we heard from him and are announcing to you: God is light,<a class='mr'></a> and there is no darkness at all in him.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>If we make the statement, “We are having fellowship with him,” and yet we go on walking in the darkness, we are lying and are not practicing the truth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>However, if we are walking in the light as he himself is in the light, we do have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus his Son cleanses us from all sin.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>If we make the statement, “We have no sin,” we are misleading ourselves<a class='mr'></a> and the truth is not in us. <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous so as to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>If we make the statement, “We have not sinned,” we are making him a liar, and his word is not in us.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>My little children, I am writing you these things so that you may not commit a sin. And yet, if anyone does commit a sin, we have a helper<a class='fn'></a> with the Father, Jesus Christ,<a class='mr'></a> a righteous one.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>And he is a propitiatory sacrifice<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for our sins,<a class='mr'></a> yet not for ours only but also for the whole world’s.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And by this we realize that we have come to know him, namely, if we continue observing his commandments. <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>The one who says, “I have come to know him,” and yet does not observe his commandments is a liar, and the truth is not in this person. <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>But whoever does observe his word, in this person the love of God has truly been made perfect.<a class='mr'></a> By this we know that we are in union with him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>The one who says he remains in union with him is himself under obligation to go on walking just as that one walked.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Beloved ones, I am writing you, not a new commandment, but an old commandment that you have had from the beginning.<a class='mr'></a> This old commandment is the word that you heard. <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Again, I am writing you a new commandment, which is true in his case and in yours, because the darkness is passing away and the true light is already shining.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>The one who says that he is in the light and yet hates<a class='mr'></a> his brother is still in the darkness.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>The one who loves his brother remains in the light,<a class='mr'></a> and in him there is no cause for stumbling. <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But the one who hates his brother is in the darkness and is walking in the darkness,<a class='mr'></a> and he does not know where he is going,<a class='mr'></a> because the darkness has blinded his eyes.</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>I am writing you, little children, because your sins have been forgiven you for the sake of his name.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>I am writing you, fathers, because you have come to know him who is from the beginning. I am writing you, young men, because you have conquered the wicked one.<a class='mr'></a> I write you, young children, because you have come to know the Father.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>I write you, fathers, because you have come to know him who is from the beginning. I write you, young men, because you are strong<a class='mr'></a> and the word of God remains in you<a class='mr'></a> and you have conquered the wicked one.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Do not love either the world or the things in the world.<a class='mr'></a> If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh<a class='mr'></a> and the desire of the eyes<a class='mr'></a> and the showy display of one’s means of life<a class='fn'></a>—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world. <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire,<a class='mr'></a> but the one who does the will of God remains forever.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Young children, it is the last hour, and just as you have heard that the antichrist is coming,<a class='mr'></a> even now many antichrists have appeared,<a class='mr'></a> from which fact we know that it is the last hour. <span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>They went out from us, but they were not of our sort;<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for if they had been of our sort, they would have remained with us. But they went out so that it might be shown that not all are of our sort.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>And you have an anointing from the holy one,<a class='mr'></a> and all of you have knowledge. <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>I write you, not because you do not know the truth,<a class='mr'></a> but because you know it, and because no lie originates with the truth.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Who is the liar but the one who denies that Jesus is the Christ?<a class='mr'></a> This is the antichrist,<a class='mr'></a> the one who denies the Father and the Son. <span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Everyone who denies the Son does not have the Father either.<a class='mr'></a> But whoever acknowledges the Son<a class='mr'></a> has the Father also.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>As for you, what you have heard from the beginning must remain in you.<a class='mr'></a> If what you have heard from the beginning remains in you, you will also remain in union with the Son and in union with the Father. <span id='dcv_2_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Furthermore, this is what he himself promised us—the life everlasting.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>I write you these things about those who are trying to mislead you. <span id='dcv_2_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>And as for you, the anointing that you received from him<a class='mr'></a> remains in you, and you do not need anyone to be teaching you; but the anointing from him is teaching you about all things<a class='mr'></a> and is true and is no lie. Just as it has taught you, remain in union with him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>So now, little children, remain in union with him, so that when he is made manifest we may have freeness of speech<a class='mr'></a> and not shrink away from him in shame at his presence. <span id='dcv_2_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>If you know that he is righteous, you also know that everyone who practices righteousness has been born from him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>See what sort of love the Father has given us,<a class='mr'></a> that we should be called children of God!<a class='mr'></a> And that is what we are. That is why the world does not know us,<a class='mr'></a> because it has not come to know him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Beloved ones, we are now children of God,<a class='mr'></a> but it has not yet been made manifest what we will be.<a class='mr'></a> We do know that when he is made manifest we will be like him, because we will see him just as he is. <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And everyone who has this hope in him purifies himself,<a class='mr'></a> just as that one is pure.</p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Everyone who practices sin is also practicing lawlessness, and sin is lawlessness. <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>You know, too, that he was made manifest to take away our sins,<a class='mr'></a> and there is no sin in him. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Everyone remaining in union with him does not practice sin;<a class='mr'></a> no one who practices sin has either seen him or come to know him. <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Little children, let no one mislead you; the one who practices righteousness is righteous, just as that one is righteous. <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>The one who practices sin originates with the Devil, because the Devil has been sinning from the beginning.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> For this purpose the Son of God was made manifest, to break up<a class='fn'></a> the works of the Devil.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Everyone who has been born from God does not practice sin,<a class='mr'></a> for His seed<a class='fn'></a> remains in such one, and he cannot practice sin, for he has been born from God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>The children of God and the children of the Devil are evident by this fact: Whoever does not practice righteousness does not originate with God, nor does the one who does not love his brother.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For this is the message that you have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>not like Cain, who originated with the wicked one and slaughtered his brother.<a class='mr'></a> And for what reason did he slaughter him? Because his own works were wicked,<a class='mr'></a> but those of his brother were righteous.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Do not be surprised, brothers, that the world hates you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>We know that we have passed over from death to life,<a class='mr'></a> because we love the brothers.<a class='mr'></a> The one who does not love remains in death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Everyone who hates his brother is a murderer,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and you know that no murderer has everlasting life remaining in him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>By this we have come to know love, because that one surrendered his life<a class='fn'></a> for us,<a class='mr'></a> and we are under obligation to surrender our lives<a class='fn'></a> for our brothers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>But whoever has the material possessions of this world and sees his brother in need and yet refuses to show him compassion, in what way does the love of God remain in him?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Little children, we should love, not in word or with the tongue,<a class='mr'></a> but in deed<a class='mr'></a> and truth.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>By this we will know that we originate with the truth, and we will assure<a class='fn'></a> our hearts before him <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>regarding whatever our hearts may condemn us in, because God is greater than our hearts and knows all things.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Beloved ones, if our hearts do not condemn us, we have freeness of speech toward God;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>and whatever we ask we receive from him,<a class='mr'></a> because we are observing his commandments and doing what is pleasing in his eyes. <span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Indeed, this is his commandment: that we have faith in the name of his Son Jesus Christ<a class='mr'></a> and love one another,<a class='mr'></a> just as he gave us a commandment. <span id='dcv_3_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Moreover, the one who observes his commandments remains in union with him, and he in union with such one.<a class='mr'></a> And by the spirit that he gave us, we know that he remains in union with us.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Beloved ones, do not believe every inspired statement,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> but test the inspired statements<a class='fn'></a> to see whether they originate with God,<a class='mr'></a> for many false prophets have gone out into the world.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>This is how you know that the inspired statement is from God: Every inspired statement that acknowledges Jesus Christ as having come in the flesh originates with God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But every inspired statement that does not acknowledge Jesus does not originate with God.<a class='mr'></a> Furthermore, this is the antichrist’s inspired statement that you have heard was coming,<a class='mr'></a> and now it is already in the world.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>You originate with God, little children, and you have conquered them,<a class='mr'></a> because the one who is in union with you<a class='mr'></a> is greater than the one who is in union with the world.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>They originate with the world;<a class='mr'></a> that is why they speak what originates with the world and the world listens to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>We originate with God. Whoever comes to know God listens to us;<a class='mr'></a> whoever does not originate with God does not listen to us.<a class='mr'></a> By this we distinguish the inspired statement of truth from the inspired statement of error.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Beloved ones, let us continue loving one another,<a class='mr'></a> because love is from God, and everyone who loves has been born from God and knows God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>By this the love of God was revealed in our case, that God sent his only-begotten Son<a class='mr'></a> into the world so that we might gain life through him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>The love is in this respect, not that we have loved God, but that he loved us and sent his Son as a propitiatory sacrifice<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for our sins.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Beloved ones, if this is how God loved us, then we are also under obligation to love one another.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>No one has seen God at any time.<a class='mr'></a> If we continue loving one another, God remains in us and his love is made perfect in us.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>By this we know that we are remaining in union with him and he in union with us, because he has given his spirit to us. <span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>In addition, we ourselves have seen and are bearing witness that the Father has sent his Son as Savior of the world.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Whoever acknowledges that Jesus is God’s Son,<a class='mr'></a> God remains in union with such one and he in union with God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And we have come to know and believe the love that God has for us.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'>God is love,<a class='mr'></a> and the one who remains in love remains in union with God and God remains in union with him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>In this way love has been made perfect in us, so that we may have freeness of speech<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> in the day of judgment, because just as that one is, so are we ourselves in this world. <span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>There is no fear in love,<a class='mr'></a> but perfect love casts<a class='fn'></a> fear out, because fear restrains us. Indeed, the one who is fearful has not been made perfect in love.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>We love, because he first loved us.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>If anyone says, “I love God,” and yet is hating his brother, he is a liar.<a class='mr'></a> For the one who does not love his brother,<a class='mr'></a> whom he has seen, cannot love God, whom he has not seen.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>And we have this commandment from him, that whoever loves God must also love his brother.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Everyone who believes that Jesus is the Christ has been born from God,<a class='mr'></a> and everyone who loves the one who caused to be born loves him who has been born from that one. <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>By this we know that we love the children of God,<a class='mr'></a> when we love God and carry out his commandments. <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments;<a class='mr'></a> and yet his commandments are not burdensome,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>because everyone who<a class='fn'></a> has been born from God conquers the world.<a class='mr'></a> And this is the conquest that has conquered the world, our faith.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Who can conquer the world?<a class='mr'></a> Is it not the one who has faith that Jesus is the Son of God?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>This is the one who came by means of water and blood, Jesus Christ, not with the water only,<a class='mr'></a> but with the water and with the blood.<a class='mr'></a> And the spirit is bearing witness,<a class='mr'></a> because the spirit is the truth. <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>For there are three witness bearers: <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>the spirit<a class='mr'></a> and the water<a class='mr'></a> and the blood;<a class='mr'></a> and the three are in agreement.</p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>If we accept the witness of men, the witness of God is greater. Because this is the witness God gives, the witness that he has given about his Son. <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>The person putting his faith in the Son of God has the witness within himself. The person not having faith in God has made him a liar,<a class='mr'></a> because he has not put his faith in the witness given by God concerning his Son. <span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And this is the witness, that God gave us everlasting life,<a class='mr'></a> and this life is in his Son.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>The one who has the Son has this life; the one who does not have the Son of God does not have this life.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>I write you these things so that you may know that you have life everlasting,<a class='mr'></a> you who put your faith in the name of the Son of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>And this is the confidence<a class='fn'></a> that we have toward him,<a class='mr'></a> that no matter what we ask according to his will, he hears us.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>And if we know that he hears us concerning whatever we are asking, we know that we are to have the things we ask for, since we have asked them of him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>If anyone catches sight of his brother committing a sin that does not incur death, he will ask, and God will give life to him,<a class='mr'></a> yes, to those not committing sin that incurs death. There is a sin that does incur death.<a class='mr'></a> It is concerning that sin that I do not tell him to make request. <span id='dcv_5_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>All unrighteousness is sin,<a class='mr'></a> and yet there is a sin that does not incur death.</p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>We know that everyone who has been born from God does not practice sin, but the one born from God<a class='fn'></a> watches him, and the wicked one cannot take hold of him.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>But we know that the Son of God has come,<a class='mr'></a> and he has given us insight<a class='fn'></a> so that we may gain the knowledge of the one who is true. And we are in union with the one who is true,<a class='mr'></a> by means of his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God and life everlasting.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Little children, guard yourselves from idols.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
</bible>
