<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dp'><a>1 </a></span>The beginning of the good news about Jesus Christ, the Son of God: <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Just as it is written in Isaiah the prophet: “(Look! I am sending my messenger ahead of you,<a class='fn'></a> who will prepare your way.)<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>A voice of one crying out in the wilderness: ‘Prepare the way of Jehovah!<a class='fn'></a> Make his roads straight.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>John the Baptizer was in the wilderness, preaching baptism in symbol of repentance for forgiveness of sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And all the territory of Ju·de′a and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem were going out to him, and they were baptized<a class='fn'></a> by him in the Jordan River, openly confessing their sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Now John wore clothing of camel’s hair and a leather belt around his waist,<a class='mr'></a> and he ate locusts and wild honey.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>And he was preaching: “Someone stronger than I am is coming after me, the lace of whose sandals I am not worthy to stoop down and untie.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>I baptized you with water, but he will baptize you with holy spirit.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>In the course of those days, Jesus came from Naz′a·reth of Gal′i·lee and was baptized in the Jordan by John.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>And immediately on coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens being parted and, like a dove, the spirit coming down upon him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And a voice came out of the heavens: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>And immediately the spirit impelled him to go into the wilderness. <span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>So he continued in the wilderness for 40 days, being tempted by Satan.<a class='mr'></a> He was with the wild beasts, but the angels were ministering to him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Now after John was arrested, Jesus went into Gal′i·lee,<a class='mr'></a> preaching the good news of God<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>and saying: “The appointed time has been fulfilled, and the Kingdom of God has drawn near. Repent,<a class='mr'></a> and have faith in the good news.”</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>While walking alongside the Sea of Gal′i·lee, he saw Simon and Simon’s brother Andrew<a class='mr'></a> casting their nets into the sea,<a class='mr'></a> for they were fishermen.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>So Jesus said to them: “Come after me, and I will make you fishers of men.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>And at once they abandoned their nets and followed him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>After going a little farther, he saw James the son of Zeb′e·dee and his brother John, while they were in their boat mending their nets,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>and without delay he called them. So they left their father Zeb′e·dee in the boat with the hired men and went off after him. <span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>And they went into Ca·per′na·um.</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'>As soon as the Sabbath began, he went into the synagogue and started to teach.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>And they were astounded at his way of teaching, for he was teaching them as one having authority, and not as the scribes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Just then there was a man in their synagogue who was under the power of an unclean spirit, and he shouted: <span id='dcv_1_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>“What have we to do with you, Jesus the Naz·a·rene′?<a class='mr'></a> Did you come to destroy us? I know exactly who you are, the Holy One of God!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>But Jesus rebuked it, saying: “Be silent, and come out of him!” <span id='dcv_1_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>And the unclean spirit, after throwing the man into a convulsion and yelling at the top of its voice, came out of him. <span id='dcv_1_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Well, the people were all so astonished that they began to discuss it among themselves, saying: “What is this? A new teaching! He authoritatively orders even the unclean spirits, and they obey him.” <span id='dcv_1_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>So the report about him spread quickly in all directions throughout the entire region of Gal′i·lee.</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>At that they left the synagogue and went to the home of Simon and Andrew with James and John.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Now Simon’s mother-in-law<a class='mr'></a> was lying down sick with a fever, and they at once told him about her. <span id='dcv_1_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Going to her, he took her by the hand and raised her up. The fever left her, and she began ministering to them.</p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>After evening had fallen, when the sun had set, the people began bringing to him all who were ill and demon possessed;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>and the whole city was gathered right at the door. <span id='dcv_1_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>So he cured many who were ill with various sicknesses,<a class='mr'></a> and he expelled many demons, but he would not let the demons speak, for they knew him to be Christ.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Early in the morning, while it was still dark, he got up and went outside and left for an isolated place, and there he began praying.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>However, Simon and those with him hunted him down <span id='dcv_1_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>and found him, and they said to him: “Everyone is looking for you.” <span id='dcv_1_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>But he said to them: “Let us go somewhere else, into the towns nearby, so that I may preach there also, for this is why I have come.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>And he went, preaching in their synagogues throughout the whole of Gal′i·lee and expelling the demons.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>There also came to him a leper, pleading with him even on bended knee, saying to him: “If you just want to, you can make me clean.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>At that he was moved with pity, and he stretched out his hand and touched him, and said to him: “I want to! Be made clean.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>Immediately the leprosy vanished from him, and he became clean. <span id='dcv_1_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>Then he gave him strict orders and at once sent him away, <span id='dcv_1_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>saying to him: “See that you say nothing to anyone, but go show yourself to the priest and offer for your cleansing the things Moses directed,<a class='mr'></a> for a witness to them.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>But after going away, the man started to proclaim it a great deal and to spread the account widely, so that Jesus was no longer able to enter openly into a city, but he stayed outside in isolated places. Yet they kept coming to him from all sides.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>However, after some days he again entered into Ca·per′na·um, and the word spread that he was at home.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>And so many gathered that there was no more room, not even around the door, and he began to speak the word to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>And they brought him a paralytic carried by four men.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>But they could not bring him right to Jesus because of the crowd, so they removed the roof above Jesus, and after digging an opening, they lowered the stretcher on which the paralytic was lying. <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>When Jesus saw their faith,<a class='mr'></a> he said to the paralytic: “Child, your sins are forgiven.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Now some of the scribes were there, sitting and reasoning in their hearts:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>“Why is this man talking this way? He is blaspheming. Who can forgive sins except one, God?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>But immediately Jesus discerned by his spirit that they were reasoning that way among themselves, so he said to them: “Why are you reasoning these things in your hearts?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Which is easier, to say to the paralytic, ‘Your sins are forgiven,’ or to say, ‘Get up and pick up your stretcher and walk’? <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>But in order for you to know that the Son of man<a class='mr'></a> has authority to forgive sins on earth—”<a class='mr'></a> he said to the paralytic: <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>“I say to you, Get up, pick up your stretcher, and go to your home.” <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>At that he got up and immediately picked up his stretcher and walked out in front of them all. So they were all astonished, and they glorified God, saying: “We have never seen anything like this.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Again he went out alongside the sea, and all the crowd kept coming to him, and he began to teach them. <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>And as he was passing by, he caught sight of Le′vi the son of Al·phae′us sitting at the tax office, and he said to him: “Be my follower.” At that he rose up and followed him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Later he was dining<a class='fn'></a> in his house, and many tax collectors and sinners were dining<a class='fn'></a> with Jesus and his disciples, for there were many of them who were following him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>But when the scribes of the Pharisees saw that he was eating with the sinners and tax collectors, they began saying to his disciples: “Does he eat with tax collectors and sinners?” <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>On hearing this, Jesus said to them: “Those who are strong do not need a physician, but those who are ill do. I came to call, not righteous people, but sinners.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Now John’s disciples and the Pharisees practiced fasting. So they came and said to him: “Why do John’s disciples and the disciples of the Pharisees practice fasting, but your disciples do not practice fasting?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>So Jesus said to them: “While the bridegroom<a class='mr'></a> is with them, the friends of the bridegroom have no reason to fast, do they? As long as they have the bridegroom with them, they cannot fast. <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>But days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them,<a class='mr'></a> and then they will fast on that day. <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Nobody sews a patch of unshrunk cloth on an old outer garment. If he does, the new piece pulls away from the old, and the tear becomes worse.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Also, no one puts new wine into old wineskins. If he does, the wine will burst the skins, and the wine is lost as well as the skins. But new wine is put into new wineskins.”</p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Now as he was passing through the grainfields on the Sabbath, his disciples started to pluck the heads of grain as they went.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>So the Pharisees said to him: “Look here! Why are they doing what is not lawful on the Sabbath?” <span id='dcv_2_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>But he said to them: “Have you never read what David did when he was in need and he and the men with him were hungry?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>How, in the account about A·bi′a·thar<a class='mr'></a> the chief priest, he entered into the house of God and ate the loaves of presentation,<a class='fn'></a> which it is not lawful for anybody to eat except the priests,<a class='mr'></a> and he also gave some to the men who were with him?” <span id='dcv_2_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Then he said to them: “The Sabbath came into existence for the sake of man,<a class='mr'></a> and not man for the sake of the Sabbath. <span id='dcv_2_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>So the Son of man is Lord even of the Sabbath.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dp'><a>3 </a></span>Once again he entered into a synagogue, and a man with a withered<a class='fn'></a> hand was there.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So they were watching him closely to see whether he would cure the man on the Sabbath, in order to accuse him. <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He said to the man with the withered<a class='fn'></a> hand: “Get up and come to the center.” <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Next he said to them: “Is it lawful on the Sabbath to do good or to do harm, to save a life<a class='fn'></a> or to kill?”<a class='mr'></a> But they kept silent. <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>After looking around at them with indignation, being thoroughly grieved at the insensibility of their hearts,<a class='mr'></a> he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>At that the Pharisees went out and immediately began holding council with the party followers of Herod<a class='mr'></a> against him, in order to kill him.</p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But Jesus departed for the sea along with his disciples, and a great multitude from Gal′i·lee and from Ju·de′a followed him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Even from Jerusalem and from Id·u·me′a and from across the Jordan and from around Tyre and Si′don, a great multitude came to him when they heard about the many things he was doing. <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And he told his disciples to have a small boat ready for him so that the crowd would not press in on him. <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Because he cured many, all those who had serious diseases were crowding around him to touch him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Even the unclean spirits,<a class='mr'></a> whenever they saw him, would fall down before him and cry out and say: “You are the Son of God.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>But many times he sternly ordered them not to make him known.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>He ascended a mountain and summoned those whom he wanted,<a class='mr'></a> and they came to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>And he formed<a class='fn'></a> a group of 12, whom he also named apostles, those who were to accompany him and whom he would send out to preach <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>and to have authority to expel demons.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And the group of 12<a class='mr'></a> that he formed<a class='fn'></a> were Simon, to whom he also gave the name Peter,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>James the son of Zeb′e·dee and John the brother of James (he also gave these the name Bo·a·ner′ges, which means “Sons of Thunder”),<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Andrew, Philip, Bar·thol′o·mew, Matthew, Thomas, James the son of Al·phae′us, Thad·dae′us, Simon the Ca·na·nae′an,<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>and Judas Is·car′i·ot, who later betrayed him.</p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'>Then he went into a house, <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>and again the crowd gathered, so that they were not able even to eat a meal. <span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>But when his relatives heard about it, they went out to seize him, for they were saying: “He has gone out of his mind.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Also, the scribes who came down from Jerusalem were saying: “He has Be·el′ze·bub,<a class='fn'></a> and he expels the demons by means of the ruler of the demons.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So after calling them to him, he spoke to them with illustrations: “How can Satan expel Satan? <span id='dcv_3_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>If a kingdom becomes divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>and if a house becomes divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand. <span id='dcv_3_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>Also, if Satan has risen up against himself and has become divided, he cannot stand but is coming to an end. <span id='dcv_3_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>In fact, no one who enters the house of a strong man is able to steal his possessions unless he first ties up the strong man. Only then can he plunder his house. <span id='dcv_3_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Truly I say to you that all things will be forgiven the sons of men, no matter what sins they commit and what blasphemies they speak. <span id='dcv_3_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>But whoever blasphemes against the holy spirit has no forgiveness forever<a class='mr'></a> but is guilty of everlasting sin.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>He said this because they were saying: “He has an unclean spirit.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>Now his mother and his brothers<a class='mr'></a> came, and standing outside, they sent someone in to call him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>As there was a crowd sitting around him, they said to him: “Look! Your mother and your brothers are outside asking for you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>But he replied to them: “Who are my mother and my brothers?” <span id='dcv_3_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Then he looked at those sitting around him in a circle and said: “See, my mother and my brothers!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>Whoever does the will of God, this one is my brother and sister and mother.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Again he began teaching beside the sea, and a very large crowd gathered near him. So he went aboard a boat and sat in it away from the shore, but the whole crowd was next to the sea, along the shore.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>And he began to teach them many things with illustrations,<a class='mr'></a> and while he was teaching, he said to them:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>“Listen. Look! The sower went out to sow.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>As he was sowing, some seeds fell alongside the road, and the birds came and ate them up. <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Others fell on rocky ground where there was not much soil, and they immediately sprang up because the soil was not deep.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But when the sun rose, they were scorched, and they withered because they had no root. <span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Other seeds fell among the thorns, and the thorns came up and choked them, and they yielded no fruit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But others fell on the fine soil, and growing up and increasing, they began to yield fruit, and they were bearing 30, 60, and 100 times more.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then he added: “Let the one who has ears to listen, listen.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now when he was alone, those around him with the Twelve began questioning him about the illustrations.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>He said to them: “To you the sacred secret<a class='mr'></a> of the Kingdom of God has been given, but to those outside all things are in illustrations,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>so that, though looking, they may look and still not see, and though hearing, they may hear and still not get the sense of it; nor will they ever turn back and receive forgiveness.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Further, he said to them: “You do not know this illustration, so how will you understand all the other illustrations?</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>“The sower sows the word.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>These, then, are the ones alongside the road where the word is sown; but as soon as they have heard it, Satan comes<a class='mr'></a> and takes away the word that was sown in them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Likewise, these are the ones sown on rocky ground; as soon as they have heard the word, they accept it with joy.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Yet they have no root in themselves, but they continue for a time; then as soon as tribulation or persecution arises because of the word, they are stumbled. <span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>There are still others that are sown among the thorns. These are the ones who have heard the word,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>but the anxieties<a class='mr'></a> of this system of things<a class='fn'></a> and the deceptive power of riches<a class='mr'></a> and the desires<a class='mr'></a> for everything else make inroads and choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful. <span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Finally, the ones that were sown on the fine soil are those who listen to the word and favorably receive it and bear fruit—30, 60, and 100 times more.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>He also said to them: “A lamp is not brought out to be put under a basket<a class='fn'></a> or under a bed, is it? Is it not brought out to be put on a lampstand?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>For there is nothing hidden that will not be exposed; nothing is carefully concealed that will not come out in the open.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Whoever has ears to listen, let him listen.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>He further said to them: “Pay attention to what you are hearing.<a class='mr'></a> With the measure that you are measuring out, you will have it measured out to you, yes, you will have more added to you. <span id='dcv_4_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>For whoever has will have more given to him,<a class='mr'></a> but whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>So he went on to say: “In this way the Kingdom of God is just as when a man casts seeds on the ground. <span id='dcv_4_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>He sleeps at night and rises up by day, and the seeds sprout and grow tall—just how, he does not know. <span id='dcv_4_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>On its own the ground bears fruit gradually, first the stalk, then the head, finally the full grain in the head. <span id='dcv_4_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>But as soon as the crop permits it, he thrusts in the sickle, because the harvesttime has come.”</p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>And he went on to say: “With what can we compare the Kingdom of God, or with what illustration can we explain it? <span id='dcv_4_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>It is like a mustard grain, which at the time it was sown in the ground was the tiniest of all the seeds on the earth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>But when it has been sown, it grows and becomes greater than all other vegetable plants and produces great branches, so that the birds of heaven are able to find lodging under its shadow.”</p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>With many illustrations<a class='mr'></a> of that sort he spoke the word to them, to the extent that they were able to listen. <span id='dcv_4_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>Indeed, without an illustration he would not speak to them, but he would explain all things privately to his disciples.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>And on that day, when evening had fallen, he said to them: “Let us cross to the other shore.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>So after they had dismissed the crowd, they took him in the boat, just as he was, and there were other boats with him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>Now a great violent windstorm broke out, and the waves kept crashing into the boat, so that the boat was close to being swamped.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>But he was in the stern, sleeping on the pillow.<a class='fn'></a> So they woke him up and said to him: “Teacher, do you not care that we are about to perish?” <span id='dcv_4_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>With that he got up and rebuked the wind and said to the sea: “Hush! Be quiet!”<a class='mr'></a> And the wind abated, and a great calm set in. <span id='dcv_4_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>So he said to them: “Why are you so afraid?<a class='fn'></a> Do you not yet have any faith?” <span id='dcv_4_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>But they felt an unusual fear, and they said to one another: “Who really is this? Even the wind and the sea obey him.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then they came to the other side of the sea into the region of the Ger′a·senes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>And immediately after Jesus got out of the boat, a man under the power of an unclean spirit met him from among the tombs.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>His haunt was among the tombs, and up to that time, absolutely no one was able to bind him securely, even with a chain. <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>He had often been bound with fetters and chains, but he snapped the chains apart and smashed the fetters; and nobody had the strength to subdue him. <span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And continually, night and day, he was crying out in the tombs and in the mountains and slashing himself with stones. <span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But on catching sight of Jesus from a distance, he ran and bowed down to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then he cried out with a loud voice: “What have I to do with you, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I put you under oath by God not to torment me.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>For Jesus had been saying to it: “Come out of the man, you unclean spirit.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But Jesus asked him: “What is your name?” And he replied: “My name is Legion, because there are many of us.” <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>And he kept pleading with Jesus not to send the spirits out of the country.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Now a great herd of swine<a class='mr'></a> was feeding there at the mountain.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>So the spirits pleaded with him: “Send us into the swine, so that we may enter into them.” <span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>And he gave them permission. With that the unclean spirits came out and went into the swine, and the herd rushed over the precipice<a class='fn'></a> into the sea, about 2,000 of them, and were drowned in the sea. <span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But their herders fled and reported it in the city and in the countryside, and people came to see what had happened.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>So they came to Jesus and saw the demon-possessed man, the one who previously had the Legion, sitting clothed and in his right mind, and they grew fearful. <span id='dcv_5_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Also, those who had seen it related to them how this had happened to the demon-possessed man and the swine. <span id='dcv_5_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>So they began to plead with Jesus to go away from their region.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Now as he was boarding the boat, the man who had been demon-possessed pleaded to go with him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>However, he did not let him but said to him: “Go home to your relatives, and report to them all the things Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> has done for you and the mercy he has shown you.” <span id='dcv_5_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>This man went away and started to proclaim in the De·cap′o·lis<a class='fn'></a> all the things Jesus had done for him, and all the people were amazed.</p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>After Jesus had crossed again by boat to the opposite shore, a large crowd gathered together to him, and he was by the sea.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>One of the presiding officers of the synagogue, named Ja′i·rus, now came, and on catching sight of him, he fell at his feet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>He pleaded with him many times, saying: “My little daughter is extremely ill.<a class='fn'></a> Please come and put your hands on her<a class='mr'></a> so that she may get well and live.” <span id='dcv_5_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>At that Jesus went with him, and a large crowd was following him and pressing against him.</p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Now there was a woman who had had a flow of blood<a class='mr'></a> for 12 years.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>She had suffered much<a class='fn'></a> at the hands of many physicians and had spent all her resources, and she was no better but, rather, had become worse. <span id='dcv_5_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>When she heard the reports about Jesus, she came up behind him in the crowd and touched his outer garment,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>for she kept saying: “If I touch just his outer garments, I will get well.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>And immediately her flow of blood dried up, and she sensed in her body that she had been healed of the grievous sickness.</p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>Immediately Jesus realized in himself that power<a class='mr'></a> had gone out of him, and he turned around in the crowd and asked: “Who touched my outer garments?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>But his disciples said to him: “You see the crowd pressing in on you, and you ask, ‘Who touched me?’” <span id='dcv_5_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>However, he was looking around to see who had done this. <span id='dcv_5_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>The woman, frightened and trembling, knowing what had happened to her, came and fell down before him and told him the whole truth. <span id='dcv_5_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>He said to her: “Daughter, your faith has made you well. Go in peace,<a class='mr'></a> and be healed from your grievous sickness.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>While he was yet speaking, some men from the home of the presiding officer of the synagogue came and said: “Your daughter died! Why bother the Teacher any longer?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>But Jesus overheard their words and said to the presiding officer of the synagogue: “Have no fear,<a class='fn'></a> only exercise faith.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>Now he did not let anyone follow him except Peter, James, and John the brother of James.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>So they came to the house of the presiding officer of the synagogue, and he saw the commotion and those weeping and wailing loudly.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>After stepping in, he said to them: “Why are you weeping and causing this commotion? The child has not died but is sleeping.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>At this they began to laugh at him scornfully. But after sending them all outside, he took the child’s father and mother and those with him, and he went in where the child was. <span id='dcv_5_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>Then, taking the hand of the child, he said to her: <i>“Tal′i·tha cu′mi,”</i> which, when translated, means: “Little girl, I say to you, ‘Get up!’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>And immediately the girl rose and began walking. (She was 12 years old.) And at once they were beside themselves with great ecstasy. <span id='dcv_5_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>But he ordered them again and again<a class='fn'></a> to let no one learn of this,<a class='mr'></a> and he said that something should be given her to eat.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dp'><a>6 </a></span>He departed from there and came into his home territory,<a class='mr'></a> and his disciples followed him. <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>When it was the Sabbath, he started teaching in the synagogue, and most who heard him were astounded and said: “Where did this man get these things?<a class='mr'></a> And why should this wisdom have been given to him, and such powerful works be performed through his hands?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>This is the carpenter,<a class='mr'></a> the son of Mary<a class='mr'></a> and the brother of James,<a class='mr'></a> Joseph, Judas, and Simon,<a class='mr'></a> is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble because of him. <span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>But Jesus said to them: “A prophet is not without honor except in his home territory and among his relatives and in his own house.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So he was not able to do any powerful work there except to lay his hands on a few sick people and cure them. <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Indeed, he was amazed at their lack of faith. And he went around in a circuit to the villages, teaching.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>He now summoned the Twelve and started sending them out two by two,<a class='mr'></a> and he gave them authority over the unclean spirits.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Also, he gave them orders to carry nothing for the trip except a staff—no bread, no food pouch, no money<a class='fn'></a> in their belts<a class='mr'></a>— <span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>but to put on sandals and not to wear two garments.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Further, he said to them: “Wherever you enter into a home, stay there until you leave that place.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And wherever a place will not receive you or listen to you, on going out from there, shake off the dirt that is on your feet for a witness to them.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then they set out and preached that people should repent,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>and they expelled many demons<a class='mr'></a> and greased many sick people with oil and cured them.</p></div><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Now King Herod heard of this, for the name of Jesus became well-known, and people were saying: “John the Baptizer has been raised up from the dead, and that is why the powerful works are operating in him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>But others were saying: “It is E·li′jah.” Still others were saying: “It is a prophet like one of the prophets of old.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>But when Herod heard it, he said: “The John whom I beheaded, this one has been raised up.” <span id='dcv_6_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>For Herod himself had sent out and arrested John and had bound him in prison on account of He·ro′di·as, the wife of Philip his brother, because he had married her.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>For John had been saying to Herod: “It is not lawful for you to have your brother’s wife.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So He·ro′di·as was nursing a grudge against him and wanted to kill him, but she could not. <span id='dcv_6_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>For Herod was in fear of John, knowing him to be a righteous and holy man,<a class='mr'></a> and he was keeping him safe. After hearing him, he was at a great loss as to what to do, yet he continued to hear him gladly.</p></div><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>But a convenient day arrived when Herod spread an evening meal on his birthday<a class='mr'></a> for his high officials and the military commanders and the most prominent men of Gal′i·lee.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>And the daughter of He·ro′di·as came in and danced and pleased Herod and those dining<a class='fn'></a> with him. The king said to the girl: “Ask me for whatever you want, and I will give it to you.” <span id='dcv_6_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Yes, he swore to her: “Whatever you ask me for, I will give it to you, up to half my kingdom.” <span id='dcv_6_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>So she went out and said to her mother: “What should I ask for?” She said: “The head of John the Baptizer.” <span id='dcv_6_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>She immediately rushed in to the king and made her request, saying: “I want you to give me right away on a platter the head of John the Baptist.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Although this deeply grieved him, the king did not want to disregard her request, because of his oaths and his guests.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>So the king immediately sent a bodyguard and commanded him to bring John’s head. So he went off and beheaded him in the prison <span id='dcv_6_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>and brought his head on a platter. He gave it to the girl, and the girl gave it to her mother. <span id='dcv_6_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>When his disciples heard of it, they came and took his body and laid it in a tomb.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>The apostles gathered around Jesus and reported to him all the things they had done and taught.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>And he said to them: “Come, you yourselves, privately into an isolated place and rest up a little.”<a class='mr'></a> For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure time even to eat a meal. <span id='dcv_6_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>So they set off in the boat for an isolated place to be by themselves.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>But people saw them going and many got to know it, and from all the cities they ran together on foot and got there ahead of them. <span id='dcv_6_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them,<a class='mr'></a> because they were as sheep without a shepherd.<a class='mr'></a> And he started to teach them many things.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>By now the hour had grown late, and his disciples came up to him and said: “This place is isolated, and the hour is already late.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>Send them away, so that they may go off into the surrounding countryside and villages and buy themselves something to eat.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>He replied to them: “You give them something to eat.” At this they said to him: “Should we go off and buy 200 de·nar′i·i<a class='fn'></a> worth of bread and give it to the people to eat?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>He said to them: “How many loaves do you have? Go see!” After finding out, they said: “Five, besides two fish.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>And he instructed all the people to recline in groups on the green grass.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>So they reclined in groups of 100 and of 50. <span id='dcv_6_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>Taking now the five loaves and the two fish, he looked up to heaven and said a blessing.<a class='mr'></a> Then he broke the loaves up and began giving them to the disciples to place them before the people, and he divided up the two fish for all. <span id='dcv_6_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>So they all ate and were satisfied, <span id='dcv_6_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>and they took up 12 baskets full of fragments, aside from the fish.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>Those who ate the loaves were 5,000 men.</p></div><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>Then, without delay, he made his disciples board the boat and go on ahead to the opposite shore toward Beth·sa′i·da, while he himself sent the crowd away.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>But after saying good-bye to them, he went to a mountain to pray.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>When evening had fallen, the boat was in the middle of the sea, but he was alone on the land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_48' class='dv dx dp'><a>48 </a></span>So when he saw them struggling to row, for the wind was against them, about the fourth watch of the night<a class='fn'></a> he came toward them, walking on the sea; but he was inclined to<a class='fn'></a> pass them by. <span id='dcv_6_49' class='dv dx dp'><a>49 </a></span>On catching sight of him walking on the sea, they thought: “It is an apparition!” And they cried out. <span id='dcv_6_50' class='dv dp'><a>50 </a></span>For they all saw him and were troubled. But immediately he spoke to them and said: “Take courage! It is I; do not be afraid.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_51' class='dv dp'><a>51 </a></span>Then he got up into the boat with them, and the wind abated. At this they were utterly amazed, <span id='dcv_6_52' class='dv dx dp'><a>52 </a></span>for they had not grasped the meaning of the loaves, but their hearts continued dull in understanding.</p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_53' class='dv dp'><a>53 </a></span>When they got across to land, they came to Gen·nes′a·ret and anchored the boat nearby.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_54' class='dv dp'><a>54 </a></span>But as soon as they got out of the boat, people recognized him. <span id='dcv_6_55' class='dv dp'><a>55 </a></span>They ran around all that region and started to bring on stretchers those who were ailing to where they heard he was. <span id='dcv_6_56' class='dv dp'><a>56 </a></span>And wherever he would enter into villages or cities or the countryside, they would place the sick ones in the marketplaces, and they would plead with him that they might touch just the fringe of his outer garment.<a class='mr'></a> And all those who touched it were made well.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Now the Pharisees and some of the scribes who had come from Jerusalem gathered around him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>And they saw some of his disciples eat their meal with defiled hands, that is, unwashed ones.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>(For the Pharisees and all the Jews do not eat unless they wash their hands up to the elbow, clinging to the tradition of the men of former times, <span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>and when they come from the market, they do not eat unless they wash themselves. There are many other traditions that they have received and cling to, such as baptisms of cups, pitchers, and copper vessels.)<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So these Pharisees and scribes asked him: “Why do your disciples not observe the tradition of the men of former times, but they eat their meal with defiled hands?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>He said to them: “Isaiah aptly prophesied about you hypocrites, as it is written, ‘This people honor me with their lips, but their hearts are far removed from me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>It is in vain that they keep worshipping me, for they teach commands of men as doctrines.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>You let go of the commandment of God and cling to the tradition of men.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Further, he said to them: “You skillfully disregard the commandment of God in order to keep your tradition.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>For example, Moses said, ‘Honor your father and your mother,’<a class='mr'></a> and, ‘Let the one who speaks abusively of<a class='fn'></a> his father or mother be put to death.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But you say, ‘If a man says to his father or his mother: “Whatever I have that could benefit you is corban (that is, a gift dedicated to God),”’ <span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>you no longer let him do a single thing for his father or his mother.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Thus you make the word of God invalid by your tradition that you have handed down.<a class='mr'></a> And you do many things like this.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>So calling the crowd to him again, he said to them: “Listen to me, all of you, and understand the meaning.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Nothing from outside a man that enters into him can defile him; but the things that come out of a man are the things that defile him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_16' class='dv dp'><a>16<a class='fn'></a> </a></span>——</p></div><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Now when he had entered a house away from the crowd, his disciples began to question him about the illustration.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So he said to them: “Are you also without understanding like them? Are you not aware that nothing from outside that enters into a man can defile him, <span id='dcv_7_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>since it enters, not into his heart, but into his stomach, and it passes out into the sewer?” Thus he declared all foods clean. <span id='dcv_7_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Further, he said: “That which comes out of a man is what defiles him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>For from inside, out of the heart of men,<a class='mr'></a> come injurious reasonings, sexual immorality,<a class='fn'></a> thefts, murders, <span id='dcv_7_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>acts of adultery, greed, acts of wickedness, deceit, brazen conduct,<a class='fn'></a> an envious eye, blasphemy, haughtiness, and unreasonableness. <span id='dcv_7_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>All these wicked things come from within and defile a man.”</p></div><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>He rose up from there and went into the region of Tyre and Si′don.<a class='mr'></a> There he entered into a house and did not want anyone to know it, but he could not escape notice. <span id='dcv_7_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Immediately, a woman whose little daughter had an unclean spirit heard about him and came and fell down at his feet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>The woman was a Greek, a Sy·ro·phoe·ni′cian by nationality;<a class='fn'></a> and she kept asking him to expel the demon from her daughter. <span id='dcv_7_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>But he said to her: “First let the children be satisfied, for it is not right to take the bread of the children and throw it to the little dogs.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>But she replied to him: “Yes, sir, and yet even the little dogs underneath the table eat of the crumbs of the little children.” <span id='dcv_7_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>At that he said to her: “Because you said this, go; the demon has gone out of your daughter.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So she went away to her home and found the young child lying on the bed, and the demon was gone.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>When Jesus returned from the region of Tyre, he went through Si′don to the Sea of Gal′i·lee, through the region of De·cap′o·lis.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Here they brought him a deaf man with a speech impediment,<a class='mr'></a> and they pleaded with him to lay his hand on him. <span id='dcv_7_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>And he took him aside privately, away from the crowd. Then he put his fingers into the man’s ears, and after spitting, he touched his tongue.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>And looking up into heaven, he sighed deeply and said to him: <i>“Eph′pha·tha,”</i> that is, “Be opened.” <span id='dcv_7_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>At this his ears were opened,<a class='mr'></a> and his speech impediment was removed, and he began speaking normally. <span id='dcv_7_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>With that he ordered them not to tell anyone,<a class='mr'></a> but the more he would order them, the more they would proclaim it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>Indeed, they were astounded beyond measure,<a class='mr'></a> and they said: “He has done all things well. He even makes the deaf hear and the speechless speak.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>In those days, there was again a large crowd, and they had nothing to eat. So he summoned the disciples and said to them: <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“I feel pity for the crowd,<a class='mr'></a> because they have already stayed with me for three days and they have nothing to eat.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>If I send them off to their homes hungry,<a class='fn'></a> they will give out on the road, and some of them are from far away.” <span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>But his disciples answered him: “From where will anyone get enough bread in this isolated place to satisfy these people?” <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>At this he asked them: “How many loaves do you have?” They said: “Seven.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>And he instructed the crowd to recline on the ground. Then he took the seven loaves, gave thanks, broke them, and began giving them to his disciples to serve, and they served them to the crowd.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>They also had a few small fish, and blessing these, he told them to serve these also. <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>So they ate and were satisfied, and they took up seven large baskets<a class='fn'></a> full of leftover fragments.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Now there were about 4,000 men. Then he sent them away.</p></div><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Immediately he boarded the boat with his disciples and came into the region of Dal·ma·nu′tha.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Here the Pharisees came and started disputing with him, demanding from him a sign from heaven, to put him to the test.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>So he sighed deeply in his spirit and said: “Why does this generation seek a sign?<a class='mr'></a> Truly I say, no sign will be given to this generation.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>With that he left them, got aboard again, and went to the opposite shore.</p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>However, they forgot to take bread along, and they had nothing with them in the boat except for one loaf.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>And he warned them in no uncertain terms: “Keep your eyes open; look out for the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>So they began arguing with one another over the fact that they had no bread. <span id='dcv_8_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Noting this, he said to them: “Why do you argue over your having no bread? Do you not yet perceive and understand? Are your hearts still dull in understanding? <span id='dcv_8_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>‘Though having eyes, do you not see; and though having ears, do you not hear?’ Do you not remember <span id='dcv_8_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>when I broke the five loaves<a class='mr'></a> for the 5,000 men, how many baskets full of fragments you collected?” They said to him: “Twelve.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>“When I broke the seven loaves for the 4,000 men, how many large baskets<a class='fn'></a> full of fragments did you take up?” And they said to him: “Seven.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>With that he said to them: “Do you not yet understand?”</p></div><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Now they put in at Beth·sa′i·da. Here people brought him a blind man, and they pleaded with him to touch him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>And he took the blind man by the hand and brought him outside the village. After spitting on his eyes,<a class='mr'></a> he laid his hands on him and asked him: “Do you see anything?” <span id='dcv_8_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>The man looked up and said: “I see people, but they look like trees walking about.” <span id='dcv_8_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Again he laid his hands on the man’s eyes, and the man saw clearly. His sight was restored, and he could see everything distinctly. <span id='dcv_8_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>So he sent him home, saying: “Do not enter into the village.”</p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Jesus and his disciples now left for the villages of Caes·a·re′a Phi·lip′pi, and on the way he began to question his disciples, saying: “Who are people saying that I am?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>They said to him: “John the Baptist,<a class='mr'></a> but others say E·li′jah,<a class='mr'></a> and still others, one of the prophets.” <span id='dcv_8_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>And he put the question to them: “You, though, who do you say I am?” Peter answered him: “You are the Christ.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>At that he strictly ordered them not to tell anyone about him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>Also, he began teaching them that the Son of man must undergo many sufferings and be rejected by the elders and the chief priests and the scribes and be killed,<a class='mr'></a> and rise three days later.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>Indeed, he was making that statement openly. But Peter took him aside and began to rebuke him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>At this he turned, looked at his disciples, and rebuked Peter, saying: “Get behind me, Satan! because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>He now called the crowd to him with his disciples and said to them: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake<a class='fn'></a> and keep following me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>For whoever wants to save his life<a class='fn'></a> will lose it, but whoever loses his life<a class='fn'></a> for my sake and for the sake of the good news will save it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>Really, what good will it do a man to gain the whole world and to lose his life?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>What, really, would a man give in exchange for his life?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>For whoever becomes ashamed of me and my words in this adulterous<a class='fn'></a> and sinful generation, the Son of man will also be ashamed of him<a class='mr'></a> when he comes in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Furthermore, he said to them: “Truly I say to you that there are some of those standing here who will not taste death at all until first they see the Kingdom of God already having come in power.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Six days later Jesus took Peter and James and John along and led them up into a lofty mountain by themselves. And he was transfigured before them;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>his outer garments began to glisten, becoming far whiter than any clothes cleaner on earth could whiten them. <span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Also, E·li′jah with Moses appeared to them, and they were conversing with Jesus. <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then Peter said to Jesus: “Rabbi, it is fine for us to be here. So let us erect three tents, one for you, one for Moses, and one for E·li′jah.” <span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>In fact, he did not know how to react, for they were quite fearful. <span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>And a cloud formed, overshadowing them, and a voice<a class='mr'></a> came out of the cloud: “This is my Son, the beloved.<a class='mr'></a> Listen to him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then suddenly they looked around and saw that no one was with them any longer except Jesus.</p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>As they were coming down from the mountain, he strictly ordered them not to relate to anybody what they had seen<a class='mr'></a> until after the Son of man had risen from the dead.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>They took the word to heart,<a class='fn'></a> but discussed among themselves what this rising from the dead meant. <span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And they began to question him, saying: “Why do the scribes say that E·li′jah<a class='mr'></a> must come first?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>He said to them: “E·li′jah does come first and restore all things;<a class='mr'></a> but how is it that it is written about the Son of man that he must undergo many sufferings<a class='mr'></a> and be treated with contempt?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>But I say to you that E·li′jah,<a class='mr'></a> in fact, has come, and they did to him whatever they wanted, just as it is written about him.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>When they came to the other disciples, they noticed a large crowd around them, and there were scribes arguing with them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>But as soon as all the crowd caught sight of him, they were astonished, and they ran up to him to greet him. <span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>So he asked them: “What are you arguing about with them?” <span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>And one of the crowd answered him: “Teacher, I brought my son to you because he has a speechless spirit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Wherever it seizes him, it throws him to the ground, and he foams at the mouth and grinds his teeth and loses his strength. I asked your disciples to expel it, but they were not able to do so.” <span id='dcv_9_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>In response he said to them: “O faithless generation,<a class='mr'></a> how long must I continue with you? How long must I put up with you? Bring him to me.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So they brought the boy to him, but at the sight of him, the spirit at once threw the child into convulsions. After falling on the ground, he kept rolling about, foaming at the mouth. <span id='dcv_9_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then Jesus asked the father: “How long has this been happening to him?” He said: “From childhood on, <span id='dcv_9_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>and often it would throw him into the fire and also into the water to destroy him. But if you can do anything, have pity on us and help us.” <span id='dcv_9_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Jesus said to him: “That expression, ‘If you can’! Why, all things are possible for the one who has faith.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Immediately the child’s father cried out and said: “I have faith! Help me out where I need faith!”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Jesus, now noticing that a crowd was rushing toward them, rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it: “You speechless and deaf spirit, I order you, get out of him and do not enter into him again!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>After crying out and going through many convulsions, it came out, and the child seemed to be dead, so that most of the people were saying: “He is dead!” <span id='dcv_9_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>But Jesus took him by the hand and raised him up, and he stood up. <span id='dcv_9_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>So after he entered into a house, his disciples asked him privately: “Why could we not expel it?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>He said to them: “This kind can come out only by prayer.”</p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>They departed from there and went through Gal′i·lee, but he did not want anyone to get to know about it. <span id='dcv_9_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>For he was teaching his disciples and telling them: “The Son of man is going to be betrayed into men’s hands, and they will kill him,<a class='mr'></a> but despite being killed, he will rise three days later.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>However, they did not understand his statement, and they were afraid to question him.</p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>And they came into Ca·per′na·um. Now when he was inside the house, he put the question to them: “What were you arguing about on the road?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>They kept silent, for on the road they had been arguing among themselves about who is greater. <span id='dcv_9_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>So he sat down and called the Twelve and said to them: “If anyone wants to be first, he must be last of all and minister of all.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>Then he took a young child and stood him in their midst; and putting his arms around him, he said to them: <span id='dcv_9_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>“Whoever receives one of such young children<a class='mr'></a> on the basis of my name receives me also; and whoever receives me receives not me only but also Him who sent me.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>John said to him: “Teacher, we saw someone expelling demons by using your name, and we tried to prevent him, because he was not following us.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>But Jesus said: “Do not try to prevent him, for there is no one who will do a powerful work on the basis of my name who will quickly be able to say anything bad about me. <span id='dcv_9_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>For whoever is not against us is for us.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>And whoever gives you a cup of water to drink because you belong to Christ,<a class='mr'></a> I tell you truly, he will by no means lose his reward.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_42' class='dv dx dp'><a>42 </a></span>But whoever stumbles one of these little ones who have faith, it would be better for him if a millstone that is turned by a donkey were put around his neck and he were pitched into the sea.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>“If ever your hand makes you stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life maimed than to go off with two hands into Ge·hen′na,<a class='fn'></a> into the fire that cannot be put out.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44<a class='fn'></a> </a></span>—— <span id='dcv_9_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>And if your foot makes you stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life lame than to be thrown with two feet into Ge·hen′na.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_46' class='dv dx dp'><a>46<a class='fn'></a> </a></span>—— <span id='dcv_9_47' class='dv dx dp'><a>47 </a></span>And if your eye makes you stumble, throw it away.<a class='mr'></a> It is better for you to enter one-eyed into the Kingdom of God than to be thrown with two eyes into Ge·hen′na,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_48' class='dv dx dp'><a>48 </a></span>where the maggot does not die and the fire is not put out.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_49' class='dv dx dp'><a>49 </a></span>“For everyone must be salted with fire.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_50' class='dv dx dp'><a>50 </a></span>Salt is fine, but if the salt ever loses its saltiness, with what will you season it?<a class='mr'></a> Have salt in yourselves,<a class='mr'></a> and keep peace with one another.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>From there he got up and came to the borders<a class='fn'></a> of Ju·de′a across the Jordan, and again crowds gathered to him. As he was accustomed to do, he again began teaching them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>And Pharisees approached, intent on testing him, and they asked whether it was lawful for a man to divorce a wife.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He answered them: “What did Moses command you?” <span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>They said: “Moses allowed the writing of a certificate of dismissal and divorcing her.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But Jesus said to them: “Out of regard for your hard-heartedness,<a class='mr'></a> he wrote this commandment for you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>However, from the beginning of creation, ‘He made them male and female.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>and the two will be one flesh,’<a class='mr'></a> so that they are no longer two, but one flesh. <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Therefore, what God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>When they were again in the house, the disciples began to question him about this. <span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>He said to them: “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery<a class='mr'></a> against her, <span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>and if ever a woman after divorcing her husband marries another, she commits adultery.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>People now began bringing him young children for him to touch them, but the disciples reprimanded them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>At seeing this, Jesus was indignant and said to them: “Let the young children come to me; do not try to stop them, for the Kingdom of God belongs to such ones.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Truly I say to you, whoever does not receive the Kingdom of God like a young child will by no means enter into it.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And he took the children into his arms and began blessing them, laying his hands on them.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>As he was going on his way, a man ran up and fell on his knees before him and put the question to him: “Good Teacher, what must I do to inherit everlasting life?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Jesus said to him: “Why do you call me good? Nobody is good except one, God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>You know the commandments: ‘Do not murder,<a class='mr'></a> do not commit adultery,<a class='mr'></a> do not steal,<a class='mr'></a> do not bear false witness,<a class='mr'></a> do not defraud,<a class='mr'></a> honor your father and your mother.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>The man said to him: “Teacher, all these things I have kept from my youth on.” <span id='dcv_10_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Jesus looked at him and felt love for him and said, “One thing is missing about you: Go, sell what things you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come be my follower.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>But he grew sad at the answer and went away grieved, for he had many possessions.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>After looking around, Jesus said to his disciples: “How difficult it will be for those with money to enter into the Kingdom of God!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>But the disciples were surprised at his words. Jesus then responded: “Children, how difficult it is to enter into the Kingdom of God! <span id='dcv_10_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>It is easier for a camel to go through a needle’s eye than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>They became still more astounded and said to him:<a class='fn'></a> “Who possibly can be saved?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Looking straight at them, Jesus said: “With men it is impossible but not so with God, for all things are possible with God.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Peter began to say to him: “Look! We have left all things and followed you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Jesus said: “Truly I say to you, no one has left house or brothers or sisters or mother or father or children or fields for my sake and for the sake of the good news<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>who will not get 100 times more now in this period of time—houses, brothers, sisters, mothers, children, and fields, with persecutions<a class='mr'></a>—and in the coming system of things,<a class='fn'></a> everlasting life. <span id='dcv_10_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>But many who are first will be last, and the last first.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>Now they were going on the road up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going ahead of them, and they were astonished, but those who followed began to fear. Once again he took the Twelve aside and started to tell them these things that were about to happen to him:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>“Look! We are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man will be handed over to the chief priests and the scribes. They will condemn him to death and hand him over to men of the nations, <span id='dcv_10_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>and these will mock him and spit on him and scourge him and kill him, but three days later he will rise.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>James and John, the sons of Zeb′e·dee,<a class='mr'></a> approached him and said to him: “Teacher, we want you to do for us whatever we ask of you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>He said to them: “What do you want me to do for you?” <span id='dcv_10_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>They replied: “Grant us to sit down, one at your right hand and one at your left, in your glory.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>But Jesus said to them: “You do not know what you are asking for. Can you drink the cup that I am drinking or be baptized with the baptism with which I am being baptized?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>They said to him: “We can.” At that Jesus said to them: “The cup I am drinking, you will drink, and with the baptism with which I am being baptized, you will be baptized.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>However, to sit down at my right hand or at my left is not mine to give, but it belongs to those for whom it has been prepared.”</p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>When the ten others heard about it, they became indignant at James and John.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>But Jesus called them to him and said to them: “You know that those who appear to be<a class='fn'></a> ruling the nations lord it over them and their great ones wield authority over them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>This must not be the way among you; but whoever wants to become great among you must be your minister,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>and whoever wants to be first among you must be the slave of all. <span id='dcv_10_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>For even the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister<a class='mr'></a> and to give his life<a class='fn'></a> as a ransom in exchange for many.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_46' class='dv dx dp'><a>46 </a></span>They then came into Jer′i·cho. But as he and his disciples and a considerable crowd were going out of Jer′i·cho, Bar·ti·mae′us (the son of Ti·mae′us), a blind beggar, was sitting beside the road.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>When he heard that it was Jesus the Naz·a·rene′, he started shouting and saying: “Son of David,<a class='mr'></a> Jesus, have mercy on me!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>At this many began rebuking him, telling him to be silent, but all the more he kept shouting: “Son of David, have mercy on me!” <span id='dcv_10_49' class='dv dx dp'><a>49 </a></span>So Jesus stopped and said: “Call him to me.” So they called the blind man, saying to him: “Take courage! Get up; he is calling you.” <span id='dcv_10_50' class='dv dp'><a>50 </a></span>Throwing off his outer garment, he leaped to his feet and went to Jesus. <span id='dcv_10_51' class='dv dp'><a>51 </a></span>Then Jesus said to him: “What do you want me to do for you?” The blind man said to him: <i>“Rab·bo′ni,</i><a class='fn'></a> let me recover my sight.” <span id='dcv_10_52' class='dv dx dp'><a>52 </a></span>And Jesus said to him: “Go. Your faith has made you well.”<a class='mr'></a> And immediately he recovered his sight,<a class='mr'></a> and he began to follow him on the road.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dp'><a>11 </a></span>Now when they were getting near to Jerusalem, to Beth′pha·ge and Beth′a·ny<a class='mr'></a> at the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>and told them: “Go into the village that is within sight, and as soon as you enter it, you will find a colt tied on which no man has sat until now. Untie it and bring it here. <span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>And if anyone says to you, ‘Why are you doing this?’ say, ‘The Lord needs it and will send it back here right away.’” <span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So they went away and found the colt tied at a door, outside on the side street, and they untied it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But some of those standing there said to them: “What are you doing untying the colt?” <span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>They told them just what Jesus had said, and they let them go.</p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>And they brought the colt<a class='mr'></a> to Jesus, and they put their outer garments on it, and he sat on it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Also, many spread their outer garments on the road, but others cut down foliage from the fields.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>And those going in front and those coming behind kept shouting: “Save, we pray!<a class='mr'></a> Blessed is the one who comes in Jehovah’s<a class='fn'></a> name!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Blessed is the coming Kingdom of our father David!<a class='mr'></a> Save, we pray, in the heights above!” <span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And he entered Jerusalem and went into the temple, and he looked around at everything, but since the hour was already late, he went out to Beth′a·ny with the Twelve.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>The next day when they were leaving Beth′a·ny, he felt hungry.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>From a distance he caught sight of a fig tree that had leaves, and he went to see whether he could find something on it. But on coming to it, he found nothing but leaves, for it was not the season for figs. <span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>So he said to it: “Let no one eat fruit from you ever again.”<a class='mr'></a> And his disciples were listening.</p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>They now came to Jerusalem. There he entered the temple and started to throw out those selling and buying in the temple, and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>and he would not let anyone carry a utensil through the temple. <span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>He was teaching and saying to them: “Is it not written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer for all the nations’?<a class='mr'></a> But you have made it a cave of robbers.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>And the chief priests and the scribes heard it, and they began to seek how to kill him;<a class='mr'></a> for they were in fear of him, because all the crowd was astounded at his teaching.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>When it became late in the day, they went out of the city. <span id='dcv_11_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>But when they were passing by early in the morning, they saw the fig tree already withered from its roots.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Peter, remembering it, said to him: “Rabbi, see! the fig tree that you cursed has withered.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>In reply Jesus said to them: “Have faith in God. <span id='dcv_11_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Truly I say to you that whoever tells this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and thrown into the sea,’ and does not doubt in his heart but has faith that what he says is going to happen, he will have it happen.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>This is why I tell you, all the things you pray and ask for, have faith that you have received them, and you will have them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>And when you stand praying, forgive whatever you have against anyone, so that your Father who is in the heavens may also forgive you your trespasses.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_26' class='dv dp'><a>26<a class='fn'></a> </a></span>——</p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>They came again to Jerusalem. And as he was walking in the temple, the chief priests and the scribes and the elders came <span id='dcv_11_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>and said to him: “By what authority do you do these things? Or who gave you this authority to do these things?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Jesus said to them: “I will ask you one question. Answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things. <span id='dcv_11_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Was the baptism by John<a class='mr'></a> from heaven or from men?<a class='fn'></a> Answer me.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>So they began to reason among themselves, saying: “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why, then, did you not believe him?’ <span id='dcv_11_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>But dare we say, ‘From men’?” They were in fear of the crowd, for these all held that John had really been a prophet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>So they answered Jesus: “We do not know.” Jesus said to them: “Neither am I telling you by what authority I do these things.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then he started to speak to them with illustrations: “A man planted a vineyard<a class='mr'></a> and put a fence around it and dug a vat for the winepress and erected a tower;<a class='mr'></a> then he leased it to cultivators and traveled abroad.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>In due season he sent a slave to the cultivators to collect some of the fruits of the vineyard from them. <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>But they took him, beat him, and sent him away empty-handed. <span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Again he sent another slave to them, and that one they struck on the head and dishonored.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And he sent another, and that one they killed, and many others, some of whom they beat and some of whom they killed. <span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>One more he had, a beloved son.<a class='mr'></a> He sent him to them last, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’ <span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>But those cultivators said among themselves, ‘This is the heir.<a class='mr'></a> Come, let us kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.’ <span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So they took him and killed him and threw him out of the vineyard.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>What will the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and kill the cultivators and will give the vineyard to others.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Did you never read this scripture: ‘The stone that the builders rejected, this has become the chief cornerstone.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>This has come from Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a> and it is marvelous in our eyes’?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>At that they wanted to seize<a class='fn'></a> him, but they feared the crowd, for they knew that he spoke the illustration with them in mind. So they left him and went away.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p82' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Next they sent to him some of the Pharisees and of the party followers of Herod in order to catch him in his speech.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>On arriving, these said to him: “Teacher, we know you are truthful and you do not seek anyone’s favor, for you do not look at the outward appearance of people, but you teach the way of God in line with truth. Is it lawful<a class='fn'></a> to pay head tax to Caesar or not? <span id='dcv_12_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Should we pay, or should we not pay?” Detecting their hypocrisy, he said to them: “Why do you put me to the test? Bring me a de·nar′i·us<a class='fn'></a> to look at.” <span id='dcv_12_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>They brought one, and he said to them: “Whose image and inscription is this?” They said to him: “Caesar’s.” <span id='dcv_12_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Jesus then said: “Pay back Caesar’s things to Caesar,<a class='mr'></a> but God’s things to God.”<a class='mr'></a> And they were amazed at him.</p></div><div id='p83' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Now the Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection,<a class='mr'></a> came and asked him:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>“Teacher, Moses wrote us that if someone’s brother dies and leaves a wife behind but does not leave a child, his brother should take the wife and raise up offspring for his brother.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>There were seven brothers. The first took a wife, but when he died he left no offspring. <span id='dcv_12_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>And the second married her but died without leaving offspring, and the third the same way. <span id='dcv_12_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And all seven left no offspring. Last of all, the woman also died. <span id='dcv_12_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>In the resurrection, whose wife will she be? For the seven had her as a wife.” <span id='dcv_12_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Jesus said to them: “Is not this why you are mistaken, because you know neither the Scriptures nor the power of God?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>For when they rise from the dead, neither do men marry nor are women given in marriage, but they are as angels in the heavens.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>But concerning the dead being raised up, have you not read in the book of Moses, in the account about the thornbush, that God said to him: ‘I am the God of Abraham and God of Isaac and God of Jacob’?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>He is a God, not of the dead, but of the living. You are very much mistaken.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p84' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>One of the scribes who had come up and heard them disputing, knowing that he had answered them in a fine way, asked him: “Which commandment is first<a class='fn'></a> of all?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Jesus answered: “The first is, ‘Hear, O Israel, Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> our God is one Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_12_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>and you must love Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul<a class='fn'></a> and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>The second is this, ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’<a class='mr'></a> There is no other commandment greater than these.” <span id='dcv_12_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>The scribe said to him: “Teacher, you spoke well, in line with truth, ‘He is One, and there is no other besides him’;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>and to love him with one’s whole heart, with one’s whole understanding, and with one’s whole strength and to love one’s neighbor as oneself is worth far more than all the whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>At this Jesus, discerning that he had answered intelligently, said to him: “You are not far from the Kingdom of God.” But no one had the courage to question him anymore.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p85' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>However, as Jesus continued teaching in the temple, he said: “How is it that the scribes say that the Christ is David’s son?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>By the holy spirit,<a class='mr'></a> David himself said, ‘Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies beneath your feet.”’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>David himself calls him Lord, so how can it be that he is his son?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p86' class='par'><p class='sb'>And the large crowd was listening to him with pleasure. <span id='dcv_12_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>And in his teaching he went on to say: “Beware of the scribes who want to walk around in robes and want greetings in the marketplaces<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>and front<a class='fn'></a> seats in the synagogues and the most prominent places at evening meals.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>They devour the houses<a class='fn'></a> of the widows, and for show<a class='fn'></a> they make long prayers. These will receive a more severe<a class='fn'></a> judgment.”</p></div><div id='p87' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>And he sat down with the treasury chests<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> in view and began observing how the crowd was dropping money into the treasury chests, and many rich people were dropping in many coins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_42' class='dv dx dp'><a>42 </a></span>Now a poor widow came and dropped in two small coins of very little value.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>So he called his disciples to him and said to them: “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all the others who put money into the treasury chests.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>For they all put in out of their surplus, but she, out of her want,<a class='fn'></a> put in everything she had, all she had to live on.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p88' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>As he was going out of the temple, one of his disciples said to him: “Teacher, see! what wonderful stones and buildings!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>However, Jesus said to him: “Do you see these great buildings? By no means will a stone be left here upon a stone and not be thrown down.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p89' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>As he was sitting on the Mount of Olives with the temple in view, Peter, James, John, and Andrew asked him privately: <span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>“Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign when all these things are to come to a conclusion?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So Jesus began to tell them: “Look out that nobody misleads you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am he,’ and will mislead many. <span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Moreover, when you hear of wars and reports of wars, do not be alarmed; these things must take place, but the end is not yet.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p90' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>“For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom;<a class='mr'></a> there will be earthquakes in one place after another; there will also be food shortages.<a class='mr'></a> These are a beginning of pangs of distress.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p91' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>“As for you, look out for yourselves. People will hand you over to local courts,<a class='mr'></a> and you will be beaten in synagogues<a class='mr'></a> and be put on the stand before governors and kings for my sake, for a witness to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Also, in all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And when they are taking you to hand you over, do not be anxious beforehand about what to say; but whatever is given you in that hour, say this, for you are not the ones speaking, but the holy spirit is.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Furthermore, brother will deliver brother over to death, and a father a child, and children will rise up against parents and have them put to death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>And you will be hated by all people on account of my name.<a class='mr'></a> But the one who has endured<a class='fn'></a> to the end<a class='mr'></a> will be saved.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p92' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>“However, when you catch sight of the disgusting thing that causes desolation<a class='mr'></a> standing where it should not be (let the reader use discernment), then let those in Ju·de′a begin fleeing to the mountains.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Let the man on the housetop not come down nor go inside to take anything out of his house; <span id='dcv_13_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>and let the man in the field not return to the things behind to pick up his outer garment. <span id='dcv_13_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Woe to the pregnant women and those nursing a baby in those days!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Keep praying that it may not occur in wintertime; <span id='dcv_13_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>for those days will be days of a tribulation<a class='mr'></a> such as has not occurred from the beginning of the creation that God created until that time, and will not occur again.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>In fact, unless Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> had cut short the days, no flesh would be saved. But on account of the chosen ones whom he has chosen, he has cut short the days.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p93' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>“Then, too, if anyone says to you, ‘See! Here is the Christ,’ or, ‘See! There he is,’ do not believe it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>For false Christs and false prophets will arise<a class='mr'></a> and will perform signs and wonders to lead astray, if possible, the chosen ones. <span id='dcv_13_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>You, then, watch out.<a class='mr'></a> I have told you all things beforehand.</p></div><div id='p94' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>“But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>and the stars will be falling out of heaven, and the powers that are in the heavens will be shaken. <span id='dcv_13_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>And then they will see the Son of man<a class='mr'></a> coming in the clouds with great power and glory.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>And then he will send out the angels and will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from earth’s extremity to heaven’s extremity.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p95' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>“Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Likewise also you, when you see these things happening, know that he is near at the doors.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Heaven and earth will pass away,<a class='mr'></a> but my words will by no means pass away.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p96' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>“Concerning that day or the hour nobody knows, neither the angels in heaven nor the Son, but the Father.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Keep looking, keep awake,<a class='mr'></a> for you do not know when the appointed time is.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>It is like a man traveling abroad who left his house and gave the authority to his slaves,<a class='mr'></a> to each one his work, and commanded the doorkeeper to keep on the watch.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>Keep on the watch, therefore, for you do not know when the master of the house is coming,<a class='mr'></a> whether late in the day or at midnight or at dawn<a class='fn'></a> or early in the morning,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>in order that when he comes suddenly, he does not find you sleeping.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>But what I say to you, I say to all: Keep on the watch.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="14"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p97' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Now the Passover<a class='mr'></a> and the Festival of Unleavened Bread<a class='mr'></a> was two days later.<a class='mr'></a> And the chief priests and the scribes were looking for a way to seize<a class='fn'></a> him by cunning<a class='fn'></a> and kill him;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>for they were saying: “Not at the festival; perhaps there might be an uproar of the people.”</p></div><div id='p98' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And while he was at Beth′a·ny dining<a class='fn'></a> in the house of Simon the leper, a woman came with an alabaster jar of perfumed oil, genuine nard, very expensive. She broke open the alabaster jar and began pouring it on his head.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>At this some said to one another indignantly: “Why has this perfumed oil been wasted? <span id='dcv_14_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>For this perfumed oil could have been sold for more than 300 de·nar′i·i<a class='fn'></a> and the money given to the poor!” And they were greatly annoyed with<a class='fn'></a> her. <span id='dcv_14_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>But Jesus said: “Let her alone. Why do you try to make trouble for her? She did a fine deed toward me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>For you always have the poor with you,<a class='mr'></a> and you can do them good whenever you want to, but you will not always have me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>She did what she could; she poured perfumed oil on my body beforehand, in view of the burial.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Truly I say to you, wherever the good news is preached in all the world,<a class='mr'></a> what this woman did will also be told in memory of her.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p99' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>And Judas Is·car′i·ot, one of the Twelve, went off to the chief priests in order to betray him to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>When they heard it, they were delighted and promised to give him silver money.<a class='mr'></a> So he began seeking an opportunity to betray him.</p></div><div id='p100' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now on the first day of the Unleavened Bread,<a class='mr'></a> when they customarily offered up the Passover sacrifice,<a class='mr'></a> his disciples said to him: “Where do you want us to go and prepare for you to eat the Passover?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>With that he sent two of his disciples and said to them: “Go into the city, and a man carrying an earthenware water jar will meet you. Follow him,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>and wherever he goes inside, say to the master of the house, ‘The Teacher says: “Where is the guest room where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”’ <span id='dcv_14_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>And he will show you a large upper room, furnished and ready. Prepare it for us there.” <span id='dcv_14_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>So the disciples went out, and they entered the city and found it just as he said to them, and they prepared for the Passover.</p></div><div id='p101' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>After evening had fallen, he came with the Twelve.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>And as they were reclining at the table and eating, Jesus said: “Truly I say to you, one of you who is eating with me will betray me.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>They began to be grieved and to say to him one by one: “It is not I, is it?” <span id='dcv_14_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>He said to them: “It is one of the Twelve, the one dipping with me into the bowl.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>For the Son of man is going away, just as it is written about him, but woe to that man through whom the Son of man is betrayed!<a class='mr'></a> It would have been better for that man if he had not been born.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p102' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>And as they continued eating, he took a loaf, said a blessing, broke it, and gave it to them, saying: “Take it; this means my body.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>And taking a cup, he offered thanks and gave it to them, and they all drank out of it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>And he said to them: “This means my ‘blood<a class='mr'></a> of the covenant,’<a class='mr'></a> which is to be poured out in behalf of many.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Truly I say to you, I will by no means drink anymore of the product of the vine until that day when I drink it new in the Kingdom of God.” <span id='dcv_14_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>Finally, after singing praises,<a class='fn'></a> they went out to the Mount of Olives.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p103' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>And Jesus said to them: “You will all be stumbled, for it is written: ‘I will strike the shepherd,<a class='mr'></a> and the sheep will be scattered about.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>But after I have been raised up, I will go ahead of you into Gal′i·lee.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>But Peter said to him: “Even if all the others are stumbled, I will not be.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>At that Jesus said to him: “Truly I say to you that today, yes, on this very night, before a rooster crows twice, you will disown me three times.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>But he kept insisting: “If I have to die with you, I will by no means disown you.” Also, all the others began to say the same thing.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p104' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>So they came to a spot named Geth·sem′a·ne, and he said to his disciples: “Sit down here while I pray.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>And he took Peter and James and John along with him,<a class='mr'></a> and he began to feel deeply distressed<a class='fn'></a> and to be greatly troubled. <span id='dcv_14_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>He said to them: “I am<a class='fn'></a> deeply grieved,<a class='mr'></a> even to death. Stay here and keep on the watch.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>And going a little way forward, he fell to the ground and began praying that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him. <span id='dcv_14_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>And he said: <i>“Abba,</i><a class='fn'></a> Father,<a class='mr'></a> all things are possible for you; remove this cup from me. Yet, not what I want, but what you want.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>He returned and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter: “Simon, are you sleeping? Did you not have the strength to keep on the watch for one hour?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>Keep on the watch and pray continually, so that you do not come into temptation.<a class='mr'></a> The spirit, of course, is eager,<a class='fn'></a> but the flesh is weak.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>And he went away again and prayed, saying the same thing.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>And he came again and found them sleeping, for their eyes were weighed down, so they did not know what to answer him. <span id='dcv_14_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>And he returned the third time and said to them: “At such a time as this, you are sleeping and resting! It is enough! The hour has come!<a class='mr'></a> Look! The Son of man is being betrayed into the hands of sinners. <span id='dcv_14_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>Get up, let us go. Look! My betrayer has drawn near.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p105' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>And immediately, while he was still speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, arrived and with him a crowd with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>Now his betrayer had given them an agreed sign, saying: “Whoever it is I kiss, he is the one; take him into custody, and lead him away under guard.” <span id='dcv_14_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>And he came straight up and approached him and said, “Rabbi!” and gave him a tender kiss. <span id='dcv_14_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>So they seized him and took him into custody. <span id='dcv_14_47' class='dv dx dp'><a>47 </a></span>However, one of those standing by drew his sword and struck the slave of the high priest, taking off his ear.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>But in response Jesus said to them: “Did you come out to arrest me with swords and clubs as against a robber?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_49' class='dv dp'><a>49 </a></span>Day after day I was with you in the temple teaching,<a class='mr'></a> and yet you did not take me into custody. Nevertheless, this is to fulfill the Scriptures.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p106' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_50' class='dv dp'><a>50 </a></span>And they all abandoned him and fled.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_51' class='dv dx dp'><a>51 </a></span>However, a certain young man wearing only a fine linen garment over his naked body began to follow him nearby, and they tried to seize him, <span id='dcv_14_52' class='dv dx dp'><a>52 </a></span>but he left his linen garment behind and got away naked.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p107' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_53' class='dv dx dp'><a>53 </a></span>They now led Jesus away to the high priest,<a class='mr'></a> and all the chief priests and the elders and the scribes assembled.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_54' class='dv dx dp'><a>54 </a></span>But Peter, from a good distance, followed him as far as into the courtyard of the high priest; and he was sitting together with the house attendants and warming himself before a bright fire.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_55' class='dv dp'><a>55 </a></span>Now the chief priests and the entire San′he·drin were looking for testimony against Jesus in order to put him to death, but they were not finding any.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_56' class='dv dp'><a>56 </a></span>Many, indeed, were giving false witness against him,<a class='mr'></a> but their testimonies were not in agreement. <span id='dcv_14_57' class='dv dp'><a>57 </a></span>Also, certain ones were standing up and bearing false witness against him, saying: <span id='dcv_14_58' class='dv dp'><a>58 </a></span>“We heard him say, ‘I will throw down this temple that was made with hands, and in three days I will build another not made with hands.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_59' class='dv dp'><a>59 </a></span>But even on these grounds, their testimony was not in agreement.</p></div><div id='p108' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_60' class='dv dx dp'><a>60 </a></span>Then the high priest stood up in their midst and questioned Jesus, saying: “Do you say nothing in reply? What is it these men are testifying against you?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_61' class='dv dx dp'><a>61 </a></span>But he kept silent and made no reply at all.<a class='mr'></a> Again the high priest began to question him and said to him: “Are you the Christ the Son of the Blessed One?” <span id='dcv_14_62' class='dv dx dp'><a>62 </a></span>Then Jesus said: “I am; and you will see the Son of man<a class='mr'></a> sitting at the right hand<a class='mr'></a> of power and coming with the clouds of heaven.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_63' class='dv dx dp'><a>63 </a></span>At this the high priest ripped his garments and said: “What further need do we have of witnesses?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_64' class='dv dp'><a>64 </a></span>You heard the blasphemy. What is your decision?”<a class='fn'></a> They all condemned him as deserving of death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_65' class='dv dx dp'><a>65 </a></span>And some started to spit on him<a class='mr'></a> and to cover his face and hit him with their fists and say to him: “Prophesy!” And slapping him in the face, the court attendants took him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p109' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_66' class='dv dx dp'><a>66 </a></span>Now while Peter was below in the courtyard, one of the servant girls of the high priest came.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_67' class='dv dx dp'><a>67 </a></span>On seeing Peter warming himself, she looked straight at him and said: “You too were with the Naz·a·rene′, this Jesus.” <span id='dcv_14_68' class='dv dx dp'><a>68 </a></span>But he denied it, saying: “Neither do I know him nor do I understand what you are talking about,” and he went outside to the entryway.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_69' class='dv dx dp'><a>69 </a></span>There the servant girl saw him and again began to say to those standing by: “This is one of them.” <span id='dcv_14_70' class='dv dx dp'><a>70 </a></span>Again he was denying it. And after a little while, those standing by again began saying to Peter: “Certainly you are one of them, for you are, in fact, a Gal·i·le′an.” <span id='dcv_14_71' class='dv dx dp'><a>71 </a></span>But he started to curse and swear: “I do not know this man of whom you speak!” <span id='dcv_14_72' class='dv dx dp'><a>72 </a></span>Immediately a rooster crowed a second time,<a class='mr'></a> and Peter recalled what Jesus had said to him: “Before a rooster crows twice, you will disown me three times.”<a class='mr'></a> And he broke down and began to weep.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="15"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p110' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Immediately at dawn, the chief priests with the elders and the scribes, indeed, the whole San′he·drin, consulted together, and they bound Jesus and led him off and handed him over to Pilate.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So Pilate put the question to him: “Are you the King of the Jews?”<a class='mr'></a> In answer he said: “You yourself say it.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But the chief priests were accusing him of many things. <span id='dcv_15_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now Pilate began questioning him again, saying: “Have you no reply to make?<a class='mr'></a> See how many charges they are bringing against you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>But Jesus made no further answer, so that Pilate was amazed.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p111' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Well, from festival to festival, he used to release to them one prisoner whom they requested.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>At the time the man named Bar·ab′bas was in prison with the seditionists, who in their sedition had committed murder. <span id='dcv_15_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So the crowd came up and began to make their request according to what Pilate used to do for them. <span id='dcv_15_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He responded to them, saying: “Do you want me to release to you the King of the Jews?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>For Pilate was aware that out of envy the chief priests had handed him over.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But the chief priests stirred up the crowd to have him release Bar·ab′bas to them instead.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Again in reply Pilate said to them: “What, then, should I do with the one you call the King of the Jews?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Once more they cried out: “To the stake with him!”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But Pilate went on to say to them: “Why? What bad thing did he do?” Still they cried out all the more: “To the stake with him!”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>At that Pilate, wishing to satisfy the crowd, released Bar·ab′bas to them; and after having Jesus whipped,<a class='mr'></a> he handed him over to be executed on the stake.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p112' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>The soldiers now led him off into the courtyard, that is, into the governor’s residence, and they called the whole body of troops together.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>And they dressed him in purple and braided a crown of thorns and put it on him; <span id='dcv_15_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>and they began to call out to him: “Greetings,<a class='fn'></a> you King of the Jews!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Also, they were hitting him on the head with a reed and spitting on him, and they got on their knees and bowed down<a class='fn'></a> to him. <span id='dcv_15_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Finally, after they had mocked him, they stripped him of the purple and put his outer garments on him. And they led him out to nail him to the stake.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Also, they compelled into service a passerby, a certain Simon of Cy·re′ne, coming from the countryside, the father of Alexander and Ru′fus, to carry his torture stake.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p113' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>So they brought him to the place called <i>Gol′go·tha,</i> which means, when translated, “Skull Place.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Here they tried to give him wine drugged with myrrh,<a class='mr'></a> but he would not take it. <span id='dcv_15_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>And they nailed him to the stake and distributed his outer garments by casting lots over them to decide who would take what.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>It was now the third hour,<a class='fn'></a> and they nailed him to the stake. <span id='dcv_15_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>And the inscription of the charge against him was written: “The King of the Jews.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Moreover, they put two robbers on stakes alongside him, one on his right and one on his left.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_28' class='dv dp'><a>28<a class='fn'></a> </a></span>—— <span id='dcv_15_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>And those passing by spoke abusively to him, shaking their heads<a class='mr'></a> and saying: “Ha! You who would throw down the temple and build it in three days,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>save yourself by coming down off the torture stake.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_15_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>In the same way also, the chief priests with the scribes were mocking him among themselves, saying: “Others he saved; himself he cannot save!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>Let the Christ, the King of Israel, now come down off the torture stake,<a class='fn'></a> so that we may see and believe.”<a class='mr'></a> Even those who were on stakes alongside him were reproaching him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p114' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>When it became the sixth hour,<a class='fn'></a> a darkness fell over all the land until the ninth hour.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>And at the ninth hour, Jesus called out with a loud voice: <i>“E′li, E′li, la′ma sa·bach·tha′ni?”</i> which means, when translated: “My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>And some of those standing near, on hearing it, began to say: “See! He is calling E·li′jah.” <span id='dcv_15_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>Then someone ran, soaked a sponge in sour wine, put it on a reed, and gave it to him to drink,<a class='mr'></a> saying: “Let him be! Let us see whether E·li′jah comes to take him down.” <span id='dcv_15_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>But Jesus let out a loud cry and expired.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>And the curtain of the sanctuary<a class='mr'></a> was torn in two from top to bottom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>Now when the army officer who was standing by with him in view saw that he had expired under these circumstances, he said: “Certainly this man was God’s Son.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p115' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>There were also women watching from a distance, among them Mary Mag′da·lene as well as Mary the mother of James the Less and of Jo′ses, and Sa·lo′me,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>who used to accompany him and minister to him<a class='mr'></a> when he was in Gal′i·lee, and many other women who had come up together with him to Jerusalem.</p></div><div id='p116' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_42' class='dv dx dp'><a>42 </a></span>Now as it was already late in the afternoon, and since it was Preparation, that is, the day before the Sabbath, <span id='dcv_15_43' class='dv dx dp'><a>43 </a></span>there came Joseph of Ar·i·ma·the′a, a reputable member of the Council, who also himself was waiting for the Kingdom of God. He took courage and went in before Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>But Pilate wondered whether he could already be dead, and summoning the army officer, he asked him whether Jesus had already died. <span id='dcv_15_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>So after making certain from the army officer, he granted the body to Joseph. <span id='dcv_15_46' class='dv dx dp'><a>46 </a></span>After he bought fine linen and took him down, he wrapped him in the fine linen and laid him in a tomb<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> that was quarried out of rock; then he rolled a stone up to the entrance of the tomb.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>But Mary Mag′da·lene and Mary the mother of Jo′ses continued looking at where he had been laid.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="16"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p117' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>So when the Sabbath<a class='mr'></a> was over, Mary Mag′da·lene, Mary<a class='mr'></a> the mother of James, and Sa·lo′me bought spices in order to come and apply them to his body.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>And very early on the first day of the week when the sun had risen, they came to the tomb.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>They were saying to one another: “Who will roll the stone away from the entrance of the tomb for us?” <span id='dcv_16_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>But when they looked up, they saw that the stone had been rolled away, although it was very large.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>When they entered into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, clothed in a white robe, and they were stunned. <span id='dcv_16_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>He said to them: “Do not be stunned.<a class='mr'></a> You are looking for Jesus the Naz·a·rene′ who was executed on the stake. He was raised up.<a class='mr'></a> He is not here. Look, here is the place where they laid him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>But go, tell his disciples and Peter, ‘He is going ahead of you into Gal′i·lee.<a class='mr'></a> You will see him there, just as he told you.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>So when they came out, they fled from the tomb, trembling and overwhelmed with emotion. And they said nothing to anyone, for they were in fear.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
</bible>
