<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dp'><a>1 </a></span>The word of Jehovah came to Jo′nah<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the son of A·mit′tai, saying: <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Get up, go to Nin′e·veh<a class='mr'></a> the great city, and proclaim judgment against her, for their wickedness has come to my attention.”</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But Jo′nah got up to run away from Jehovah to Tar′shish; he went down to Jop′pa and found a ship going to Tar′shish. So he paid the fare and went aboard to go with them to Tar′shish, away from Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Then Jehovah hurled a strong wind at the sea, and there was such a violent storm on the sea that the ship was about to be wrecked. <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>The mariners were so frightened that each of them began to call on his god for help. And they began throwing the articles of the ship into the sea, to make it lighter.<a class='mr'></a> But Jo′nah had gone down into the inner part of the ship,<a class='fn'></a> where he lay down and fell fast asleep. <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The ship captain approached and said to him: “Why are you sleeping? Get up, call out to your god! Perhaps the true God will show his concern for us, and we will not perish.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then they said to one another: “Come, let us cast lots<a class='mr'></a> to find out who is to blame for this calamity.” So they cast lots, and the lot fell to Jo′nah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>They said to him: “Please tell us, who is to blame for this calamity that has come upon us? What is your work, and where do you come from? What is your country, and from what people are you?”</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He replied: “I am a Hebrew, and I fear<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah the God of the heavens, the One who made the sea and the dry land.”</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>At this the men became even more afraid, and they asked him: “What have you done?” (The men learned that he was running away from Jehovah, because he had told them.) <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So they said to him: “What should we do to you to make the sea calm down for us?” For the sea was growing more and more stormy. <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>He replied: “Lift me up and throw me into the sea, and the sea will calm down for you; for I know that it is because of me that this violent storm has come upon you.” <span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>However, the men rowed hard<a class='fn'></a> to bring the ship back to dry land, but they could not, because the sea grew more and more stormy around them.</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then they called out to Jehovah and said: “Ah, now, O Jehovah, please, may we not perish because of this man!<a class='fn'></a> Do not hold us responsible for innocent blood, since you have done as you pleased, O Jehovah.” <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Then they lifted Jo′nah up and threw him into the sea; and the sea ceased its raging. <span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then the men were struck with great fear of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> and they offered a sacrifice to Jehovah and made vows.</p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Jehovah now sent a huge fish to swallow Jo′nah, so that Jo′nah came to be in the belly of the fish for three days and three nights.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then Jo′nah prayed to Jehovah his God from the belly of the fish,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>and he said:</p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sz'>“Out of my distress I called out to Jehovah, and he answered me.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sz'>Out of the depths<a class='fn'></a> of the Grave<a class='fn'></a> I cried for help.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sz'>You heard my voice.</p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>When you threw me to the depths, into the heart of the open sea,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Then the currents engulfed me.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sz'>All your breakers and waves swept over me.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>And I said, ‘I have been driven away from your sight!</p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sz'>How will I gaze again upon your holy temple?’</p></div><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Waters engulfed me and threatened my life;<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The watery deep closed in on me.</p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sz'>Weeds were wrapped around my head.</p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>To the bottoms of the mountains I sank down.</p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sz'>The bars of the earth were closing upon me forever.</p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sz'>But out of the pit you brought up my life, O Jehovah my God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>When my life<a class='fn'></a> was ebbing away, Jehovah was the One whom I remembered.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sz'>Then my prayer came in to you, into your holy temple.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Those who are devoted to the worthless idols forsake their source of loyal love.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But as for me, with the voice of thanksgiving I will sacrifice to you.</p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sz'>What I have vowed, I will pay.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sz'>Salvation is from Jehovah.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>In time Jehovah commanded the fish, and it vomited Jo′nah out onto the dry land.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then the word of Jehovah came to Jo′nah a second time, saying:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Get up, go to Nin′e·veh<a class='mr'></a> the great city, and proclaim to her the message that I tell you.”</p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>So Jo′nah got up and went to Nin′e·veh<a class='mr'></a> in obedience to the word of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> Now Nin′e·veh was a very large city<a class='fn'></a>—a walking distance of three days. <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Then Jo′nah entered the city, and walking a day’s journey, he was proclaiming: “In just 40 days more, Nin′e·veh will be overthrown.”</p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>And the men of Nin′e·veh put faith in God,<a class='mr'></a> and they proclaimed a fast and put on sackcloth, from the greatest to the least of them. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>When the message reached the king of Nin′e·veh, he rose up from his throne and took off his royal garment and covered himself with sackcloth and sat down in the ashes. <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Furthermore, he issued a proclamation throughout Nin′e·veh,</p><p class='sb'>“By the decree of the king and his nobles: No man or beast, herd or flock, should eat anything at all. They should not take food, nor should they drink any water. <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and beast; and let them call out earnestly to God and turn from their evil ways and from the violence they practice. <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Who knows whether the true God may reconsider<a class='fn'></a> what he intends to do and turn from his burning anger, so that we may not perish?”</p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>When the true God saw what they did, how they had turned back from their evil ways,<a class='mr'></a> he reconsidered<a class='fn'></a> the calamity that he said he would bring on them, and he did not bring it.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>But this was highly displeasing to Jo′nah, and he became hot with anger. <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So he prayed to Jehovah: “Ah, now, Jehovah, was this not my concern when I was in my own land? That is why I tried to flee to Tar′shish<a class='mr'></a> in the first place; for I knew that you are a compassionate<a class='fn'></a> and merciful God, slow to anger and abundant in loyal love,<a class='mr'></a> one who feels grieved over calamity. <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Now, O Jehovah, please take away my life,<a class='fn'></a> for it is better for me to die than to live.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Jehovah asked: “Is it right for you to be so angry?”</p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Jo′nah then went out of the city and sat down east of the city. He made a shelter for himself there and sat in its shade to see what would happen to the city.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Jehovah God then provided a bottle-gourd plant<a class='fn'></a> to grow up over Jo′nah, to give him shade for his head and to relieve his misery. And Jo′nah was very pleased with the bottle-gourd plant.</p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But the true God sent a worm at the break of dawn on the next day, and it attacked the bottle-gourd plant, and it withered. <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>When the sun began to shine, God also sent a scorching east wind, and the sun beat down on Jo′nah’s head, and he grew faint. He kept asking to die,<a class='fn'></a> and he kept saying, “It is better for me to die than to live.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>God asked Jo′nah: “Is it right for you to be so angry over the bottle-gourd plant?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'>At that he said: “I have a right to be angry, so angry that I want to die.” <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>But Jehovah said: “You felt sorry for the bottle-gourd plant, which you did not work for, nor did you make it grow; it grew in one night and perished in one night. <span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Should I not also feel sorry for Nin′e·veh the great city,<a class='mr'></a> in which there are more than 120,000 men who do not even know right from wrong,<a class='fn'></a> as well as their many animals?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
</bible>
