<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>Peter, an apostle<a class='mr'></a> of Jesus Christ, to the temporary residents scattered about in Pon′tus, Ga·la′ti·a, Cap·pa·do′ci·a,<a class='mr'></a> Asia, and Bi·thyn′i·a, to those chosen <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>according to the foreknowledge of God the Father,<a class='mr'></a> with sanctification by the spirit,<a class='mr'></a> for the purpose of being obedient and sprinkled with the blood of Jesus Christ:<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'>May undeserved kindness and peace be increased to you.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, for according to his great mercy he gave us a new birth<a class='mr'></a> to a living hope<a class='mr'></a> through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>to an incorruptible and undefiled and unfading inheritance.<a class='mr'></a> It is reserved in the heavens for you,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>who are being safeguarded by God’s power through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last period of time. <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Because of this you are greatly rejoicing, though for a short time, if it must be, you have been distressed by various trials,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>in order that the tested quality of your faith,<a class='mr'></a> of much greater value than gold that perishes despite its being tested<a class='fn'></a> by fire, may be found a cause for praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Though you never saw him, you love him. Though you do not see him now, yet you exercise faith in him and are greatly rejoicing with an indescribable and glorious joy, <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>as you attain the goal of your faith, your salvation.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Concerning this salvation, the prophets who prophesied about the undeserved kindness meant for you made a diligent inquiry and a careful search.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>They kept on investigating what particular time or what season the spirit within them was indicating concerning Christ<a class='mr'></a> as it testified beforehand about the sufferings meant for Christ<a class='mr'></a> and about the glory that would follow. <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>It was revealed to them that they were ministering, not to themselves, but to you, regarding what has now been announced to you by those who declared the good news to you with holy spirit sent from heaven.<a class='mr'></a> Into these very things, angels are desiring to peer.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>So brace up your minds for activity;<a class='mr'></a> keep your senses completely;<a class='mr'></a> set your hope on the undeserved kindness that will be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ. <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>As obedient children, stop being molded by<a class='fn'></a> the desires you formerly had in your ignorance, <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>but like the Holy One who called you, become holy yourselves in all your conduct,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>for it is written: “You must be holy, because I am holy.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>And if you are calling on the Father who judges impartially<a class='mr'></a> according to each one’s work, conduct yourselves with fear<a class='mr'></a> during the time of your temporary residence. <span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>For you know that it was not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, that you were set free<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> from your futile way of life handed down to you by your forefathers.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>But it was with precious blood,<a class='mr'></a> like that of an unblemished and spotless lamb,<a class='mr'></a> that of Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>True, he was foreknown before the founding of the world,<a class='mr'></a> but he was made manifest at the end of the times for your sake.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Through him you are believers in God,<a class='mr'></a> the one who raised him up from the dead<a class='mr'></a> and gave him glory,<a class='mr'></a> so that your faith and hope might be in God.</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Now that you have purified yourselves<a class='fn'></a> by your obedience to the truth with unhypocritical brotherly affection<a class='mr'></a> as the result, love one another intensely from the heart.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>For you have been given a new birth,<a class='mr'></a> not by corruptible, but by incorruptible seed,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> through the word of the living and enduring God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>For “all flesh is<a class='fn'></a> like grass, and all its glory is like a blossom of the field; the grass withers, and the flower falls off, <span id='dcv_1_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>but the saying<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> endures forever.”<a class='mr'></a> And this “saying”<a class='fn'></a> is the good news that was declared to you.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So rid yourselves of all badness<a class='mr'></a> and deceit and hypocrisy and envy and all backbiting. <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>As newborn infants,<a class='mr'></a> form a longing for the unadulterated<a class='fn'></a> milk of the word, so that by means of it you may grow to salvation,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>provided you have tasted<a class='fn'></a> that the Lord is kind.</p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>As you come to him, a living stone rejected by men<a class='mr'></a> but chosen, precious to God,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>you yourselves as living stones are being built up into a spiritual house<a class='mr'></a> to be a holy priesthood, in order to offer up spiritual sacrifices<a class='mr'></a> acceptable to God through Jesus Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>For it says in Scripture: “Look! I am laying in Zion a chosen stone, a precious foundation cornerstone, and no one exercising faith in it will ever be disappointed.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>It is to you, therefore, that he is precious, because you are believers; but to those not believing, “the stone that the builders rejected,<a class='mr'></a> this has become the chief cornerstone”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>and “a stone of stumbling and a rock of offense.”<a class='mr'></a> They are stumbling because they are disobedient to the word. To this very end they were appointed. <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But you are “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation,<a class='mr'></a> a people for special possession,<a class='mr'></a> that you should declare abroad the excellencies”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> of the One who called you out of darkness into his wonderful light.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For you were once not a people, but now you are God’s people;<a class='mr'></a> once you had not been shown mercy, but now you have received mercy.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Beloved, I urge you as foreigners and temporary residents<a class='mr'></a> to keep abstaining from fleshly desires,<a class='mr'></a> which wage war against you.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Maintain your conduct fine among the nations,<a class='mr'></a> so that when they accuse you of being wrongdoers, they may be eyewitnesses of your fine works<a class='mr'></a> and, as a result, glorify God in the day of his inspection.</p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>For the Lord’s sake subject yourselves to every human creation,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> whether to a king<a class='mr'></a> as being superior <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>or to governors as sent by him to punish wrongdoers but to praise those who do good.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>For it is the will of God that by doing good you may silence<a class='fn'></a> the ignorant talk of unreasonable men.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Be as free people,<a class='mr'></a> using your freedom, not as a cover<a class='fn'></a> for doing wrong,<a class='mr'></a> but as slaves of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Honor men of all sorts,<a class='mr'></a> have love for the whole association of brothers,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> be in fear of God,<a class='mr'></a> honor the king.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Let servants be in subjection to their masters with all due fear,<a class='mr'></a> not only to the good and reasonable but also to those hard to please. <span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For it is agreeable when someone endures hardship<a class='fn'></a> and suffers unjustly because of conscience toward God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>For what merit is there if you are beaten for sinning and you endure it?<a class='mr'></a> But if you endure suffering because of doing good, this is an agreeable thing to God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you,<a class='mr'></a> leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>He committed no sin,<a class='mr'></a> nor was deception found in his mouth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>When he was being insulted,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> he did not insult<a class='fn'></a> in return.<a class='mr'></a> When he was suffering,<a class='mr'></a> he did not threaten, but he entrusted himself to the One who judges<a class='mr'></a> righteously. <span id='dcv_2_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>He himself bore our sins<a class='mr'></a> in his own body on the stake,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> so that we might die to<a class='fn'></a> sins and live to righteousness. And “by his wounds you were healed.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>For you were like sheep going astray,<a class='mr'></a> but now you have returned to the shepherd<a class='mr'></a> and overseer of your souls.<a class='fn'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>In the same way, you wives, be in subjection to your husbands,<a class='mr'></a> so that if any are not obedient to the word, they may be won without a word through the conduct of their wives,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>because of having been eyewitnesses of your chaste conduct<a class='mr'></a> together with deep respect. <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Do not let your adornment be external—the braiding of hair and the wearing of gold ornaments<a class='mr'></a> or fine clothing— <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>but let it be the secret person of the heart in the incorruptible adornment of the quiet and mild spirit,<a class='mr'></a> which is of great value in the eyes of God. <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>For this is how the holy women of the past who hoped in God used to adorn themselves, subjecting themselves to their husbands, <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>just as Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord.<a class='mr'></a> And you have become her children, provided you continue doing good and do not give in to fear.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>You husbands, in the same way, continue dwelling with them according to knowledge.<a class='fn'></a> Assign them honor<a class='mr'></a> as to a weaker vessel, the feminine one, since they are also heirs with you<a class='mr'></a> of the undeserved favor of life, in order for your prayers not to be hindered.</p></div><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Finally, all of you have unity of mind,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion,<a class='mr'></a> and humility.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Do not pay back injury for injury<a class='mr'></a> or insult for insult.<a class='mr'></a> Instead, repay with a blessing,<a class='mr'></a> for you were called to this course, so that you might inherit a blessing.</p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>For “whoever would love life and see good days must guard his tongue from bad<a class='mr'></a> and his lips from speaking deception. <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Let him turn away from what is bad<a class='mr'></a> and do what is good;<a class='mr'></a> let him seek peace and pursue it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>For the eyes of Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> are on the righteous, and his ears listen to their supplication,<a class='mr'></a> but the face of Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> is against those doing bad things.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Indeed, who will harm you if you become zealous for what is good?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>But even if you should suffer for the sake of righteousness, you are happy.<a class='mr'></a> However, do not fear what they fear,<a class='fn'></a> nor be disturbed.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts, always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper<a class='mr'></a> and deep respect.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Maintain a good conscience,<a class='mr'></a> so that in whatever way you are spoken against, those who speak against you may be put to shame<a class='mr'></a> because of your good conduct as followers of Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>For it is better to suffer because you are doing good,<a class='mr'></a> if it is God’s will to allow it, than because you are doing evil.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>For Christ died once for all time for sins,<a class='mr'></a> a righteous person for unrighteous ones,<a class='mr'></a> in order to lead you to God.<a class='mr'></a> He was put to death in the flesh<a class='mr'></a> but made alive in the spirit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>And in this state he went and preached to the spirits in prison,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>who had formerly been disobedient when God was patiently waiting<a class='fn'></a> in Noah’s day,<a class='mr'></a> while the ark was being constructed,<a class='mr'></a> in which a few people, that is, eight souls,<a class='fn'></a> were carried safely through the water.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Baptism, which corresponds to this, is also now saving you (not by the removing of the filth of the flesh, but by the request to God for a good conscience),<a class='mr'></a> through the resurrection of Jesus Christ. <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>He is at God’s right hand,<a class='mr'></a> for he went to heaven, and angels and authorities and powers were made subject to him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Since Christ suffered in the flesh,<a class='mr'></a> you too arm yourselves with the same mental disposition;<a class='fn'></a> because the person who has suffered in the flesh has desisted from sins,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>so that he may live the remainder of his time in the flesh, no more for the desires of men,<a class='mr'></a> but for God’s will.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For the time that has passed by is sufficient for you to have done the will of the nations<a class='mr'></a> when you carried on in acts of brazen conduct,<a class='fn'></a> unbridled passions, overdrinking, wild parties,<a class='fn'></a> drinking bouts, and lawless idolatries.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>They are puzzled that you do not continue running with them in the same decadent course of debauchery, so they speak abusively of you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But these people will render an account to the one who is ready to judge those living and those dead.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>In fact, this is why the good news was declared also to the dead,<a class='mr'></a> so that although they are judged in the flesh from the standpoint of men, they might live in harmony with the spirit from God’s standpoint.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>But the end of all things has drawn close. Therefore, be sound in mind,<a class='mr'></a> and be vigilant<a class='fn'></a> with a view to prayers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Above all things, have intense love for one another,<a class='mr'></a> because love covers a multitude of sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Be hospitable to one another without grumbling.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>To the extent that each one has received a gift, use it in ministering to one another as fine stewards of God’s undeserved kindness that is expressed in various ways.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>If anyone speaks, let him do so as speaking pronouncements from God; if anyone ministers, let him do so as depending on the strength that God supplies;<a class='mr'></a> so that in all things God may be glorified<a class='mr'></a> through Jesus Christ. The glory and the might are his forever and ever. Amen.</p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Beloved ones, do not be surprised about the fiery trials that you are experiencing,<a class='mr'></a> as though something strange were happening to you. <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>On the contrary, go on rejoicing<a class='mr'></a> over the extent to which you are sharers in the sufferings of the Christ,<a class='mr'></a> so that you may rejoice and be overjoyed also during the revelation of his glory.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>If you are being reproached<a class='fn'></a> for the name of Christ, you are happy,<a class='mr'></a> because the spirit of glory, yes, the spirit of God, is resting upon you.</p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>However, let none of you suffer as a murderer or a thief or a wrongdoer or a busybody in other people’s matters.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>But if anyone suffers as a Christian, let him not feel ashamed,<a class='mr'></a> but let him keep on glorifying God while bearing this name. <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>For it is the appointed time for the judgment to start with the house of God.<a class='mr'></a> Now if it starts first with us,<a class='mr'></a> what will the outcome be for those who are not obedient to the good news of God?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>“And if the righteous man is being saved with difficulty, what will happen to the ungodly man and the sinner?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So, then, let those who are suffering in harmony with the will of God keep on entrusting<a class='fn'></a> themselves<a class='fn'></a> to a faithful Creator while they are doing good.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Therefore, as a fellow elder, a witness of the sufferings of the Christ and a sharer of the glory that is to be revealed,<a class='mr'></a> I make this appeal<a class='fn'></a> to the elders among you: <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Shepherd the flock of God<a class='mr'></a> under your care, serving as overseers,<a class='fn'></a> not under compulsion, but willingly before God;<a class='mr'></a> not for love of dishonest gain,<a class='mr'></a> but eagerly; <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>not lording it over those who are God’s inheritance,<a class='mr'></a> but becoming examples to the flock.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>And when the chief shepherd<a class='mr'></a> has been made manifest, you will receive the unfading crown of glory.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>In the same way, you younger men, be in subjection to the older men.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> But all of you clothe<a class='fn'></a> yourselves with humility<a class='fn'></a> toward one another, because God opposes the haughty ones, but he gives undeserved kindness to the humble ones.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>while you throw all your anxiety<a class='fn'></a> on him,<a class='mr'></a> because he cares for you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Keep your senses, be watchful!<a class='mr'></a> Your adversary, the Devil, walks about like a roaring lion, seeking to devour someone.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But take your stand against him,<a class='mr'></a> firm in the faith, knowing that the same kind of sufferings are being experienced by the entire association of your brothers<a class='fn'></a> in the world.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>But after you have suffered a little while, the God of all undeserved kindness, who called you to his everlasting glory<a class='mr'></a> in union with Christ, will himself finish your training. He will make you firm,<a class='mr'></a> he will make you strong,<a class='mr'></a> he will firmly ground you. <span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>To him be the might forever. Amen.</p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Through Sil·va′nus,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> whom I regard as a faithful brother, I have written you in few words in order to encourage you and to give an earnest witness that this is the true undeserved kindness of God. Stand firm in it. <span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>She who is in Babylon, a chosen one like you, sends you her greetings, and so does Mark,<a class='mr'></a> my son. <span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Greet one another with a kiss of love.</p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'>May all of you who are in union with Christ have peace.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>
