<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>The older man<a class='fn'></a> to the chosen lady and to her children, whom I truly love, and not only I but also all those who have come to know the truth, <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>because of the truth that remains in us and will be with us forever. <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>There will be with us undeserved kindness, mercy, and peace from God the Father and from Jesus Christ, the Son of the Father, with truth and love.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>I rejoice very much because I have found some of your children walking in the truth,<a class='mr'></a> just as we received commandment from the Father. <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So now I request you, lady, that we love one another. (I am writing you, not a new commandment, but one that we had from the beginning.)<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>And this is what love means, that we go on walking according to his commandments.<a class='mr'></a> This is the commandment, just as you have heard from the beginning, that you should go on walking in it. <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>For many deceivers have gone out into the world,<a class='mr'></a> those not acknowledging Jesus Christ as coming in the flesh.<a class='mr'></a> This is the deceiver and the antichrist.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Look out for yourselves, so that you do not lose the things we have worked to produce, but that you may obtain a full reward.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Everyone who pushes ahead and does not remain in the teaching of the Christ does not have God.<a class='mr'></a> The one who does remain in this teaching is the one who has both the Father and the Son.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>If anyone comes to you and does not bring this teaching, do not receive him into your homes<a class='mr'></a> or say a greeting to him. <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For the one who says a greeting to him is a sharer in his wicked works.</p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Although I have many things to write to you, I do not want to do so with paper and ink, but I am hoping to come to you and to speak with you face-to-face, so that your joy may be in full measure.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>The children of your sister, the chosen one, send you their greetings.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>
