<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
<text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>After the death of A′hab, Mo′ab<a class='mr'></a> revolted against Israel.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>It was then that A·ha·zi′ah fell down through the grating in his roof chamber in Sa·mar′i·a and was injured. So he sent messengers and said to them: “Go, inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron<a class='mr'></a> to find out whether I will recover from this injury.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>But the angel of Jehovah said to E·li′jah<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the Tish′bite: “Rise up, go to meet the messengers of the king of Sa·mar′i·a and say to them, ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are going to inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Therefore this is what Jehovah says: “You will not leave the bed on which you are lying, for you will certainly die.”’” With that E·li′jah went off.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>When the messengers returned to him, he immediately said to them: “Why have you come back?” <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>They replied to him: “There was a man who came up to meet us, and he said to us, ‘Go, return to the king who sent you and tell him, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are sending to inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron? Therefore, you will not leave the bed on which you are lying, for you will certainly die.’”’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>At this he asked them: “What did the man look like who came up to meet you and spoke these words to you?” <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So they said to him: “He was a man with a garment of hair<a class='mr'></a> and a leather belt around his waist.”<a class='mr'></a> Immediately he said: “It was E·li′jah the Tish′bite.”</p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The king then sent to him a chief of 50 with his 50 men. When he went up to him, he was sitting on the top of the mountain. He said to him: “Man of the true God,<a class='mr'></a> the king says, ‘Come down.’” <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>But E·li′jah answered the chief of the 50: “Well, if I am a man of God, let fire come down from the heavens<a class='mr'></a> and consume you and your 50 men.” And fire came down from the heavens and consumed him and his 50 men.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So the king sent again to him another chief of 50 with his 50 men. He went and said to him: “Man of the true God, this is what the king says, ‘Come down quickly.’” <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>But E·li′jah answered them: “If I am a man of the true God, let fire come down from the heavens and consume you and your 50 men.” And fire of God came down from the heavens and consumed him and his 50 men.</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then the king sent again a third chief of 50 and his 50 men. But the third chief of 50 went up and bowed down on his knees in front of E·li′jah and began to beg for favor and say to him: “Man of the true God, please, let my life and the lives of<a class='fn'></a> these 50 servants of yours be precious in your eyes. <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Fire has already come down from the heavens and consumed the two former chiefs of 50 and their groups of 50, but now let my life<a class='fn'></a> be precious in your eyes.”</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>At that the angel of Jehovah told E·li′jah: “Go down with him. Do not be afraid of him.” So he rose and went down with him to the king. <span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>E·li′jah then said to the king, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘You sent messengers to inquire of Ba′al-ze′bub the god of Ek′ron.<a class='mr'></a> Is it because there is no God in Israel?<a class='mr'></a> Why did you not inquire of his word? Therefore, you will not leave the bed on which you are lying, for you will certainly die.’” <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>So he died, according to the word of Jehovah that E·li′jah had spoken; and because he did not have a son, Je·ho′ram<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> became king in his place, in the second year of Je·ho′ram<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the king of Judah.</p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of A·ha·zi′ah,<a class='mr'></a> what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>When Jehovah was about to take E·li′jah<a class='mr'></a> up to the heavens<a class='fn'></a> in a windstorm,<a class='mr'></a> E·li′jah and E·li′sha<a class='mr'></a> went out from Gil′gal.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>E·li′jah said to E·li′sha: “Stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to Beth′el.” But E·li′sha said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are<a class='fn'></a> living, I will not leave you.” So they went down to Beth′el.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then the sons of the prophets<a class='fn'></a> in Beth′el came out to E·li′sha and said to him: “Do you know that today Jehovah is taking your master away from headship over you?”<a class='mr'></a> At this he said: “I already know it. Be silent.”</p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>E·li′jah now said to him: “E·li′sha, stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to Jer′i·cho.”<a class='mr'></a> But he said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are<a class='fn'></a> living, I will not leave you.” So they came to Jer′i·cho. <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then the sons of the prophets who were in Jer′i·cho approached E·li′sha and said to him: “Do you know that today Jehovah is taking your master away from headship over you?” At this he said: “I already know it. Be silent.”</p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>E·li′jah now said to him: “Stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to the Jordan.” But he said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are<a class='fn'></a> living, I will not leave you.” So both of them went on. <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>And 50 of the sons of the prophets also went and stood watching from a distance while the two of them stood by the Jordan. <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then E·li′jah took his official garment<a class='mr'></a> and rolled it up and struck the waters, and they were divided to the left and to the right, so that both of them went across on the dry ground.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>As soon as they had gone across, E·li′jah said to E·li′sha: “Ask what you want me to do for you before I am taken from you.” So E·li′sha said: “Please, may I receive a double portion<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> of your spirit?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>He replied: “You have asked a difficult thing. If you see me when I am taken from you, it will happen for you that way; but if you do not, it will not happen.”</p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>As they were walking along, speaking as they walked, suddenly a fiery chariot and fiery horses<a class='mr'></a> made a separation between the two of them, and E·li′jah ascended to the heavens<a class='fn'></a> in the windstorm.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>While E·li′sha was watching, he was crying out: “My father, my father! The chariot of Israel and his horsemen!”<a class='mr'></a> When he could no longer see him, he took hold of his own garments and ripped them into two pieces.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>After that he picked up the official garment<a class='mr'></a> of E·li′jah that had fallen off him and went back and stood by the bank of the Jordan. <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then he took the official garment of E·li′jah that had fallen off him and struck the waters and said: “Where is Jehovah, the God of E·li′jah?” When he struck the waters, they were divided to the left and to the right, so that E·li′sha went across.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>When the sons of the prophets at Jer′i·cho saw him from a distance, they said: “The spirit of E·li′jah has settled down on E·li′sha.”<a class='mr'></a> So they went to meet him and bowed down to the ground before him. <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>They said to him: “Here are 50 capable men with your servants. Let them go, please, to look for your master. Perhaps the spirit<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah has lifted him up and then thrown him on one of the mountains or in one of the valleys.”<a class='mr'></a> But he said: “Do not send them.” <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>However, they kept urging him until he was embarrassed, so he said: “Send them.” They sent the 50 men, who kept looking for three days but did not find him. <span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>When they returned to him, he was staying in Jer′i·cho.<a class='mr'></a> Then he said to them: “Did I not tell you not to go?”</p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>In time the men of the city said to E·li′sha: “My master can see that the city is well-situated;<a class='mr'></a> but the water is bad, and the land is barren.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>At that he said: “Bring me a small new bowl and put salt in it.” So they brought it to him. <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then he went out to the source of the water and threw salt into it<a class='mr'></a> and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘I have healed this water. No more will it cause death or barrenness.’”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And the water has been healed down to this day, according to the word spoken by E·li′sha.</p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>He went up from there to Beth′el. As he was going along the way, some young boys came out from the city and began to jeer at him,<a class='mr'></a> and they kept saying to him: “Go up, you baldhead! Go up, you baldhead!” <span id='dcv_2_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Finally he turned around and looked at them and cursed them in the name of Jehovah. Then two she-bears<a class='mr'></a> came out of the forest and tore 42 of the children to pieces.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>He kept going from there to Mount Car′mel,<a class='mr'></a> and from there he returned to Sa·mar′i·a.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dp'><a>3 </a></span>Je·ho′ram<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′hab became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a in the 18th year of King Je·hosh′a·phat of Judah, and he reigned for 12 years. <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, but not to the extent of his father or his mother, for he removed the sacred pillar of Ba′al that his father had made.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>However, he clung to the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> He did not depart from them.</p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now Me′sha the king of Mo′ab was a sheep raiser, and he used to pay 100,000 lambs and 100,000 unshorn rams as tribute to the king of Israel. <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>As soon as A′hab died,<a class='mr'></a> the king of Mo′ab revolted against the king of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So King Je·ho′ram went out on that day from Sa·mar′i·a and mustered all Israel. <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>He also sent a message to King Je·hosh′a·phat of Judah, saying: “The king of Mo′ab has revolted against me. Will you go with me to war against Mo′ab?” To this he said: “I will go.<a class='mr'></a> I am the same as you. My people are the same as your people. My horses are the same as your horses.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then he asked: “By which way should we go up?” He replied: “By the way of the wilderness of E′dom.”</p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The king of Israel then set out with the king of Judah and the king of E′dom.<a class='mr'></a> After they journeyed roundabout for seven days, there was no water for the camp and for the domestic animals that were following behind them. <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>The king of Israel said: “How terrible! Jehovah has called these three kings, only to give them into the hand of Mo′ab!” <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>At that Je·hosh′a·phat said: “Is there no prophet of Jehovah here through whom we may inquire of Jehovah?”<a class='mr'></a> So one of the servants of the king of Israel answered: “There is E·li′sha<a class='mr'></a> the son of Sha′phat, who used to pour out water on the hands of E·li′jah.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then Je·hosh′a·phat said: “The word of Jehovah is with him.” So the king of Israel and Je·hosh′a·phat and the king of E′dom went down to him.</p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>E·li′sha said to the king of Israel: “What do I have to do with you?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> Go to the prophets of your father and to the prophets of your mother.”<a class='mr'></a> But the king of Israel said to him: “No, for it is Jehovah who has called these three kings to give them into the hand of Mo′ab.” <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>To this E·li′sha said: “As surely as Jehovah of armies whom I serve<a class='fn'></a> is living, if I did not have regard for King Je·hosh′a·phat<a class='mr'></a> of Judah, I would not look at you or take notice of you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Now bring me a harpist.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> As soon as the harpist started playing, the hand of Jehovah came on him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>He said, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Dig trench after trench in this valley,<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>for this is what Jehovah says: “You will not see wind, and you will not see rain; yet this valley<a class='fn'></a> will be filled with water,<a class='mr'></a> and you will drink from it, you, your livestock, and your other animals.”’ <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>But this is a trivial thing in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> for he will also give Mo′ab into your hand.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>You must strike down every fortified city<a class='mr'></a> and every choice city, you should cut down every good tree, you should stop up all the springs of water, and you should ruin every good plot of land with stones.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>And in the morning, at the time of the morning grain offering,<a class='mr'></a> water was suddenly coming from the direction of E′dom, and the land became filled with the water.</p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>All the Mo′ab·ites heard that the kings had come up to fight against them, so they called together all the men who could bear arms,<a class='fn'></a> and they stationed themselves at the border. <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>When they got up early in the morning, the sun was shining on the water, and to the Mo′ab·ites on the opposite side, the water looked red like blood. <span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>They said: “This is blood! The kings have surely slaughtered one another with the sword. So, then, to the spoil,<a class='mr'></a> O Mo′ab!” <span id='dcv_3_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>When they came into the camp of Israel, the Israelites rose up and began striking down the Mo′ab·ites, who fled from them.<a class='mr'></a> They advanced into Mo′ab, striking the Mo′ab·ites down as they went. <span id='dcv_3_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>They tore down the cities, and each man threw a stone into every good plot of land, filling it with stones; they stopped up every spring of water,<a class='mr'></a> and they cut down every good tree.<a class='mr'></a> Finally only the stone walls of Kir-har′e·seth<a class='mr'></a> remained standing, and the slingers surrounded it and struck it down.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>When the king of Mo′ab saw that the battle was lost, he took with him 700 men armed with swords to break through to the king of E′dom;<a class='mr'></a> but they were not able to. <span id='dcv_3_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>So he took his firstborn son who was going to reign in his place and offered him up as a burnt sacrifice<a class='mr'></a> on the wall. And there came to be great indignation against Israel, so they withdrew from against him and returned to their land.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now one of the wives of the sons of the prophets<a class='mr'></a> cried out to E·li′sha, saying: “Your servant my husband is dead, and you well know that your servant had always feared Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> Now a creditor has come to take both of my children as his slaves.” <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>At this E·li′sha said to her: “What can I do for you? Tell me, what do you have in the house?” She replied: “Your servant has nothing at all in the house but a jar<a class='fn'></a> of oil.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then he said: “Go outside, ask for containers from all your neighbors, empty containers. Do not limit yourself to a few. <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Then go in and close the door behind you and your sons. Fill all these containers, and set the full ones aside.” <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So she left him.</p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'>When she closed the door behind her and her sons, they passed the containers to her, and she kept pouring.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>When the containers were full, she said to one of her sons: “Bring another container to me.”<a class='mr'></a> But he said to her: “There are no more containers.” At that the oil stopped.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>So she came in and told the man of the true God, and he said: “Go, sell the oil and pay off your debts, and you and your sons can live from what is left.”</p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>One day E·li′sha went to Shu′nem,<a class='mr'></a> where there was a prominent woman, and she urged him to eat a meal there.<a class='mr'></a> As often as he would pass by, he would stop there to eat. <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So she said to her husband: “I know that it is a holy man of God who comes this way regularly. <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Please, let us make a small room on the roof<a class='mr'></a> and put there for him a bed, a table, a chair, and a lampstand. Then, whenever he comes to us, he can stay there.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>One day he came there, and he went to the room on the roof to lie down. <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>He then said to Ge·ha′zi<a class='mr'></a> his attendant: “Call this Shu′nam·mite<a class='mr'></a> woman.” So he called her, and she stood before him. <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then he said to Ge·ha′zi: “Please tell her, ‘Here you have gone to all this trouble for us.<a class='mr'></a> What can be done for you?<a class='mr'></a> Should I speak in your behalf to the king<a class='mr'></a> or to the chief of the army?’” But her reply was: “I am living among my own people.” <span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>So he said: “Then what can be done for her?” Ge·ha′zi now said: “Well, she does not have a son,<a class='mr'></a> and her husband is old.” <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Immediately he said: “Call her.” So he called her, and she stood at the doorway. <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then he said: “At this time next year, you will be embracing a son.”<a class='mr'></a> But she said: “No, my master, man of the true God! Do not tell lies to your servant.”</p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>However, the woman became pregnant and gave birth to a son at the same time the next year, just as E·li′sha had told her. <span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>The child grew up, and one day he went out to his father, who was with the reapers. <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>He kept saying to his father: “My head, O my head!” Then his father said to the attendant: “Carry him to his mother.” <span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So he carried him back to his mother, and he sat on her lap until noon, and then he died.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then she went up and laid him on the bed of the man of the true God,<a class='mr'></a> and she shut the door behind her and left. <span id='dcv_4_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>She now called her husband and said: “Send me, please, one of the attendants and one of the donkeys, and let me go quickly to the man of the true God and return.” <span id='dcv_4_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>But he said: “Why are you going to see him today? It is not a new moon<a class='mr'></a> or a sabbath.” However, she said: “Everything is all right.” <span id='dcv_4_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>So she saddled the donkey and said to her attendant: “Go quickly. Do not slow down for me unless I tell you to.”</p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>So she went to the man of the true God at Mount Car′mel. As soon as the man of the true God saw her from afar, he said to Ge·ha′zi his attendant: “Look! The Shu′nam·mite woman is over there. <span id='dcv_4_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>Please run to meet her and ask her, ‘Are you well? Is your husband well? Is your child well?’” To this she said: “All is well.” <span id='dcv_4_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>When she came to the man of the true God at the mountain, she at once grabbed hold of his feet.<a class='mr'></a> At this Ge·ha′zi came near to push her away, but the man of the true God said: “Let her alone, for she is in bitter distress,<a class='fn'></a> and Jehovah has hidden it from me and has not told me.” <span id='dcv_4_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>She then said: “Did I ask my lord for a son? Did I not say, ‘You must not give me a false hope’?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>He immediately said to Ge·ha′zi: “Wrap your garments around your waist<a class='mr'></a> and take my staff in your hand and go. If you encounter anyone, do not greet him; and if anyone should greet you, do not answer him. Go and place my staff on the boy’s face.” <span id='dcv_4_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>At this the boy’s mother said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you yourself are<a class='fn'></a> living, I will not leave you.”<a class='mr'></a> So he got up and went with her. <span id='dcv_4_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Ge·ha′zi went before them and put the staff on the boy’s face, but there was no sound or response.<a class='mr'></a> He went back to meet E·li′sha and told him: “The boy did not wake up.”</p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>When E·li′sha came into the house, the boy was lying dead on his bed.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>He went in and closed the door behind them both and began to pray to Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>Then he got up on the bed and lay down on the child and put his own mouth on the boy’s mouth, his own eyes on his eyes, and his own palms on his palms and kept bent over him, and the child’s body started to grow warm.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>He walked back and forth in the house, and he got up on the bed and bent over him again. The boy sneezed seven times, after which he opened his eyes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>E·li′sha now called Ge·ha′zi and said: “Call the Shu′nam·mite woman.” So he called her and she came in to him. Then he said: “Pick up your son.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>And she came in and fell at his feet and bowed down to the ground before him, after which she picked up her son and went out.</p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>When E·li′sha returned to Gil′gal, there was famine in the land.<a class='mr'></a> The sons of the prophets<a class='mr'></a> were sitting before him, and he said to his attendant:<a class='mr'></a> “Put the large pot on and boil stew for the sons of the prophets.” <span id='dcv_4_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>So one of them went out to the field to pick mallows, and he found a wild vine and picked wild gourds from it, filling his garment. He then returned and sliced them into the stewpot, not knowing what they were. <span id='dcv_4_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>They later served it to the men to eat, but as soon as they ate from the stew, they cried out: “There is death in the pot, O man of the true God.” And they could not eat it. <span id='dcv_4_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>So he said: “Bring some flour.” After he threw it into the pot, he said: “Serve it to the people.” And nothing harmful was in the pot.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>A man came from Ba′al-shal′i·shah,<a class='mr'></a> and he brought the man of the true God 20 loaves of barley bread<a class='mr'></a> made from the first ripe fruits, as well as a bag of new grain.<a class='mr'></a> Then E·li′sha said: “Give it to the people so that they may eat.” <span id='dcv_4_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>However, his attendant said: “How can I set this before 100 men?”<a class='mr'></a> To this he said: “Give it to the people so that they may eat, for this is what Jehovah says, ‘They will eat and have some left over.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>At that he put it before them, and they ate and they had some left over,<a class='mr'></a> according to the word of Jehovah.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Now Na′a·man the army chief of the king of Syria was a prominent man who was held in esteem by his lord, because through him Jehovah had given victory<a class='fn'></a> to Syria. He was a mighty warrior, although he was a leper.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>On one of their raids, the Syrians had taken captive from the land of Israel a little girl who became a servant to Na′a·man’s wife. <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>She said to her mistress: “If only my lord would visit the prophet<a class='mr'></a> in Sa·mar′i·a! Then he would cure him of his leprosy.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So he<a class='fn'></a> went and reported to his lord, telling him what the girl from Israel had said.</p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then the king of Syria said: “Go now! And I will send a letter to the king of Israel.” So he went, taking with him ten talents<a class='fn'></a> of silver, 6,000 pieces of gold, and ten changes of garments. <span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>He brought to the king of Israel the letter, which read: “Along with this letter that has come to you, I send my servant Na′a·man so that you may cure him of his leprosy.” <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>As soon as the king of Israel read the letter, he ripped his garments apart and said: “Am I God, to put to death and to keep alive?<a class='mr'></a> For he is sending this man to me, telling me to cure him of his leprosy! You can see for yourselves that he is seeking a quarrel with me.”</p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>But when E·li′sha the man of the true God heard that the king of Israel had ripped his garments apart, he at once sent word to the king: “Why did you rip your garments apart? Please let him come to me so that he may know that there is a prophet in Israel.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So Na′a·man came with his horses and his war chariots and stood at the entrance of the house of E·li′sha. <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>However, E·li′sha sent a messenger to tell him: “Go, wash seven times<a class='mr'></a> in the Jordan,<a class='mr'></a> and your flesh will be restored, and you will be clean.” <span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>At this Na′a·man became indignant and started to leave, saying: “Here I said to myself, ‘He will come out to me and stand here and call on the name of Jehovah his God, moving his hand back and forth over the leprosy to cure it.’ <span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Are not the A·ba′nah and the Phar′par, the rivers of Damascus,<a class='mr'></a> better than all the waters of Israel? Can I not wash in them and become clean?” With that he turned and went away in a rage.</p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>His servants now approached him and said: “My father, if the prophet had told you to do something extraordinary, would you not do it? How much more, then, since he only said to you, ‘Wash and be clean’?” <span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>At that he went down and plunged<a class='fn'></a> into the Jordan seven times, according to the word of the man of the true God.<a class='mr'></a> Then his flesh was restored like the flesh of a little boy,<a class='mr'></a> and he became clean.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>After that he went back to the man of the true God,<a class='mr'></a> he and all his entourage,<a class='fn'></a> and he stood before him and said: “Now I know that there is no God anywhere in all the earth but in Israel.<a class='mr'></a> Now accept, please, a gift<a class='fn'></a> from your servant.” <span id='dcv_5_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>However, E·li′sha said: “As surely as Jehovah whom I serve<a class='fn'></a> is living, I will not accept it.”<a class='mr'></a> He urged him to accept it, but he kept refusing. <span id='dcv_5_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Finally Na′a·man said: “If not, please, let your servant be given two mule-loads of soil from this land, for your servant will no longer offer a burnt offering or a sacrifice to any gods other than Jehovah. <span id='dcv_5_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>But may Jehovah forgive your servant for this one thing: When my lord goes into the house<a class='fn'></a> of Rim′mon to bow down there, he supports himself on my arm, so I have to bow down at the house of Rim′mon. When I bow down at the house of Rim′mon, may Jehovah, please, forgive your servant for this.” <span id='dcv_5_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>At this he said to him: “Go in peace.” After he departed from him and had traveled for some distance, <span id='dcv_5_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Ge·ha′zi<a class='mr'></a> the attendant of E·li′sha the man of the true God<a class='mr'></a> said to himself: ‘Here my master has spared this Syrian Na′a·man<a class='mr'></a> by not accepting from him what he brought. As surely as Jehovah is living, I will run after him and take something from him.’ <span id='dcv_5_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>So Ge·ha′zi chased after Na′a·man. When Na′a·man saw someone running after him, he got down from his chariot to meet him and said: “Is everything all right?” <span id='dcv_5_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>To this he said: “All is well. My master has sent me, saying, ‘Look! Just now two young men from the mountainous region of E′phra·im from the sons of the prophets came to me. Give them, please, a talent of silver and two changes of garments.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Na′a·man said: “Go on, take two talents.” He kept urging him,<a class='mr'></a> and he wrapped up two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of garments, and gave them to two of his attendants, who carried them before him.</p></div><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>When he reached O′phel,<a class='fn'></a> he took them from their hand and put them in the house and sent the men away. After they left, <span id='dcv_5_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>he went in and stood by his master. E·li′sha now said to him: “Where did you come from, Ge·ha′zi?” But he said: “Your servant did not go anywhere.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>E·li′sha said to him: “Was my heart not there with you when the man got down from his chariot to meet you? Is it a time to accept silver or to accept garments or olive groves or vineyards or sheep or cattle or male or female servants?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Now Na′a·man’s leprosy<a class='mr'></a> will stick to you and your descendants forever.” Immediately he went out from before him a leper, white as snow.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>The sons of the prophets<a class='mr'></a> said to E·li′sha: “Look! The place where we are staying with you is too cramped for us. <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Please let us go to the Jordan. Let each of us take a log from there and make a place there where we can dwell.” He said: “Go.” <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>One of them said: “Will you please come along with your servants?” At that he said: “I will come.” <span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So he went with them, and they came to the Jordan and began to cut down the trees. <span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>As one of them was cutting down a tree, the axhead fell into the water, and he cried out: “Alas, my master, it was borrowed!” <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The man of the true God said: “Where did it fall?” So he showed him the place. He then cut off a piece of wood and threw it there and made the axhead float. <span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>He said: “Lift it out.” So he reached out his hand and took it.</p></div><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Now the king of Syria went to war against Israel.<a class='mr'></a> He consulted with his servants and said: “I will encamp at such and such a place with you.” <span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then the man of the true God<a class='mr'></a> sent word to the king of Israel, saying: “Beware of passing by this place, because that is where the Syrians are coming down.” <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So the king of Israel sent word to the place that the man of the true God had warned him about. He kept warning him, and he stayed away from there on several occasions.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>This enraged the king<a class='fn'></a> of Syria, so he summoned his servants and said to them: “Tell me! Who among us is on the side of the king of Israel?” <span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then one of his servants said: “None of us, my lord the king! It is E·li′sha the prophet in Israel who tells the king of Israel the things that you say in your own bedroom.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>He said: “Go and find out where he is, so that I may send men to capture him.” Later the report was made to him: “He is in Do′than.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>He immediately sent horses and war chariots there, as well as a large army; they came by night and surrounded the city.</p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>When the attendant<a class='fn'></a> of the man of the true God rose early and went outside, he saw that an army with horses and war chariots was surrounding the city. At once the attendant said to him: “Alas, my master! What are we to do?” <span id='dcv_6_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>But he said: “Do not be afraid!<a class='mr'></a> For there are more who are with us than those who are with them.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then E·li′sha began to pray and say: “O Jehovah, open his eyes, please, that he may see.”<a class='mr'></a> Immediately Jehovah opened the attendant’s eyes and he saw, and look! the mountainous region was full of horses and war chariots of fire<a class='mr'></a> all around E·li′sha.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>When the Syrians came down to him, E·li′sha prayed to Jehovah and said: “Please, strike this nation with blindness.”<a class='mr'></a> So he struck them with blindness, just as E·li′sha had requested. <span id='dcv_6_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>E·li′sha now said to them: “This is not the way, and this is not the city. Follow me, and let me lead you to the man you are looking for.” However, he led them to Sa·mar′i·a.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>When they arrived in Sa·mar′i·a, E·li′sha said: “O Jehovah, open their eyes so that they may see.” So Jehovah opened their eyes, and they saw that they were in the middle of Sa·mar′i·a. <span id='dcv_6_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>When the king of Israel saw them, he said to E·li′sha: “Should I strike them down, should I strike them down, my father?” <span id='dcv_6_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>But he said: “You must not strike them down. Do you strike down those whom you have taken captive with your sword and with your bow? Give them bread and water so they may eat and drink<a class='mr'></a> and return to their lord.” <span id='dcv_6_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So he spread a great feast for them, and they ate and drank, after which he sent them away to return to their lord. And not once did the marauder bands of the Syrians<a class='mr'></a> come again into the land of Israel.</p></div><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Afterward Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria gathered all his army<a class='fn'></a> together and went up and besieged Sa·mar′i·a.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>So there was a great famine<a class='mr'></a> in Sa·mar′i·a, and they besieged it until a donkey’s head<a class='mr'></a> was worth 80 silver pieces, and a fourth of a cab measure<a class='fn'></a> of dove’s droppings was worth 5 silver pieces. <span id='dcv_6_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>As the king of Israel was passing by on the wall, a woman cried out to him: “Help us, O my lord the king!” <span id='dcv_6_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>To this he said: “If Jehovah does not help you, where can I get help for you? From the threshing floor? Or from the wine or oil press?” <span id='dcv_6_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>The king asked her: “What is the matter with you?” She replied: “This woman said to me, ‘Hand over your son, and we will eat him today, and we will eat my son tomorrow.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>So we boiled my son and ate him.<a class='mr'></a> The next day I said to her, ‘Hand over your son so that we may eat him.’ But she hid her son.”</p></div><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>As soon as the king heard the woman’s words, he ripped his garments apart.<a class='mr'></a> When he passed by on the wall, the people saw that he was wearing sackcloth under his clothes.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Then he said: “So may God do to me and add to it if the head of E·li′sha the son of Sha′phat remains on him today!”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>E·li′sha was sitting in his house, and the elders were sitting with him. The king sent a man ahead of him, but before the messenger arrived, E·li′sha said to the elders: “Have you seen how this son of a murderer<a class='mr'></a> has sent to take off my head? Watch when the messenger comes, close the door, and hold the door shut against him. Is not the sound of his lord’s footsteps behind him?” <span id='dcv_6_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>While he was still speaking with them, the messenger came to him, and the king said: “This calamity is from Jehovah. Why should I wait any longer for Jehovah?”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dp'><a>7 </a></span>E·li′sha now said, “Listen to the word of Jehovah. This is what Jehovah says: ‘Tomorrow about this time at the gate<a class='fn'></a> of Sa·mar′i·a, a seah measure<a class='fn'></a> of fine flour will be worth a shekel,<a class='fn'></a> and two seah measures of barley will be worth a shekel.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>At that the adjutant whom the king relied on said to the man of the true God: “Even if Jehovah should open floodgates in the heavens, could this<a class='fn'></a> possibly take place?”<a class='mr'></a> To that he said: “You will see it with your own eyes,<a class='mr'></a> but you will not eat from it.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>There were four lepers at the entrance of the city gate,<a class='mr'></a> and they said to one another: “Why are we sitting here until we die? <span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>If we say, ‘Let us go into the city,’ while the famine is in the city,<a class='mr'></a> we would die there. And if we sit here, we will die anyway. So now let us go over to the camp of the Syrians. If they spare our lives, we will live, but if they put us to death, then we will die.” <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>They then got up in the evening darkness and entered the camp of the Syrians. When they reached the outskirts of the Syrian camp, there was nobody there.</p></div><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>For Jehovah had caused the Syrian camp to hear the sound of war chariots and horses, the sound of a huge army.<a class='mr'></a> So they said to one another: “Look! The king of Israel has hired the kings of the Hit′tites and the kings of Egypt to come against us!” <span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>They immediately got up and fled in the evening darkness, leaving their tents, horses, donkeys, and the whole camp just as it was, and they fled for their lives.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>When these lepers reached the outskirts of the camp, they entered into one of the tents and began to eat and drink. They carried away from there silver, gold, and garments and went and hid them. Then they returned and entered another tent and carried things away from there and went and hid them.</p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Finally they said to one another: “What we are doing is not right. This day is a day of good news! If we hesitate and wait until dawn, we will deserve to be punished. Let us now go and report this at the king’s house.” <span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So they went and called out to the gatekeepers of the city and reported to them: “We went into the camp of the Syrians, but nobody was there—we did not hear anyone at all. There were only the horses and donkeys tied and the tents left just as they were.” <span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>At once the gatekeepers called out, and it was reported inside the king’s house.</p></div><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Immediately the king got up by night and said to his servants: “Please let me tell you what the Syrians have done to us. They know that we are hungry,<a class='mr'></a> so they left the camp to hide in the field, saying, ‘They will come out of the city, and we will catch them alive and enter into the city.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then one of his servants said: “Please, let some men take five of the remaining horses that are in the city. Look! They will end up the same as all the crowd of Israel that remain here. Look! They will end up the same as all the crowd of Israel that perished. Let us then send them out and see.” <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>So they took two chariots with horses, and the king sent them out to the camp of the Syrians, saying: “Go and see.” <span id='dcv_7_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>They followed them as far as the Jordan, and the entire way was covered with garments and utensils that the Syrians had thrown away as they fled in panic. The messengers returned and reported it to the king.</p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>The people then went out and plundered the camp of the Syrians, so that a seah measure of fine flour came to be worth a shekel, and two seah measures of barley came to be worth a shekel, according to the word of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>The king had appointed the adjutant whom he relied on to be in charge of the gate, but the people trampled him to death at the gate, just as the man of the true God had told the king when he came down to him. <span id='dcv_7_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>It happened just as the man of the true God had said to the king: “Two seah measures of barley will be worth a shekel, and a seah measure of fine flour will be worth a shekel tomorrow at this time at the gate of Sa·mar′i·a.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But the adjutant had said to the man of the true God: “Even if Jehovah should open floodgates in the heavens, could such a thing<a class='fn'></a> take place?” To this E·li′sha had said: “You will see it with your own eyes, but you will not eat from it.” <span id='dcv_7_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>That is exactly what happened to him, because the people trampled him to death at the gate.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dp'><a>8 </a></span>E·li′sha said to the woman whose son he had restored to life:<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> “Rise up and go, you with your household, and live as a foreigner wherever you can, for Jehovah has declared a famine,<a class='mr'></a> and it will come on the land for seven years.” <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>So the woman got up and did what the man of the true God said. She went with her household and settled in the land of the Phi·lis′tines<a class='mr'></a> for seven years.</p></div><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>At the end of seven years, the woman returned from the land of the Phi·lis′tines and went to appeal to the king for her house and her field. <span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now the king was speaking to Ge·ha′zi the attendant of the man of the true God, saying: “Relate to me, please, all the great things that E·li′sha has done.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Just as he was relating to the king how he had restored the dead one to life,<a class='mr'></a> the woman whose son he had restored to life came to the king, appealing for her house and her field.<a class='mr'></a> At once Ge·ha′zi said: “My lord the king, this is the woman, and this is her son, whom E·li′sha restored to life.” <span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>At that the king asked the woman, and she related the story to him. Then the king assigned her a court official, telling him: “Return all that belongs to her and all the products of the field from the day she left the land until now.”</p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>E·li′sha came to Damascus<a class='mr'></a> when Ben-ha′dad<a class='mr'></a> the king of Syria was sick. So the report was made to him: “The man of the true God<a class='mr'></a> has come here.” <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>At that the king said to Haz′a·el:<a class='mr'></a> “Take a gift with you and go and meet the man of the true God.<a class='mr'></a> Inquire of Jehovah through him, asking, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’” <span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Haz′a·el went to meet him and took a gift with him, every sort of good thing of Damascus, the load of 40 camels. He came and stood before him and said: “Your son, Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria, has sent me to you, asking, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’” <span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>E·li′sha replied to him: “Go and tell him, ‘You will certainly recover,’ but Jehovah has shown me that he will certainly die.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And he kept staring at him to the point of embarrassment. Then the man of the true God gave way to weeping. <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Haz′a·el asked: “Why is my lord weeping?” He replied: “Because I know what harm you will do to the people of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> Their fortified places you will set on fire, their choice men you will kill with the sword, their children you will dash to pieces, and their pregnant women you will rip open.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Haz′a·el said: “How could your servant, who is a mere dog, do such a deed?” But E·li′sha said: “Jehovah has shown me that you will be king over Syria.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then he left E·li′sha and returned to his own lord, who said to him: “What did E·li′sha say to you?” He replied: “He told me that you will certainly recover.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>But the next day, Haz′a·el took a coverlet, dipped it in water, and held<a class='fn'></a> it over his face until he died.<a class='mr'></a> And Haz′a·el became king in his place.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>In the fifth year of Je·ho′ram<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′hab the king of Israel, while Je·hosh′a·phat was king of Judah, Je·ho′ram<a class='mr'></a> the son of King Je·hosh′a·phat of Judah became king. <span id='dcv_8_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>He was 32 years old when he became king, and he reigned for eight years in Jerusalem. <span id='dcv_8_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>He walked in the way of the kings of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> just as those of the house of A′hab had done,<a class='mr'></a> for A′hab’s daughter had become his wife;<a class='mr'></a> and he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But Jehovah did not want to bring Judah to ruin for the sake of David his servant,<a class='mr'></a> since he had promised him to give a lamp to him<a class='mr'></a> and to his sons always.</p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>In his days E′dom revolted against Judah<a class='mr'></a> and then set up its own king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>So Je·ho′ram crossed over to Za′ir with all his chariots, and he rose up by night and defeated the E′dom·ites who were surrounding him and the chariot commanders; and the troops fled to their tents. <span id='dcv_8_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>But E′dom has kept up its revolt against Judah to this day. Lib′nah<a class='mr'></a> also revolted at that time.</p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>And the rest of the history of Je·ho′ram, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_8_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Then Je·ho′ram was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David.<a class='mr'></a> And his son A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>In the 12th year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab the king of Israel, A·ha·zi′ah the son of King Je·ho′ram of Judah became king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>A·ha·zi′ah was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ath·a·li′ah<a class='mr'></a> the granddaughter<a class='fn'></a> of King Om′ri<a class='mr'></a> of Israel. <span id='dcv_8_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>He walked in the way of the house of A′hab<a class='mr'></a> and kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, like the house of A′hab, for he was related to the house of A′hab by marriage.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>So he went with Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab to wage war against King Haz′a·el of Syria at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> but the Syrians wounded Je·ho′ram.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>So King Je·ho′ram returned to Jez′re·el<a class='mr'></a> to recover from the wounds that the Syrians had inflicted on him at Ra′mah when he fought against King Haz′a·el of Syria.<a class='mr'></a> A·ha·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ram the king of Judah went down to Jez′re·el to see Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab, because he had been wounded.<a class='fn'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>E·li′sha the prophet then called one of the sons of the prophets and said to him: “Wrap your garments around your waist, and quickly take this flask of oil with you and go to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>When you arrive there, look for Je′hu<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Nim′shi; go in and have him get up from among his brothers and take him into the innermost room. <span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then take the flask of oil and pour it out on his head and say, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I anoint you as king over Israel.”’<a class='mr'></a> Then open the door and flee without delay.”</p></div><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So the prophet’s attendant got on his way to Ra′moth-gil′e·ad. <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>When he arrived, the army chiefs were seated there. He said: “I have a message for you, O chief.” Je′hu asked: “For which one of us?” He said: “For you, O chief.” <span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So Je′hu got up and went into the house; the attendant poured the oil out on his head and said to him, “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘I anoint you as king over Jehovah’s people, over Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>You must strike down the house of A′hab your lord, and I will avenge the blood of my servants the prophets and of all the servants of Jehovah who died at the hands of Jez′e·bel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>And the whole house of A′hab will perish; and I will annihilate from A′hab every male,<a class='fn'></a> including the helpless and weak in Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>And I will make the house of A′hab like the house of Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ne′bat and like the house of Ba′a·sha<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·hi′jah. <span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>As for Jez′e·bel, the dogs will eat her up in the plot of land at Jez′re·el,<a class='mr'></a> and no one will bury her.’” With that he opened the door and fled.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>When Je′hu went back to the servants of his lord, they asked him: “Is everything all right? Why did this crazy man come to you?” He answered them: “You know that sort of man and his sort of talk.” <span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>But they said: “That is not true! Tell us, please.” Then he said: “This is what he said to me, and then he added, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I anoint you as king over Israel.”’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>At this each of them quickly took his garment and put it under him on the bare steps,<a class='mr'></a> and they blew the horn and said: “Je′hu has become king!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then Je′hu<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Nim′shi conspired against Je·ho′ram.</p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sb'>Je·ho′ram had been on guard at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> he with all Israel, because of King Haz′a·el<a class='mr'></a> of Syria. <span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>King Je·ho′ram later returned to Jez′re·el<a class='mr'></a> to recover from the wounds that the Syrians inflicted on him when he fought King Haz′a·el of Syria.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sb'>Je′hu now said: “If you agree,<a class='fn'></a> do not let anyone escape from the city to go and report this in Jez′re·el.” <span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then Je′hu mounted his chariot and went to Jez′re·el, for Je·ho′ram was lying there wounded, and King A·ha·zi′ah of Judah had gone down to see Je·ho′ram. <span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>As the watchman was standing on the tower in Jez′re·el, he saw the throng of Je′hu’s men approaching. At once he said: “I see a throng of men.” Je·ho′ram said: “Take a cavalryman and send him to meet them, and let him say, ‘Are you coming in peace?’” <span id='dcv_9_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So a horseman went to meet him and said: “This is what the king says, ‘Are you coming in peace?’” But Je′hu said: “What do you have to do with ‘peace’? Fall in behind me!”</p></div><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sb'>The watchman then reported: “The messenger reached them, but he has not returned.” <span id='dcv_9_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So he sent out a second horseman, who said when he came to them: “This is what the king says, ‘Are you coming in peace?’” But Je′hu said: “What do you have to do with ‘peace’? Fall in behind me!”</p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>The watchman then reported: “He reached them, but he has not returned, and the driving is like the driving of Je′hu the grandson<a class='fn'></a> of Nim′shi, for he drives like a madman.” <span id='dcv_9_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Je·ho′ram said: “Hitch up!” So his war chariot was hitched up and King Je·ho′ram of Israel and King A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah each went out in his own war chariot to meet Je′hu. They encountered him in the plot of land of Na′both<a class='mr'></a> the Jez′re·el·ite.</p></div><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>As soon as Je·ho′ram saw Je′hu, he said: “Are you coming in peace, Je′hu?” But he said: “What peace could there be as long as there is the prostitution of Jez′e·bel<a class='mr'></a> your mother and her many sorceries?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>At once Je·ho′ram turned his chariot to flee, and he said to A·ha·zi′ah: “We have been tricked, A·ha·zi′ah!” <span id='dcv_9_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Je′hu took his bow in hand and shot Je·ho′ram between the shoulders, and the arrow came out at his heart, and he collapsed in his war chariot. <span id='dcv_9_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>He then said to Bid′kar his adjutant: “Pick him up and throw him into the field of Na′both the Jez′re·el·ite.<a class='mr'></a> Remember, you and I were riding together<a class='fn'></a> behind A′hab his father when Jehovah himself made this pronouncement against him:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>‘“As surely as I saw the blood of Na′both<a class='mr'></a> and the blood of his sons yesterday,” declares Jehovah, “I will repay<a class='mr'></a> you in this very plot of land,” declares Jehovah.’ So now pick him up and throw him into the plot of land, according to the word of Jehovah.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>When King A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah saw what was happening, he fled by way of the garden house. (Later Je′hu pursued him and said: “Strike him down also!” So they struck him down in the chariot on his way up to Gur, which is by Ib′le·am.<a class='mr'></a> But he continued his flight to Me·gid′do and died there. <span id='dcv_9_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then his servants carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and they buried him in his grave with his forefathers in the City of David.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>It was in the 11th year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab that A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> had become king over Judah.)</p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>When Je′hu came to Jez′re·el,<a class='mr'></a> Jez′e·bel<a class='mr'></a> heard of it. So she painted her eyes with black paint<a class='fn'></a> and adorned her head and looked down through the window. <span id='dcv_9_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>As Je′hu came in through the gate, she said: “Did it go well with Zim′ri, the killer of his lord?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Looking up to the window, he said: “Who is on my side? Who?”<a class='mr'></a> Immediately two or three court officials looked down at him. <span id='dcv_9_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>He said: “Throw her down!” So they threw her down, and some of her blood splattered on the wall and on the horses, and he trampled her. <span id='dcv_9_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>After that he went in and ate and drank. He then said: “Please, take care of this accursed woman and bury her. After all, she is the daughter of a king.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>But when they went to bury her, they did not find anything but her skull and her feet and the palms of her hands.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>When they returned and told him, he said: “This fulfills the word of Jehovah<a class='mr'></a> that he spoke through his servant E·li′jah the Tish′bite, saying, ‘In the plot of land of Jez′re·el, the dogs will eat the flesh of Jez′e·bel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>And the dead body of Jez′e·bel will become as manure on the surface of the field in the plot of land of Jez′re·el, so that they may not say: “This is Jez′e·bel.”’”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now A′hab<a class='mr'></a> had 70 sons in Sa·mar′i·a. So Je′hu wrote letters and sent them to Sa·mar′i·a, to the princes of Jez′re·el, the elders,<a class='mr'></a> and the guardians of A′hab’s children,<a class='fn'></a> saying: <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Now when this letter comes to you, the sons of your lord will be with you, as well as the war chariots, the horses, a fortified city, and weapons. <span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Select the best and most suitable<a class='fn'></a> of the sons of your lord and put him on the throne of his father. Then fight for the house of your lord.”</p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>But they were overcome with fear and said: “Look! If two kings could not stand before him,<a class='mr'></a> how can we stand?” <span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So the overseer of the palace,<a class='fn'></a> the governor of the city, the elders, and the guardians sent this message to Je′hu: “We are your servants, and we will do everything that you tell us. We will not make anyone king. Do whatever seems good in your eyes.”</p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then he wrote them a second letter, saying: “If you belong to me and are willing to obey me, bring the heads of the sons of your lord and come to me tomorrow at this time at Jez′re·el.”</p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sb'>Now the 70 sons of the king were with the distinguished men of the city who were raising them. <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>As soon as the letter came to them, they took the sons of the king and slaughtered them, 70 men,<a class='mr'></a> and they put their heads in baskets and sent them to him at Jez′re·el. <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>The messenger came in and told him: “They have brought the heads of the sons of the king.” So he said: “Put them in two heaps at the entrance of the city gate until morning.” <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>When he went out in the morning, he stood before all the people and said: “You are innocent.<a class='fn'></a> Yes, I conspired against my lord, and I killed him,<a class='mr'></a> but who struck down all of these? <span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Know, then, that not a single word of Jehovah’s that Jehovah has spoken against the house of A′hab will go unfulfilled,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and Jehovah has done what he spoke through his servant E·li′jah.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Moreover, Je′hu struck down all who were left of the house of A′hab in Jez′re·el, as well as all his distinguished men, his acquaintances, and his priests,<a class='mr'></a> until he had left him no survivor.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then he got up and went on his way to Sa·mar′i·a. The binding house<a class='fn'></a> of the shepherds was on the way. <span id='dcv_10_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>There Je′hu encountered the brothers of King A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah, and he said to them, “Who are you?” They said: “We are the brothers of A·ha·zi′ah, and we are on our way down to ask if all is well with the sons of the king and the sons of the queen mother.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_10_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Immediately he said: “Capture them alive!” So they captured them alive and slaughtered them at the cistern of the binding house, 42 men. He did not let a single one of them survive.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>As he went from there, he encountered Je·hon′a·dab<a class='mr'></a> the son of Re′chab,<a class='mr'></a> who was coming to meet him. When he greeted<a class='fn'></a> him, he said to him: “Is your heart fully<a class='fn'></a> with me, just as my heart is with your heart?”</p></div><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sb'>Je·hon′a·dab replied: “It is.”</p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sb'>“If so, give me your hand.”</p></div><div id='p82' class='par'><p class='sb'>So he gave him his hand, and Je′hu pulled him up into the chariot with him. <span id='dcv_10_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then he said: “Come along with me, and see my toleration of no rivalry toward<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah.”<a class='mr'></a> So they had him ride with him in his war chariot. <span id='dcv_10_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then he came to Sa·mar′i·a, and he struck down all who were left over of A′hab’s house in Sa·mar′i·a until he had annihilated them,<a class='mr'></a> according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken to E·li′jah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p83' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Further, Je′hu collected all the people together and said to them: “A′hab worshipped Ba′al a little,<a class='mr'></a> but Je′hu will worship him much more. <span id='dcv_10_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>So summon all the prophets of Ba′al,<a class='mr'></a> all his worshippers, and all his priests<a class='mr'></a> to me. Do not let a single one be absent, because I have a great sacrifice for Ba′al. Anyone who is absent will not live.” But Je′hu was acting with cunning to destroy the worshippers of Ba′al.</p></div><div id='p84' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Je′hu continued: “Declare<a class='fn'></a> a solemn assembly for Ba′al.” So they proclaimed it. <span id='dcv_10_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>After that Je′hu sent word throughout Israel, and all the worshippers of Ba′al came. Not a single one was left out who did not come. They entered the house<a class='fn'></a> of Ba′al,<a class='mr'></a> and the house of Ba′al was filled from end to end. <span id='dcv_10_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>He said to the one who was in charge of the wardrobe: “Bring out garments for all the worshippers of Ba′al.” So he brought out the clothing for them. <span id='dcv_10_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Then Je′hu and Je·hon′a·dab<a class='mr'></a> the son of Re′chab went into the house of Ba′al. He now said to the worshippers of Ba′al: “Search carefully and see that there are no worshippers of Jehovah here, only worshippers of Ba′al.” <span id='dcv_10_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Finally they came in to offer up sacrifices and burnt offerings. Je′hu had stationed 80 of his men outside and said: “If any one of the men I am putting into your hands escapes, it will be your life for his.”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p85' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>As soon as he finished offering up the burnt offering, Je′hu said to the guards<a class='fn'></a> and the adjutants: “Come in and strike them down! Do not let a single one escape!”<a class='mr'></a> So the guards and the adjutants struck them down with the sword and threw them out, and they kept going as far as the inner sanctuary<a class='fn'></a> of the house of Ba′al. <span id='dcv_10_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Then they brought out the sacred pillars<a class='mr'></a> of the house of Ba′al and burned each one.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>They tore down the sacred pillar<a class='mr'></a> of Ba′al, and they tore down the house of Ba′al<a class='mr'></a> and turned it into latrines, as it remains to this day.</p></div><div id='p86' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Thus Je′hu annihilated Ba′al out of Israel. <span id='dcv_10_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>However, Je′hu did not turn away from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit as regards the golden calves that were in Beth′el and in Dan.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So Jehovah said to Je′hu: “Because you have acted well and have done what is right in my eyes by carrying out all that was in my heart to do to the house of A′hab,<a class='mr'></a> four generations of your sons will sit on the throne of Israel.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>But Je′hu did not take care to walk in the Law of Jehovah the God of Israel with all his heart.<a class='mr'></a> He did not turn away from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p87' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>In those days Jehovah started to cut off<a class='fn'></a> Israel piece by piece. Haz′a·el kept attacking them throughout the territory of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>from the Jordan eastward, all the land of Gil′e·ad—of the Gad′ites, the Reu′ben·ites, and the Ma·nas′sites<a class='mr'></a>—from A·ro′er, which is by the Ar′non Valley,<a class='fn'></a> to Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p88' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>And the rest of the history of Je′hu, all that he did and all his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_10_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Then Je′hu was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·mar′i·a; and his son Je·ho′a·haz<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place. <span id='dcv_10_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>The length<a class='fn'></a> of Je′hu’s reign over Israel was 28 years in Sa·mar′i·a.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p89' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Now when Ath·a·li′ah,<a class='mr'></a> A·ha·zi′ah’s mother, saw that her son had died,<a class='mr'></a> she rose up and destroyed the entire royal line.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>However, Je·hosh′e·ba the daughter of King Je·ho′ram, A·ha·zi′ah’s sister, took Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·ha·zi′ah and stole him away from among the sons of the king who were to be put to death, keeping him and his nurse in an inner bedroom. They managed to keep him concealed from Ath·a·li′ah, so he was not put to death. <span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He remained with her for six years, hidden at the house of Jehovah, while Ath·a·li′ah was ruling over the land.</p></div><div id='p90' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>In the seventh year, Je·hoi′a·da sent for the chiefs of hundreds of the Ca′ri·an bodyguard and of the palace guards<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and had them come to him at the house of Jehovah. He made a pact<a class='fn'></a> with them and had them swear to it at the house of Jehovah, and then he showed them the son of the king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>He ordered them: “This is what you are to do: One third of you will be on duty on the Sabbath and will keep strict watch over the king’s house,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>another third will be at the Gate of the Foundation, and another third will be at the gate behind the palace guards. You will take turns watching over the house. <span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Your two divisions that are supposed to be off duty on the Sabbath must keep strict watch over the house of Jehovah to protect the king. <span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>You must surround the king on every side, each with his weapons in hand. Anyone entering within the ranks will be put to death. Stay with the king wherever he goes.”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p91' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The chiefs of hundreds<a class='mr'></a> did exactly what Je·hoi′a·da the priest had commanded. So each one took his men who were on duty on the Sabbath, together with those who were off duty on the Sabbath, and they came in to Je·hoi′a·da the priest.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>The priest then gave the chiefs of hundreds the spears and the circular shields that had belonged to King David, which were in the house of Jehovah. <span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And the palace guards<a class='mr'></a> took their positions, each with his weapons in hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, by the altar<a class='mr'></a> and by the house, all around the king. <span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then Je·hoi′a·da brought the king’s son<a class='mr'></a> out and put on him the crown<a class='fn'></a> and the Testimony,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and they made him king and anointed him. They began to clap their hands and say: “Long live the king!”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p92' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>When Ath·a·li′ah heard the sound of the people running, she immediately came to the people at the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then she saw the king standing there by the pillar according to the custom.<a class='mr'></a> The chiefs and the trumpeters<a class='mr'></a> were with the king, and all the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing the trumpets. At this Ath·a·li′ah ripped her garments apart and cried out: “Conspiracy! Conspiracy!” <span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>But Je·hoi′a·da the priest commanded the chiefs of hundreds,<a class='mr'></a> those appointed over the army, and said to them: “Take her out from among the ranks, and if anyone follows her, put him to death with the sword!” For the priest had said: “Do not put her to death in the house of Jehovah.” <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>So they seized her, and when she reached the place where the horses enter the king’s house,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> she was put to death there.</p></div><div id='p93' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then Je·hoi′a·da made a covenant between Jehovah and the king and the people,<a class='mr'></a> that they would continue as the people of Jehovah, and he also made a covenant between the king and the people.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>After that all the people of the land came to the house<a class='fn'></a> of Ba′al and tore down his altars,<a class='mr'></a> completely smashed his images,<a class='mr'></a> and killed Mat′tan the priest of Ba′al<a class='mr'></a> in front of the altars.</p></div><div id='p94' class='par'><p class='sb'>Then the priest appointed overseers over the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Further, he took the chiefs of hundreds,<a class='mr'></a> the Ca′ri·an bodyguard, the palace guards,<a class='mr'></a> and all the people of the land to escort the king down from the house of Jehovah, and they came to the king’s house<a class='fn'></a> by the way of the gate of the palace guard. He then sat on the throne of the kings.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So all the people of the land rejoiced and the city was quiet, for they had put Ath·a·li′ah to death with the sword at the king’s house.</p></div><div id='p95' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> was seven years old when he became king.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p96' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dp'><a>12 </a></span>In the seventh year of Je′hu,<a class='mr'></a> Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> became king, and he reigned for 40 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Zib′i·ah from Be′er-she′ba.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Je·ho′ash continued doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes all the days that Je·hoi′a·da the priest instructed him. <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>However, the high places<a class='mr'></a> were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.</p></div><div id='p97' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Je·ho′ash said to the priests: “Take all the money that is brought to the house of Jehovah for the holy offerings,<a class='mr'></a> the money for which each one is assessed,<a class='mr'></a> the money given as an estimated value for a person,<a class='fn'></a> and all the money that each person’s heart is moved to bring to the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>The priests will personally take it from their donors<a class='fn'></a> and use it to repair the house, wherever any damage is<a class='fn'></a> found.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p98' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>By the 23rd year of King Je·ho′ash, the priests had not yet repaired the damage to the house.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>So King Je·ho′ash called Je·hoi′a·da<a class='mr'></a> the priest and the other priests and said to them: “Why are you not repairing the damage to the house? Therefore, do not take any more money from your donors unless it is used to repair the house.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>At that the priests agreed not to take any more money from the people and not to be responsible for repairing the house.</p></div><div id='p99' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Je·hoi′a·da the priest then took a chest<a class='mr'></a> and bored a hole in its lid and put it next to the altar on the right as one enters the house of Jehovah. That is where the priests who served as doorkeepers would put all the money that was brought into the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Whenever they saw that there was a great deal of money in the chest, the secretary of the king and the high priest would come up and collect<a class='fn'></a> and count the money that had been brought to the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>They would give the money that had been counted to those appointed over the work being done in the house of Jehovah. They, in turn, paid it to the woodworkers and to the builders who were working at the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>as well as to the masons and the stonecutters. They also bought timbers and hewn stones for repairing the damage to the house of Jehovah and used the money for all the other expenses incurred in repairing the house.</p></div><div id='p100' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>However, none of the money brought to the house of Jehovah was used to make basins of silver, extinguishers, bowls, trumpets,<a class='mr'></a> or any sort of gold or silver article for the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>They would give it only to those who did the work, and with it they repaired the house of Jehovah. <span id='dcv_12_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>They would not call for an accounting from the men to whom they gave the money to give to the workers, for they were trustworthy.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>However, the money for guilt offerings<a class='mr'></a> and the money for sin offerings was not brought to the house of Jehovah; it belonged to the priests.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p101' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>It was then that Haz′a·el<a class='mr'></a> the king of Syria went up to fight against Gath,<a class='mr'></a> and he captured it, after which he decided to attack<a class='fn'></a> Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>At that King Je·ho′ash of Judah took all the holy offerings that his forefathers Je·hosh′a·phat, Je·ho′ram, and A·ha·zi′ah, the kings of Judah, had sanctified, as well as his own holy offerings and all the gold to be found in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah and the king’s house,<a class='fn'></a> and sent them to Haz′a·el the king of Syria.<a class='mr'></a> So he withdrew from Jerusalem.</p></div><div id='p102' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Je·ho′ash, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_12_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>However, his servants joined in a conspiracy against him<a class='mr'></a> and struck Je·ho′ash down at the house of the Mound,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> on the way that goes down to Sil′la. <span id='dcv_12_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>His servants Jo′za·car the son of Shim′e·ath and Je·hoz′a·bad the son of Sho′mer were the ones who struck him and put him to death.<a class='mr'></a> They buried him with his forefathers in the City of David, and his son Am·a·zi′ah became king in his place.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p103' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dp'><a>13 </a></span>In the 23rd year of Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·ha·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> the king of Judah, Je·ho′a·haz the son of Je′hu<a class='mr'></a> became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for 17 years. <span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and he persisted in the sin that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> He did not turn away from it. <span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>So Jehovah’s anger<a class='mr'></a> grew hot against Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and he gave them into the hand of King Haz′a·el<a class='mr'></a> of Syria and into the hand of Ben-ha′dad<a class='mr'></a> the son of Haz′a·el all their days.</p></div><div id='p104' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>In time Je·ho′a·haz begged for the favor<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah, and Jehovah listened to him, for he had seen the oppression the king of Syria had inflicted on Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So Jehovah provided Israel with a savior<a class='mr'></a> to free them from Syria’s grip, and the Israelites were able to dwell in their homes as before.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>(However, they did not depart from the sin of the house of Jer·o·bo′am that he had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> They continued in this sin,<a class='fn'></a> and the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> continued to stand in Sa·mar′i·a.) <span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Je·ho′a·haz was left with an army of only 50 horsemen, 10 chariots, and 10,000 foot soldiers, because the king of Syria had destroyed them,<a class='mr'></a> trampling them like the dust at threshing time.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p105' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Je·ho′a·haz, all that he did and his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then Je·ho′a·haz was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·mar′i·a;<a class='mr'></a> and his son Je·ho′ash became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p106' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>In the 37th year of King Je·ho′ash of Judah, Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·ho′a·haz became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for 16 years. <span id='dcv_13_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, not departing from all the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had made Israel commit.<a class='mr'></a> He continued<a class='fn'></a> in these sins.</p></div><div id='p107' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Je·ho′ash, all that he did and his mightiness and how he fought against King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah,<a class='mr'></a> is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_13_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then Je·ho′ash was laid to rest with his forefathers, and Jer·o·bo′am<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> sat on his throne. And Je·ho′ash was buried in Sa·mar′i·a with the kings of Israel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p108' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Now when E·li′sha<a class='mr'></a> became ill with the sickness from which he eventually died, Je·ho′ash the king of Israel came down to him and wept over him, saying: “My father, my father! The chariot of Israel and his horsemen!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>E·li′sha then said to him: “Take a bow and arrows.” So he took a bow and arrows. <span id='dcv_13_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then he said to the king of Israel: “Put your hand to the bow.” So he put his hand to it, after which E·li′sha laid his hands on the king’s hands. <span id='dcv_13_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then he said: “Open the window toward the east.” So he opened it. E·li′sha said: “Shoot!” So he shot. He now said: “Jehovah’s arrow of victory,<a class='fn'></a> the arrow of victory over<a class='fn'></a> Syria! You will strike down<a class='fn'></a> Syria at A′phek<a class='mr'></a> until you finish it off.”</p></div><div id='p109' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>He continued: “Take the arrows,” and he took them. Then he said to the king of Israel: “Strike the ground.” So he struck the ground three times and stopped. <span id='dcv_13_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>At that the man of the true God grew indignant at him and said: “You should have struck the ground five or six times! Then you would have struck down Syria until you finished it off, but now you will strike down Syria only three times.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p110' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>After that E·li′sha died and was buried. There were Mo′ab·ite marauder bands<a class='mr'></a> that would come into the land at the beginning of the year.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_13_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>As some men were burying a man, they saw the marauder band, so they quickly threw the man into E·li′sha’s burial place and ran off. When the man touched the bones of E·li′sha, he came to life<a class='mr'></a> and stood on his feet.</p></div><div id='p111' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Now King Haz′a·el<a class='mr'></a> of Syria oppressed Israel<a class='mr'></a> all the days of Je·ho′a·haz. <span id='dcv_13_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>However, Jehovah extended favor and mercy to them<a class='mr'></a> and showed his concern for them for the sake of his covenant with Abraham,<a class='mr'></a> Isaac,<a class='mr'></a> and Jacob.<a class='mr'></a> He did not want to bring them to ruin, and he has not cast them away from his presence to this day. <span id='dcv_13_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>When King Haz′a·el of Syria died, his son Ben-ha′dad became king in his place. <span id='dcv_13_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz then took back from Ben-ha′dad the son of Haz′a·el the cities that he had taken in war from Je·ho′a·haz his father. Three times Je·ho′ash struck him down,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and he recovered the cities of Israel.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="14"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p112' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>In the second year of Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel, Am·a·zi′ah the son of King Je·ho′ash of Judah became king. <span id='dcv_14_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ho·ad′din of Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, but not like David<a class='mr'></a> his forefather. He did everything as Je·ho′ash his father had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>However, the high places were not removed,<a class='mr'></a> and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>As soon as he had the kingdom firmly in his control, he struck down his servants who had struck down his father the king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But he did not put the sons of the murderers to death, in harmony with Jehovah’s commandment written in the book of Moses’ Law: “Fathers should not be put to death for their sons, and sons should not be put to death for their fathers; but each one should be put to death for his own sin.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>He struck down the E′dom·ites<a class='mr'></a> in the Valley of Salt,<a class='mr'></a> 10,000 men, and captured Se′la in the war,<a class='mr'></a> and its name became Jok′the·el to this day.</p></div><div id='p113' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then Am·a·zi′ah sent messengers to Je·ho′ash son of Je·ho′a·haz son of Je′hu the king of Israel, saying: “Come, let us confront each other in battle.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>King Je·ho′ash of Israel sent this message to King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah: “The thorny weed in Leb′a·non sent a message to the cedar in Leb′a·non, ‘Give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ However, a wild beast of Leb′a·non passed by and trampled down the thorny weed. <span id='dcv_14_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>True, you have struck down E′dom,<a class='mr'></a> so your heart has become arrogant. Enjoy your glory, but stay in your own house.<a class='fn'></a> Why should you provoke disaster and fall, bringing Judah down with you?” <span id='dcv_14_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But Am·a·zi′ah did not listen.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p114' class='par'><p class='sb'>So King Je·ho′ash of Israel went up, and he and King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah confronted each other in battle at Beth-she′mesh,<a class='mr'></a> which belongs to Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Judah was defeated by Israel, so each one fled to his home.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>King Je·ho′ash of Israel captured King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah, son of Je·ho′ash son of A·ha·zi′ah, at Beth-she′mesh. Then they came to Jerusalem, and he made a breach in the wall of Jerusalem from the Gate of E′phra·im<a class='mr'></a> to the Corner Gate,<a class='mr'></a> 400 cubits.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>He took all the gold and the silver and all the articles that were found in the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the house<a class='fn'></a> of the king, as well as hostages. Then he returned to Sa·mar′i·a.</p></div><div id='p115' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Je·ho′ash, what he did and his mightiness and how he fought against King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_14_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then Je·ho′ash was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·mar′i·a<a class='mr'></a> with the kings of Israel; and his son Jer·o·bo′am<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p116' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Am·a·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah lived for 15 years after the death of Je·ho′ash<a class='mr'></a> the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Am·a·zi′ah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_14_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Later a conspiracy was formed against him<a class='mr'></a> at Jerusalem, and he fled to La′chish, but they sent men after him to La′chish and put him to death there. <span id='dcv_14_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So they carried him back on horses, and he was buried in Jerusalem with his forefathers in the City of David.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then all the people of Judah took Az·a·ri′ah,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> who was 16 years old,<a class='mr'></a> and made him king in place of his father Am·a·zi′ah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>He rebuilt E′lath<a class='mr'></a> and restored it to Judah after the king<a class='fn'></a> was laid to rest with his forefathers.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p117' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>In the 15th year of Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah, Jer·o·bo′am<a class='mr'></a> the son of King Je·ho′ash of Israel became king in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for 41 years. <span id='dcv_14_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>He restored the boundary of Israel from Le′bo-ha′math<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> clear to the Sea of the Ar′a·bah,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> according to the word that Jehovah the God of Israel spoke through his servant Jo′nah<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·mit′tai, the prophet from Gath-he′pher.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>For Jehovah had seen the very bitter affliction of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> There was no one left to help Israel, not even the helpless or the weak. <span id='dcv_14_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>But Jehovah had promised not to wipe out the name of Israel from under the heavens.<a class='mr'></a> So he saved them by the hand of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Je·ho′ash.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p118' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Jer·o·bo′am, all that he did and his mightiness, how he fought and how he restored Damascus<a class='mr'></a> and Ha′math<a class='mr'></a> to Judah in Israel, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_14_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Then Jer·o·bo′am was laid to rest with his forefathers, with the kings of Israel; and his son Zech·a·ri′ah<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="15"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p119' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>In the 27th year of King Jer·o·bo′am<a class='fn'></a> of Israel, Az·a·ri′ah<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the son of King Am·a·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah became king.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He was 16 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 52 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·co·li′ah of Jerusalem. <span id='dcv_15_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Am·a·zi′ah had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>However, the high places were not removed,<a class='mr'></a> and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Jehovah afflicted the king, and he remained a leper<a class='mr'></a> until the day of his death; and he stayed in a separate house,<a class='mr'></a> while the king’s son Jo′tham<a class='mr'></a> was in charge of the house,<a class='fn'></a> judging the people of the land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Az·a·ri′ah,<a class='mr'></a> all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_15_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then Az·a·ri′ah was laid to rest with his forefathers,<a class='mr'></a> and they buried him with his forefathers in the City of David; and his son Jo′tham became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p120' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>In the 38th year of King Az·a·ri′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah, Zech·a·ri′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Jer·o·bo′am became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for six months. <span id='dcv_15_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his forefathers had done. He did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh conspired against him and struck him down<a class='mr'></a> at Ib′le·am.<a class='mr'></a> After putting him to death, he became king in his place. <span id='dcv_15_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Zech·a·ri′ah, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. <span id='dcv_15_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>That fulfilled Jehovah’s word spoken to Je′hu: “Four generations of your sons<a class='mr'></a> will sit on the throne of Israel.”<a class='mr'></a> And that is how it happened.</p></div><div id='p121' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh became king in the 39th year of King Uz·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah, and he reigned for a full month in Sa·mar′i·a. <span id='dcv_15_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then Men′a·hem the son of Ga′di came up from Tir′zah<a class='mr'></a> to Sa·mar′i·a and struck down Shal′lum<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ja′besh in Sa·mar′i·a. After putting him to death, he became king in his place. <span id='dcv_15_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Shal′lum and the conspiracy that he formed, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. <span id='dcv_15_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>It was then that Men′a·hem came from Tir′zah and struck down Tiph′sah and all who were in it and its territory, because it did not open its gates to him. He struck it down and ripped open its pregnant women.</p></div><div id='p122' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>In the 39th year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Men′a·hem the son of Ga′di became king over Israel, and he reigned for ten years in Sa·mar′i·a. <span id='dcv_15_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit,<a class='mr'></a> all his days. <span id='dcv_15_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>King Pul<a class='mr'></a> of As·syr′i·a came into the land, and Men′a·hem gave Pul 1,000 talents<a class='fn'></a> of silver in return for his support in strengthening his hold on the kingdom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>So Men′a·hem raised the silver from Israel by exacting it from the prominent, wealthy men.<a class='mr'></a> He gave the king of As·syr′i·a 50 silver shekels<a class='fn'></a> for each man. Then the king of As·syr′i·a turned back and did not stay in the land. <span id='dcv_15_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Men′a·hem,<a class='mr'></a> all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? <span id='dcv_15_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Then Men′a·hem was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Pek·a·hi′ah became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p123' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>In the 50th year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Pek·a·hi′ah the son of Men′a·hem became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for two years. <span id='dcv_15_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Then his adjutant Pe′kah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Rem·a·li′ah conspired against him and struck him down in Sa·mar′i·a in the fortified tower of the king’s house<a class='fn'></a> with Ar′gob and A·ri′eh. He had 50 men of Gil′e·ad with him; and after he put him to death, he became king in his place. <span id='dcv_15_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Pek·a·hi′ah, all that he did, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel.</p></div><div id='p124' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>In the 52nd year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Pe′kah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Rem·a·li′ah became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for 20 years. <span id='dcv_15_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and he did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>In the days of King Pe′kah of Israel, King Tig′lath-pil·e′ser<a class='mr'></a> of As·syr′i·a invaded and captured I′jon, A′bel-beth-ma′a·cah,<a class='mr'></a> Ja·no′ah, Ke′desh,<a class='mr'></a> Ha′zor, Gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> and Gal′i·lee—all the land of Naph′ta·li<a class='mr'></a>—and he took the inhabitants into exile in As·syr′i·a.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>Then Ho·she′a<a class='mr'></a> the son of E′lah formed a conspiracy against Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah, and he struck him and put him to death; and he became king in his place in the 20th year of Jo′tham<a class='mr'></a> the son of Uz·zi′ah. <span id='dcv_15_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Pe′kah, all that he did, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel.</p></div><div id='p125' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>In the second year of Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah the king of Israel, Jo′tham<a class='mr'></a> the son of King Uz·zi′ah<a class='mr'></a> of Judah became king. <span id='dcv_15_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 16 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ru′sha the daughter of Za′dok.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Uz·zi′ah had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.<a class='mr'></a> He was the one who built the upper gate of the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Jo′tham, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_15_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>In those days Jehovah began sending Re′zin the king of Syria and Pe′kah<a class='mr'></a> the son of Rem·a·li′ah against Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>Then Jo′tham was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather. And his son A′haz became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="16"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p126' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_1' class='dc dp'><a>16 </a></span>In the 17th year of Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah, A′haz<a class='mr'></a> the son of King Jo′tham of Judah became king. <span id='dcv_16_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>A′haz was 20 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 16 years in Jerusalem. He did not do what was right in the eyes of Jehovah his God as David his forefather had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Instead, he walked in the way of the kings of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and he even made his own son pass through the fire,<a class='mr'></a> following the detestable practices of the nations<a class='mr'></a> that Jehovah had driven out from before the Israelites. <span id='dcv_16_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>He also kept sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places,<a class='mr'></a> on the hills, and under every luxuriant tree.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p127' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>It was then that King Re′zin of Syria and Pe′kah son of Rem·a·li′ah the king of Israel came up to wage war against Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> They laid siege against A′haz but were not able to capture the city. <span id='dcv_16_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>At that time King Re′zin of Syria restored E′lath<a class='mr'></a> to E′dom, after which he drove the Jews<a class='fn'></a> out of E′lath. And the E′dom·ites entered E′lath, and they have occupied it down to this day. <span id='dcv_16_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>So A′haz sent messengers to King Tig′lath-pil·e′ser<a class='mr'></a> of As·syr′i·a, saying: “I am your servant and your son. Come up and save me from the hand of the king of Syria and the hand of the king of Israel, who are attacking me.” <span id='dcv_16_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>A′haz then took the silver and the gold that was to be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the king’s house<a class='fn'></a> and sent the king of As·syr′i·a a bribe.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>The king of As·syr′i·a responded to his request, and he went up to Damascus and captured it and led its people into exile to Kir,<a class='mr'></a> and he put Re′zin to death.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p128' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then King A′haz went to meet King Tig′lath-pil·e′ser of As·syr′i·a at Damascus. When he saw the altar that was in Damascus, King A′haz sent U·ri′jah the priest a plan of the altar, showing its pattern and how it was made.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>U·ri′jah<a class='mr'></a> the priest built an altar<a class='mr'></a> according to all the directions that King A′haz had sent from Damascus. U·ri′jah the priest finished building it before King A′haz returned from Damascus. <span id='dcv_16_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>When the king returned from Damascus and saw the altar, he approached the altar and made offerings on it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>And on that altar he continued to make his burnt offerings and his grain offerings smoke; he also poured out his drink offerings and sprinkled the blood of his communion sacrifices on it. <span id='dcv_16_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then he moved the copper altar<a class='mr'></a> that was before Jehovah from its place in front of the house, from between his own altar and the house of Jehovah, and he put it at the north side of his own altar. <span id='dcv_16_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>King A′haz commanded U·ri′jah<a class='mr'></a> the priest: “Make the morning burnt offering smoke on the great altar,<a class='mr'></a> also the evening grain offering,<a class='mr'></a> the king’s burnt offering, and his grain offering, as well as the burnt offerings, the grain offerings, and the drink offerings of all the people. You should also sprinkle on it all the blood of the burnt offerings and all the blood of the other sacrifices. As for the copper altar, let me decide what to do with it.” <span id='dcv_16_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>And U·ri′jah the priest did everything that King A′haz had commanded.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p129' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Furthermore, King A′haz cut the side panels of the carriages<a class='mr'></a> into pieces and removed the basins from them,<a class='mr'></a> and he took the Sea down off the copper bulls<a class='mr'></a> that supported it and put it on a stone pavement.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>And the covered structure for the Sabbath that had been built in the house and the king’s outer entryway he shifted away from the house of Jehovah; he did so because of the king of As·syr′i·a.</p></div><div id='p130' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of A′haz, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Then A′haz was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David; and his son Hez·e·ki′ah<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="17"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p131' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>In the 12th year of King A′haz of Judah, Ho·she′a<a class='mr'></a> the son of E′lah became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a; he ruled for nine years. <span id='dcv_17_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, only not to the extent of the kings of Israel prior to him. <span id='dcv_17_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>King Shal·man·e′ser of As·syr′i·a came up against him,<a class='mr'></a> and Ho·she′a became his servant and began to pay tribute to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>However, the king of As·syr′i·a learned that Ho·she′a was involved in a conspiracy, for he had sent messengers to King So of Egypt<a class='mr'></a> and did not bring the tribute up to the king of As·syr′i·a as in former years. Therefore, the king of As·syr′i·a kept him confined and bound in prison.</p></div><div id='p132' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>The king of As·syr′i·a invaded the entire land, and he came to Sa·mar′i·a and laid siege to it for three years. <span id='dcv_17_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>In the ninth year of Ho·she′a, the king of As·syr′i·a captured Sa·mar′i·a.<a class='mr'></a> He then led the people of Israel into exile<a class='mr'></a> in As·syr′i·a and made them dwell in Ha′lah and in Ha′bor at the river Go′zan<a class='mr'></a> and in the cities of the Medes.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p133' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>This happened because the people of Israel had sinned against Jehovah their God, who brought them up out of the land of Egypt from under the control of Phar′aoh king of Egypt.<a class='mr'></a> They worshipped<a class='fn'></a> other gods,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>they followed the customs of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the Israelites, and they followed the customs that the kings of Israel had established.</p></div><div id='p134' class='par'><p class='sb'>&#160;<span id='dcv_17_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The Israelites were pursuing the things that were not right according to Jehovah their God. They kept building high places in all their cities,<a class='mr'></a> from watchtower to fortified city.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_17_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>They kept setting up for themselves sacred pillars and sacred poles<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> on every high hill and under every luxuriant tree;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>and on all the high places they would make sacrificial smoke just as the nations did that Jehovah had driven into exile from before them.<a class='mr'></a> They kept doing wicked things to offend Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p135' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>They continued to serve disgusting idols,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> about which Jehovah had told them: “You must not do this!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Jehovah kept warning Israel and Judah through all his prophets and every visionary,<a class='mr'></a> saying: “Turn back from your wicked ways!<a class='mr'></a> Keep my commandments and my statutes according to all the law that I commanded your forefathers and that I sent to you through my servants the prophets.” <span id='dcv_17_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But they did not listen, and they remained just as stubborn as<a class='fn'></a> their forefathers who had not shown faith in Jehovah their God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>They continued rejecting his regulations and his covenant<a class='mr'></a> that he had made with their forefathers and his reminders that he had given to warn them,<a class='mr'></a> and they kept following worthless idols<a class='mr'></a> and became worthless themselves,<a class='mr'></a> imitating the nations all around them that Jehovah had commanded them not to imitate.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p136' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>They kept leaving all the commandments of Jehovah their God, and they made metal statues<a class='fn'></a> of two calves<a class='mr'></a> and a sacred pole,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and they bowed down to all the army of the heavens<a class='mr'></a> and served Ba′al.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>They also made their sons and their daughters pass through the fire,<a class='mr'></a> they practiced divination<a class='mr'></a> and looked for omens, and they kept devoting<a class='fn'></a> themselves to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, to offend him.</p></div><div id='p137' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>So Jehovah was very angry with Israel, so that he removed them from his sight.<a class='mr'></a> He did not let any remain but the tribe of Judah alone.</p></div><div id='p138' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Even Judah did not keep the commandments of Jehovah their God;<a class='mr'></a> they also walked in the customs that Israel followed.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Jehovah rejected all the descendants of Israel and humiliated them and gave them into the hand of plunderers, until he had cast them away from before him. <span id='dcv_17_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>He ripped Israel away from the house of David, and they made Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat king.<a class='mr'></a> But Jer·o·bo′am caused Israel to stray from following Jehovah, and he caused them to commit a great sin. <span id='dcv_17_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And the people of Israel kept walking in all the sins that Jer·o·bo′am had committed.<a class='mr'></a> They did not depart from them <span id='dcv_17_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>until Jehovah removed Israel from his sight, just as he had declared through all his servants the prophets.<a class='mr'></a> So Israel was taken into exile from its land to As·syr′i·a,<a class='mr'></a> where they remain to this day.</p></div><div id='p139' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>The king of As·syr′i·a then brought people from Babylon, Cu′thah, Av′va, Ha′math, and Seph·ar·va′im<a class='mr'></a> and settled them in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a in place of the Israelites; they took possession of Sa·mar′i·a and lived in its cities. <span id='dcv_17_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>When they first began dwelling there, they did not fear<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah. So Jehovah sent lions among them,<a class='mr'></a> and they killed some of the people. <span id='dcv_17_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>It was reported to the king of As·syr′i·a: “The nations that you have taken into exile and resettled in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a do not know the religion<a class='fn'></a> of the God of the land. So he keeps sending lions among them, which are putting them to death, because none of them know the religion of the God of the land.”</p></div><div id='p140' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>At that the king of As·syr′i·a commanded: “Have one of the priests whom you took into exile from there return to live there and to teach them the religion of the God of the land.” <span id='dcv_17_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>So one of the priests whom they had taken into exile from Sa·mar′i·a came back to live in Beth′el,<a class='mr'></a> and he began to teach them how they should fear<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p141' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>However, each different nation made their own god,<a class='fn'></a> which they placed in the houses of worship on the high places that the Sa·mar′i·tans had made; each different nation did so in their cities where they were living. <span id='dcv_17_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>So the men of Babylon made Suc′coth-be′noth, the men of Cuth made Ner′gal, the men of Ha′math<a class='mr'></a> made A·shi′ma, <span id='dcv_17_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>and the Av′vites made Nib′haz and Tar′tak. The Se′phar·vites would burn their sons in the fire to A·dram′me·lech and A·nam′me·lech, the gods of Seph·ar·va′im.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Although they feared Jehovah, they appointed priests for the high places from the people in general, and these officiated for them at the houses of worship on the high places.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Thus, they feared Jehovah, but they worshipped their own gods according to the religion<a class='fn'></a> of the nations from which they had been deported.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p142' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>To this day they follow their former religions.<a class='fn'></a> None of them worship<a class='fn'></a> Jehovah, and none follow his statutes, his judgments, the Law, and the commandment that Jehovah gave the sons of Jacob, whose name he changed to Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>When Jehovah made a covenant with them,<a class='mr'></a> he commanded them: “You must not fear other gods, and you must not bow down to them or serve them or sacrifice to them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>But Jehovah, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt with great power and an outstretched arm,<a class='mr'></a> is the One you should fear,<a class='mr'></a> and to him you should bow down, and to him you should sacrifice. <span id='dcv_17_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>And the regulations, the judgments, the Law, and the commandment that he wrote for you,<a class='mr'></a> you should always follow carefully, and you must not fear other gods. <span id='dcv_17_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>And you must not forget the covenant that I made with you,<a class='mr'></a> and you must not fear other gods. <span id='dcv_17_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>But it is Jehovah your God whom you should fear, as he is the one who will rescue you out of the hand of all your enemies.”</p></div><div id='p143' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>But they did not obey, and they followed their former religion.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>So these nations came to fear Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> but they were also serving their own graven images. Both their sons and their grandsons have done just as their forefathers did, down to this day.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="18"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p144' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>In the third year of Ho·she′a<a class='mr'></a> the son of E′lah the king of Israel, Hez·e·ki′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of King A′haz<a class='mr'></a> of Judah became king. <span id='dcv_18_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was A′bi<a class='fn'></a> the daughter of Zech·a·ri′ah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes,<a class='mr'></a> just as David his forefather had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>He was the one who removed the high places,<a class='mr'></a> smashed the sacred pillars, and cut down the sacred pole.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> He also crushed the copper serpent that Moses had made;<a class='mr'></a> for down to that time the people of Israel had been making sacrificial smoke to it and it used to be called the copper serpent-idol.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_18_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>He trusted in Jehovah<a class='mr'></a> the God of Israel; there was no one like him among all the kings of Judah after him nor among those prior to him. <span id='dcv_18_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>He held fast to Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> He did not turn away from following him; he continued to keep the commandments that Jehovah had given to Moses. <span id='dcv_18_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>And Jehovah was with him. Wherever he went, he acted wisely. He rebelled against the king of As·syr′i·a and refused to serve him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>He also defeated the Phi·lis′tines<a class='mr'></a> clear to Gaz′a and its territories, from watchtower to fortified city.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p145' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>In the fourth year of King Hez·e·ki′ah, that is, the seventh year of Ho·she′a<a class='mr'></a> the son of E′lah the king of Israel, King Shal·man·e′ser of As·syr′i·a came up against Sa·mar′i·a and began to lay siege to it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>They captured it<a class='mr'></a> at the end of three years; in the sixth year of Hez·e·ki′ah, which was the ninth year of King Ho·she′a of Israel, Sa·mar′i·a was captured. <span id='dcv_18_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Then the king of As·syr′i·a took Israel into exile<a class='mr'></a> in As·syr′i·a and settled them in Ha′lah and in Ha′bor at the river Go′zan and in the cities of the Medes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>This was because they had not listened to the voice of Jehovah their God but kept violating his covenant, all that Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded.<a class='mr'></a> They neither listened nor obeyed.</p></div><div id='p146' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>In the 14th year of King Hez·e·ki′ah, Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a<a class='mr'></a> came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and captured them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>So King Hez·e·ki′ah of Judah sent word to the king of As·syr′i·a at La′chish: “I am at fault. Withdraw from against me, and I will give whatever you may impose on me.” The king of As·syr′i·a imposed on King Hez·e·ki′ah of Judah a fine of 300 silver talents<a class='fn'></a> and 30 gold talents. <span id='dcv_18_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>So Hez·e·ki′ah gave all the silver that could be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the king’s house.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>At that time Hez·e·ki′ah removed<a class='fn'></a> the doors of the temple<a class='mr'></a> of Jehovah and the doorposts that King Hez·e·ki′ah of Judah himself had overlaid,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and he gave them to the king of As·syr′i·a.</p></div><div id='p147' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>The king of As·syr′i·a then sent the Tar′tan,<a class='fn'></a> the Rab′sa·ris,<a class='fn'></a> and the Rab′sha·keh<a class='fn'></a> with a vast army from La′chish<a class='mr'></a> to King Hez·e·ki′ah in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> They went up to Jerusalem and took up a position by the conduit of the upper pool, which is at the highway of the laundryman’s field.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>When they called for the king to come out, E·li′a·kim<a class='mr'></a> son of Hil·ki′ah, who was in charge of the household,<a class='fn'></a> Sheb′nah<a class='mr'></a> the secretary, and Jo′ah son of A′saph the recorder came out to them.</p></div><div id='p148' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So the Rab′sha·keh said to them: “Please, say to Hez·e·ki′ah, ‘This is what the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a, says: “What is the basis for your confidence?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>You are saying, ‘I have a strategy and the power to wage war,’ but these are empty words. In whom have you put your trust, so that you dare to rebel against me?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Look! You trust in the support of this crushed reed, Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> which if a man should lean on it would enter into his palm and pierce it. That is the way Phar′aoh king of Egypt is to all those who trust in him. <span id='dcv_18_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>And if you should say to me, ‘We trust in Jehovah our God,’<a class='mr'></a> is he not the one whose high places and altars Hez·e·ki′ah has removed,<a class='mr'></a> while he says to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘You should bow down before this altar in Jerusalem’?”’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So now make this wager, please, with my lord the king of As·syr′i·a: I will give you 2,000 horses if you are able to find enough riders for them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>How, then, could you drive back even one governor who is the least of my lord’s servants, while you put your trust in Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? <span id='dcv_18_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Now is it without authorization from Jehovah that I have come up against this place to destroy it? Jehovah himself said to me, ‘Go up against this land and destroy it.’”</p></div><div id='p149' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>At this E·li′a·kim son of Hil·ki′ah, and Sheb′nah<a class='mr'></a> and Jo′ah said to the Rab′sha·keh:<a class='mr'></a> “Speak to your servants, please, in the Ar·a·ma′ic<a class='fn'></a> language,<a class='mr'></a> for we can understand it; do not speak to us in the language of the Jews in the hearing of the people on the wall.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>But the Rab′sha·keh said to them: “Is it just to your lord and to you that my lord sent me to speak these words? Is it not also to the men who sit on the wall, those who will eat their own excrement and drink their own urine along with you?”</p></div><div id='p150' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then the Rab′sha·keh stood and called out loudly in the language of the Jews, saying: “Hear the word of the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>This is what the king says, ‘Do not let Hez·e·ki′ah deceive you, for he is not able to rescue you out of my hand.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>And do not let Hez·e·ki′ah cause you to trust in Jehovah by saying: “Jehovah will surely rescue us, and this city will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Do not listen to Hez·e·ki′ah, for this is what the king of As·syr′i·a says: “Make peace with me and surrender,<a class='fn'></a> and each of you will eat from his own vine and from his own fig tree and will drink the water of his own cistern, <span id='dcv_18_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>until I come and take you to a land like your own land,<a class='mr'></a> a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive trees and honey. Then you will live and not die. Do not listen to Hez·e·ki′ah, for he misleads you by saying, ‘Jehovah will rescue us.’ <span id='dcv_18_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Have any of the gods of the nations rescued their land out of the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a? <span id='dcv_18_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Where are the gods of Ha′math<a class='mr'></a> and Ar′pad? Where are the gods of Seph·ar·va′im,<a class='mr'></a> He′na, and Iv′vah? Have they rescued Sa·mar′i·a out of my hand?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Who among all the gods of the lands have rescued their land out of my hand, so that Jehovah should rescue Jerusalem out of my hand?”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p151' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>But the people kept silent and did not say a word to him in reply, for the order of the king was, “You must not answer him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>But E·li′a·kim son of Hil·ki′ah, who was in charge of the household,<a class='fn'></a> Sheb′nah the secretary, and Jo′ah son of A′saph the recorder came to Hez·e·ki′ah with their garments ripped apart and told him the words of the Rab′sha·keh.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="19"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p152' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>As soon as King Hez·e·ki′ah heard this, he ripped his garments apart and covered himself with sackcloth and went into the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then he sent E·li′a·kim, who was in charge of the household,<a class='fn'></a> Sheb′nah the secretary, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to the prophet Isaiah,<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′moz. <span id='dcv_19_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>They said to him: “This is what Hez·e·ki′ah says, ‘This day is a day of distress, of rebuke,<a class='fn'></a> and of disgrace; for the children are ready to be born,<a class='fn'></a> but there is no strength to give birth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Perhaps Jehovah your God will hear all the words of the Rab′sha·keh, whom the king of As·syr′i·a his lord sent to taunt the living God,<a class='mr'></a> and he will call him to account for the words that Jehovah your God has heard. So offer up a prayer<a class='mr'></a> in behalf of the remnant who have survived.’”</p></div><div id='p153' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So the servants of King Hez·e·ki′ah went in to Isaiah,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>and Isaiah said to them: “This is what you should say to your lord, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Do not be afraid<a class='mr'></a> because of the words that you heard, the words with which the attendants of the king of As·syr′i·a blasphemed me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Here I am putting a thought in his mind,<a class='fn'></a> and he will hear a report and return to his own land; and I will make him fall by the sword in his own land.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p154' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>After the Rab′sha·keh heard that the king of As·syr′i·a had pulled away from La′chish,<a class='mr'></a> he returned to him and found him fighting against Lib′nah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Now the king heard it said about King Tir·ha′kah of E·thi·o′pi·a: “Here he has come out to fight against you.” So he sent messengers<a class='mr'></a> again to Hez·e·ki′ah, saying: <span id='dcv_19_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>“This is what you should say to King Hez·e·ki′ah of Judah, ‘Do not let your God in whom you trust deceive you by saying: “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Look! You have heard what the kings of As·syr′i·a did to all the lands by devoting them to destruction.<a class='mr'></a> Will you alone be rescued? <span id='dcv_19_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Did the gods of the nations that my forefathers destroyed rescue them? Where are Go′zan, Ha′ran,<a class='mr'></a> Re′zeph, and the people of E′den who were in Tel-as′sar? <span id='dcv_19_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Where is the king of Ha′math, the king of Ar′pad, and the king of the cities of Seph·ar·va′im, and of He′na, and of Iv′vah?’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p155' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Hez·e·ki′ah took the letters out of the hand of the messengers and read them. Hez·e·ki′ah then went up to the house of Jehovah and spread them<a class='fn'></a> out before Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>And Hez·e·ki′ah began to pray<a class='mr'></a> before Jehovah and say: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, sitting enthroned above<a class='fn'></a> the cherubs,<a class='mr'></a> you alone are the true God of all the kingdoms of the earth.<a class='mr'></a> You made the heavens and the earth. <span id='dcv_19_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Incline your ear, O Jehovah, and hear!<a class='mr'></a> Open your eyes,<a class='mr'></a> O Jehovah, and see! Hear the words that Sen·nach′er·ib has sent to taunt the living God. <span id='dcv_19_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>It is a fact, O Jehovah, that the kings of As·syr′i·a have devastated the nations and their lands.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>And they have thrown their gods into the fire, because they were not gods<a class='mr'></a> but the work of human hands,<a class='mr'></a> wood and stone. That is why they could destroy them. <span id='dcv_19_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But now, O Jehovah our God, please save us out of his hand, so that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you alone are God, O Jehovah.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p156' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Isaiah son of A′moz then sent this message to Hez·e·ki′ah: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘I have heard your prayer<a class='mr'></a> to me concerning King Sen·nach′er·ib of As·syr′i·a.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>This is the word that Jehovah has spoken against him:</p></div><div id='p157' class='par'><p class='sz'>“The virgin daughter of Zion despises you, she scoffs at you.</p></div><div id='p158' class='par'><p class='sz'>The daughter of Jerusalem shakes her head at you.</p></div><div id='p159' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Whom have you taunted and blasphemed?<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p160' class='par'><p class='sz'>Against whom have you raised your voice<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And lifted your arrogant eyes?</p></div><div id='p161' class='par'><p class='sz'>It is against the Holy One of Israel!<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p162' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Through your messengers<a class='mr'></a> you have taunted Jehovah<a class='mr'></a> and said,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>‘With the multitude of my war chariots</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>I will ascend the heights of mountains,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The remotest parts of Leb′a·non.</p></div><div id='p163' class='par'><p class='sz'>I will cut down its lofty cedars, its choice juniper trees.</p></div><div id='p164' class='par'><p class='sz'>I will enter its farthest retreats, its densest forests.</p></div><div id='p165' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>I will dig wells and drink foreign waters;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>I will dry up all the streams<a class='fn'></a> of Egypt with the soles of my feet.’</p></div><div id='p166' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Have you not heard? From long ago it was determined.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p167' class='par'><p class='sz'>From days gone by I have prepared<a class='fn'></a> it.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p168' class='par'><p class='sz'>Now I will bring it about.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p169' class='par'><p class='sz'>You will turn fortified cities into desolate piles of ruins.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p170' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Their inhabitants will be helpless;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>They will be terrified and put to shame.</p></div><div id='p171' class='par'><p class='sz'>They will become as vegetation of the field and green grass,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>As grass of the roofs that is scorched by the east wind.</p></div><div id='p172' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>But I well know when you sit, when you go out, when you come in,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And when you are enraged against me,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sl'><span class='br'></span><span id='dcv_19_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Because your rage against me<a class='mr'></a> and your roaring have reached my ears.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p173' class='par'><p class='sz'>So I will put my hook in your nose and my bridle<a class='mr'></a> between your lips,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will lead you back the way you came.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p174' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>“‘And this will be the sign for you:<a class='fn'></a> This year you will eat what grows on its own;<a class='fn'></a> and in the second year you will eat grain that sprouts from that;<a class='mr'></a> but in the third year you will sow seed and reap, and you will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Those of the house of Judah who escape, those who are left,<a class='mr'></a> will take root downward and produce fruit upward. <span id='dcv_19_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>For a remnant will go out of Jerusalem and survivors from Mount Zion. The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p175' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>“‘Therefore this is what Jehovah says about the king of As·syr′i·a:<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p176' class='par'><p class='sz'>“He will not come into this city<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Or shoot an arrow there</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Or confront it with a shield</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Or cast up a siege rampart against it.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p177' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>By the way he came he will return;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>He will not come into this city,” declares Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p178' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_19_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>“I will defend this city<a class='mr'></a> and save it for my own sake<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And for the sake of my servant David.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p179' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>On that very night the angel of Jehovah went out and struck down 185,000 men in the camp of the As·syr′i·ans.<a class='mr'></a> When people rose up early in the morning, they saw all the dead bodies.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>So King Sen·nach′er·ib of As·syr′i·a departed and returned to Nin′e·veh<a class='mr'></a> and stayed there.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>And as he was bowing down at the house<a class='fn'></a> of his god Nis′roch, his own sons A·dram′me·lech and Shar·e′zer struck him down with the sword<a class='mr'></a> and then escaped to the land of Ar′a·rat.<a class='mr'></a> And his son E′sar-had′don<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="20"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p180' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_1' class='dc dp'><a>20 </a></span>In those days Hez·e·ki′ah became sick and was at the point of death.<a class='mr'></a> The prophet Isaiah the son of A′moz came and said to him, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Give instructions to your household, for you will die; you will not recover.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>At that he turned his face to the wall and began to pray to Jehovah: <span id='dcv_20_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>“I beg you, O Jehovah, remember, please, how I have walked before you faithfully and with a complete heart, and I have done what was good in your eyes.”<a class='mr'></a> And Hez·e·ki′ah began to weep profusely.</p></div><div id='p181' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Isaiah had not yet gone out to the middle courtyard when Jehovah’s word came to him, saying:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>“Go back and say to Hez·e·ki′ah, the leader of my people, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather says: “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears.<a class='mr'></a> Here I am healing you.<a class='mr'></a> On the third day you will go up to the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>I will add 15 years to your life,<a class='fn'></a> and I will rescue you and this city out of the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a,<a class='mr'></a> and I will defend this city for my own sake and for the sake of David my servant.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p182' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Isaiah then said: “Bring a cake of pressed dried figs.” So they brought it and applied it to the boil, after which he gradually recovered.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p183' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Hez·e·ki′ah had asked Isaiah: “What is the sign<a class='mr'></a> to show that Jehovah will heal me and that I will go up on the third day to the house of Jehovah?” <span id='dcv_20_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Isaiah replied: “This is the sign from Jehovah to show you that Jehovah will carry out the word that he has spoken: Do you want the shadow on the stairway<a class='fn'></a> to move forward ten steps or back ten steps?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Hez·e·ki′ah said: “It is an easy thing for the shadow to extend itself ten steps but not to go back ten steps.” <span id='dcv_20_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>So Isaiah the prophet called out to Jehovah, and He made the shadow on the stairway of A′haz go back ten steps after it had already descended the steps.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p184' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>At that time the king of Babylon, Be·ro′dach-bal′a·dan son of Bal′a·dan, sent letters and a gift to Hez·e·ki′ah, for he had heard that Hez·e·ki′ah had been sick.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Hez·e·ki′ah welcomed<a class='fn'></a> them and showed them his entire treasure-house<a class='mr'></a>—the silver, the gold, the balsam oil and other precious oil, his armory, and everything that was to be found in his treasuries. There was nothing that Hez·e·ki′ah did not show them in his own house<a class='fn'></a> and in all his dominion.</p></div><div id='p185' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>After that Isaiah the prophet came in to King Hez·e·ki′ah and asked him: “What did these men say, and where did they come from?” So Hez·e·ki′ah said: “They came from a distant land, from Babylon.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Next he asked: “What did they see in your house?”<a class='fn'></a> Hez·e·ki′ah replied: “They saw everything in my house.<a class='fn'></a> There was nothing that I did not show them in my treasuries.”</p></div><div id='p186' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Isaiah now said to Hez·e·ki′ah: “Hear the word of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>‘Look! Days are coming, and all that is in your house<a class='fn'></a> and all that your forefathers have stored up to this day will be carried off to Babylon.<a class='mr'></a> Nothing will be left,’ says Jehovah. <span id='dcv_20_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>‘And some of your own sons to whom you will become father will be taken<a class='mr'></a> and will become court officials in the palace of the king of Babylon.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p187' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>At that Hez·e·ki′ah said to Isaiah: “The word of Jehovah that you have spoken is good.”<a class='mr'></a> Then he added: “It is good if there will be peace and stability<a class='fn'></a> during my lifetime.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p188' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Hez·e·ki′ah, all his mightiness and how he made the pool<a class='mr'></a> and the conduit and brought the water into the city,<a class='mr'></a> is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_20_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then Hez·e·ki′ah was laid to rest with his forefathers;<a class='mr'></a> and his son Ma·nas′seh<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="21"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p189' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_1' class='dc dp'><a>21 </a></span>Ma·nas′seh<a class='mr'></a> was 12 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 55 years in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> His mother’s name was Heph′zi·bah. <span id='dcv_21_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, following the detestable practices of the nations<a class='mr'></a> that Jehovah had driven out from before the people of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>He rebuilt the high places that his father Hez·e·ki′ah had destroyed,<a class='mr'></a> and he set up altars to Ba′al and made a sacred pole,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> just as A′hab the king of Israel had done.<a class='mr'></a> And he bowed down to all the army of the heavens and served them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>He also built altars in the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> about which Jehovah had said: “In Jerusalem, I will put my name.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And he built altars to all the army of the heavens<a class='mr'></a> in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>And he made his own son pass through the fire; he practiced magic, looked for omens,<a class='mr'></a> and appointed spirit mediums and fortune-tellers.<a class='mr'></a> He did on a grand scale what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, to offend him.</p></div><div id='p190' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>He put the carved image of the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> that he made into the house about which Jehovah had said to David and to his son Sol′o·mon: “In this house and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will permanently put my name.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>And I will never again make the feet of Israel wander from the land that I gave to their forefathers,<a class='mr'></a> provided they carefully observe all that I have commanded them,<a class='mr'></a> the entire Law that my servant Moses ordered them to follow.” <span id='dcv_21_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>But they did not obey, and Ma·nas′seh kept leading them astray, causing them to do greater evil than the nations that Jehovah had annihilated from before the Israelites.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p191' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Jehovah kept speaking through his servants the prophets,<a class='mr'></a> saying: <span id='dcv_21_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>“Ma·nas′seh the king of Judah has done all these detestable things; he has acted more wickedly than all the Am′or·ites<a class='mr'></a> before him,<a class='mr'></a> and he has made Judah sin with his disgusting idols.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_21_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Here I am bringing such a disaster on Jerusalem<a class='mr'></a> and Judah that it will make both ears of anyone who hears about it tingle.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>And I will stretch out on Jerusalem the measuring line<a class='mr'></a> applied to Sa·mar′i·a<a class='mr'></a> and use the leveling tool<a class='fn'></a> applied to the house of A′hab,<a class='mr'></a> and I will wipe Jerusalem clean, just as one wipes a bowl clean, wiping it and turning it upside down.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>I will forsake the remnant of my inheritance<a class='mr'></a> and give them into the hand of their enemies, and they will become plunder and spoil to all their enemies,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>because they did what was bad in my eyes and were continually offending me from the day that their forefathers came out of Egypt to this day.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p192' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Ma·nas′seh also shed innocent blood in very great quantity until he had filled Jerusalem from one end to the other,<a class='mr'></a> besides his sin of causing Judah to sin by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah. <span id='dcv_21_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Ma·nas′seh and all that he did and the sins that he committed, are they not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_21_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then Ma·nas′seh was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the garden of his house, in the garden of Uz′za;<a class='mr'></a> and his son A′mon became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p193' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>A′mon<a class='mr'></a> was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for two years in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> His mother’s name was Me·shul′le·meth the daughter of Ha′ruz from Jot′bah. <span id='dcv_21_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Ma·nas′seh had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>He kept walking in all the ways that his father walked, and he continued serving and bowing down to the disgusting idols that his father had served.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>So he abandoned Jehovah the God of his forefathers, and he did not walk in the way of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Eventually A′mon’s servants conspired against him and put the king to death in his own house. <span id='dcv_21_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>But the people of the land struck down all those who conspired against King A′mon, and they made his son Jo·si′ah king in his place.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of A′mon, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_21_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>So they buried him in his grave in the garden of Uz′za,<a class='mr'></a> and his son Jo·si′ah<a class='mr'></a> became king in his place.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="22"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p194' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_1' class='dc dp'><a>22 </a></span>Jo·si′ah<a class='mr'></a> was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned for 31 years in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> His mother’s name was Je·di′dah the daughter of A·dai′ah from Boz′kath.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes and walked in all the ways of David his forefather,<a class='mr'></a> and he did not deviate to the right or to the left.</p></div><div id='p195' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>In the 18th year of King Jo·si′ah, the king sent Sha′phan the secretary, the son of Az·a·li′ah the son of Me·shul′lam, to the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> saying: <span id='dcv_22_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>“Go up to Hil·ki′ah<a class='mr'></a> the high priest, and let him collect all the money that is being brought into the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> which the doorkeepers have collected from the people.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Have them give it to those appointed over the work in the house of Jehovah who, in turn, will give it to the workers in the house of Jehovah who are to repair the damage to<a class='fn'></a> the house,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>that is, to the craftsmen, the builders, and the masons; and they are to use it to buy timbers and hewn stones to repair the house.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But no accounting should be required of them for the money that they are given, because they are trustworthy.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p196' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Later Hil·ki′ah the high priest said to Sha′phan the secretary:<a class='mr'></a> “I have found the book of the Law<a class='mr'></a> in the house of Jehovah.” So Hil·ki′ah gave the book to Sha′phan, who began to read it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then Sha′phan the secretary went to the king and told him: “Your servants have poured out the money that was found in the house, and they have handed it over to those appointed over the work in the house of Jehovah.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Sha′phan the secretary also told the king: “There is a book<a class='mr'></a> that Hil·ki′ah the priest has given me.” Then Sha′phan began to read it before the king.</p></div><div id='p197' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>As soon as the king heard the words of the book of the Law, he ripped his garments apart.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then the king gave this order to Hil·ki′ah the priest, A·hi′kam<a class='mr'></a> the son of Sha′phan, Ach′bor the son of Mi·cai′ah, Sha′phan the secretary, and A·sai′ah the king’s servant: <span id='dcv_22_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>“Go, inquire of Jehovah in my behalf, in behalf of the people, and in behalf of all Judah concerning the words of this book that has been found; for Jehovah’s rage that has been set ablaze against us is great,<a class='mr'></a> because our forefathers did not obey the words of this book by observing all that is written concerning us.”</p></div><div id='p198' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_22_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>So Hil·ki′ah the priest, A·hi′kam, Ach′bor, Sha′phan, and A·sai′ah went to Hul′dah the prophetess.<a class='mr'></a> She was the wife of Shal′lum son of Tik′vah son of Har′has, the caretaker of the wardrobe, and she was dwelling in the Second Quarter of Jerusalem; and they spoke to her there.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>She said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Tell the man who sent you to me: <span id='dcv_22_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah says, ‘I will bring calamity on this place and its inhabitants, all the words of the book that the king of Judah has read.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Because they have abandoned me and are making sacrifices smoke to other gods<a class='mr'></a> in order to offend me with all the work of their hands,<a class='mr'></a> my rage will be set ablaze against this place and it will not be extinguished.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_22_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>But to the king of Judah who sent you to inquire of Jehovah, this is what you should say to him, “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Regarding the words that you have heard, <span id='dcv_22_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>because your heart was responsive<a class='fn'></a> and you humbled yourself<a class='mr'></a> before Jehovah on hearing what I have spoken against this place and its inhabitants—that they would become an object of horror and a curse—and you ripped your garments apart<a class='mr'></a> and wept before me, I also have heard you, declares Jehovah. <span id='dcv_22_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>That is why I will gather you to your ancestors,<a class='fn'></a> and you will be laid in your grave in peace, and your eyes will not see all the calamity that I will bring on this place.’”’” Then they brought the reply to the king.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="23"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p199' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_1' class='dc dp'><a>23 </a></span>So the king sent word, and they summoned all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>After that the king went up to the house of Jehovah with all the men of Judah, all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests, and the prophets—all the people, from small to great. He read in their hearing all the words of the book<a class='mr'></a> of the covenant<a class='mr'></a> that had been found in the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>The king stood by the pillar and made a covenant<a class='fn'></a> before Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> that he would follow Jehovah and keep his commandments, his reminders, and his statutes with all his heart and with all his soul<a class='fn'></a> by carrying out the words of this covenant that were written in this book. And all the people agreed to the covenant.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p200' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>The king then ordered Hil·ki′ah<a class='mr'></a> the high priest, the priests of the second rank, and the doorkeepers to bring out from the temple of Jehovah all the utensils made for Ba′al, for the sacred pole,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and for all the army of the heavens. Then he burned them outside Jerusalem on the terraces of Kid′ron, and he took their ashes to Beth′el.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So he put out of business the foreign-god priests, whom the kings of Judah had appointed to make sacrificial smoke on the high places in the cities of Judah and the surroundings of Jerusalem, as well as those making sacrificial smoke to Ba′al, to the sun, to the moon, to the constellations of the zodiac, and to all the army of the heavens.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>He brought the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> out from the house of Jehovah to the outskirts of Jerusalem, to the Kid′ron Valley, and he burned it<a class='mr'></a> in the Kid′ron Valley and ground it to dust and scattered its dust on the graves of the common people.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>He also tore down the houses of the male temple prostitutes,<a class='mr'></a> which were in the house of Jehovah and where the women were weaving tent shrines for the sacred pole.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p201' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then he brought all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and he made unfit for worship the high places where the priests had been making sacrificial smoke, from Ge′ba<a class='mr'></a> to Be′er-she′ba.<a class='mr'></a> He also tore down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the gate of Joshua the chief of the city, which were on the left as one entered the city gate. <span id='dcv_23_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The priests of the high places did not serve at the altar of Jehovah in Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> but they did eat unleavened bread along with their brothers. <span id='dcv_23_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>He also made unfit for worship To′pheth,<a class='mr'></a> which is in the Valley of the Sons of Hin′nom,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> so that no one could make his son or his daughter pass through the fire to Mo′lech.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And he prohibited the horses that the kings of Judah had dedicated<a class='fn'></a> to the sun from entering the house of Jehovah by the chamber<a class='fn'></a> of Na′than-mel′ech the court official, which was in the porticoes; and he burned the chariots of the sun<a class='mr'></a> in the fire. <span id='dcv_23_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>The king also tore down the altars that the kings of Judah had set up on the roof<a class='mr'></a> of A′haz’s upper chamber, as well as the altars that Ma·nas′seh had set up in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> He crushed them and scattered their dust in the Kid′ron Valley. <span id='dcv_23_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>And the king made unfit for worship the high places in front of Jerusalem that were to the south<a class='fn'></a> of the Mount of Ruination,<a class='fn'></a> which Sol′o·mon the king of Israel had built to Ash′to·reth the disgusting goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans; and to Che′mosh the disgusting god of Mo′ab; and to Mil′com<a class='mr'></a> the detestable god of the Am′mon·ites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>He broke the sacred pillars to pieces and cut down the sacred poles<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and filled their places with human bones. <span id='dcv_23_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He also tore down the altar in Beth′el, the high place that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had made that caused Israel to sin.<a class='mr'></a> After tearing down that altar and the high place, he burned the high place, ground it to dust, and burned the sacred pole.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p202' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>When Jo·si′ah turned and saw the graves on the mountain, he had the bones taken from the graves and burned them on the altar, making it unfit for worship, according to Jehovah’s word that had been proclaimed by the man of the true God who foretold that these things would happen.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then he said: “What is the gravestone over there that I am looking at?” At this the men of the city said to him: “It is the grave of the man of the true God from Judah<a class='mr'></a> who foretold these things that you have done against the altar of Beth′el.” <span id='dcv_23_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>So he said: “Let him rest. Do not let anyone disturb his bones.” So they left his bones undisturbed, as well as the bones of the prophet who had come from Sa·mar′i·a.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p203' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Jo·si′ah also removed all the houses of worship on the high places that were in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a,<a class='mr'></a> which the kings of Israel had built to offend God, and he did the same thing to them that he had done at Beth′el.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>So he sacrificed on the altars all the priests of the high places who were there, and he burned human bones on them.<a class='mr'></a> After that he returned to Jerusalem.</p></div><div id='p204' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>The king now commanded all the people: “Hold a Passover<a class='mr'></a> to Jehovah your God as is written in this book of the covenant.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>No Passover like this had been held since the days when the judges had judged Israel or in all the days of the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>But in the 18th year of King Jo·si′ah, this Passover to Jehovah was held in Jerusalem.</p></div><div id='p205' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Jo·si′ah also cleared out the spirit mediums, the fortune-tellers,<a class='mr'></a> the teraphim statues,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the disgusting idols,<a class='fn'></a> and all the disgusting things that had appeared in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, in order to carry out the words of the Law<a class='mr'></a> that were written in the book that Hil·ki′ah the priest had found in the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>There was no king like him prior to him, who returned to Jehovah with all his heart and with all his soul<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and with all his strength, according to all the Law of Moses; nor did anyone like him rise up after him.</p></div><div id='p206' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Nevertheless, Jehovah did not turn away from his burning anger that blazed against Judah because of all the offensive things that Ma·nas′seh had done to offend Him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Jehovah said: “I will also remove Judah from my sight,<a class='mr'></a> just as I removed Israel;<a class='mr'></a> and I will reject this city that I chose, Jerusalem, and the house about which I said, ‘My name will continue there.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p207' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Jo·si′ah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? <span id='dcv_23_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>In his days Phar′aoh Ne′choh the king of Egypt came to meet the king of As·syr′i·a by the Eu·phra′tes River, and King Jo·si′ah went out to confront him; but when Ne′choh saw him, he put him to death at Me·gid′do.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So his servants transported his dead body in a chariot from Me·gid′do and brought him to Jerusalem and buried him in his grave. Then the people of the land took Jo·si′ah’s son Je·ho′a·haz and anointed him and made him king in place of his father.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p208' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Je·ho′a·haz<a class='mr'></a> was 23 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·mu′tal<a class='mr'></a> the daughter of Jeremiah from Lib′nah. <span id='dcv_23_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>He began to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his forefathers had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Phar′aoh Ne′choh<a class='mr'></a> imprisoned him at Rib′lah<a class='mr'></a> in the land of Ha′math, to keep him from reigning in Jerusalem, and then imposed on the land a fine of 100 silver talents<a class='fn'></a> and a gold talent.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Furthermore, Phar′aoh Ne′choh made Jo·si′ah’s son E·li′a·kim king in place of his father Jo·si′ah and changed his name to Je·hoi′a·kim; but he took Je·ho′a·haz and brought him to Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> where he eventually died.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_23_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Je·hoi′a·kim gave the silver and the gold to Phar′aoh, but he had to tax the land to give the silver that Phar′aoh demanded. He exacted an assessed amount of silver and gold from each of the people of the land to give to Phar′aoh Ne′choh.</p></div><div id='p209' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_23_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>Je·hoi′a·kim<a class='mr'></a> was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> His mother’s name was Ze·bi′dah the daughter of Pe·dai′ah from Ru′mah. <span id='dcv_23_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes,<a class='mr'></a> according to all that his forefathers had done.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="24"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p210' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_24_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>In Je·hoi′a·kim’s days King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar<a class='mr'></a> of Babylon came against him, and Je·hoi′a·kim became his servant for three years. However, he turned against him and rebelled. <span id='dcv_24_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then Jehovah began to send against him marauder bands of Chal·de′ans,<a class='mr'></a> Syrians, Mo′ab·ites, and Am′mon·ites. He kept sending them against Judah to destroy it, according to Jehovah’s word<a class='mr'></a> that he had spoken through his servants the prophets. <span id='dcv_24_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Surely it was by the order of Jehovah that this happened to Judah, to remove them from his sight<a class='mr'></a> because of all the sins that Ma·nas′seh had committed,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_24_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>and also the innocent blood that he had shed,<a class='mr'></a> for he had filled Jerusalem with innocent blood and Jehovah was not willing to forgive.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p211' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_24_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>As for the rest of the history of Je·hoi′a·kim, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_24_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then Je·hoi′a·kim was laid to rest with his forefathers;<a class='mr'></a> and his son Je·hoi′a·chin became king in his place.</p></div><div id='p212' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_24_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Never again did the king of Egypt venture out of his land, for the king of Babylon had taken all that belonged to the king of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> from the Wadi<a class='fn'></a> of Egypt<a class='mr'></a> up to the Eu·phra′tes River.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p213' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_24_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Je·hoi′a·chin<a class='mr'></a> was 18 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> His mother’s name was Ne·hush′ta the daughter of El·na′than of Jerusalem. <span id='dcv_24_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his father had done. <span id='dcv_24_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>During that time the servants of King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar of Babylon came up against Jerusalem, and the city came under siege.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_24_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar of Babylon came to the city while his servants were laying siege to it.</p></div><div id='p214' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_24_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>King Je·hoi′a·chin of Judah went out to the king of Babylon,<a class='mr'></a> along with his mother, his servants, his princes, and his court officials;<a class='mr'></a> and the king of Babylon took him captive in the eighth year of his reign.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_24_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then he took out from there all the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> He cut into pieces all the gold utensils that Sol′o·mon the king of Israel had made in the temple of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> just as Jehovah had foretold. <span id='dcv_24_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>He took into exile all Jerusalem, all the princes,<a class='mr'></a> all the mighty warriors, and every craftsman and metalworker<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a>—he took 10,000 into exile. No one was left behind except the poorest people of the land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_24_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Thus he took Je·hoi′a·chin<a class='mr'></a> into exile to Babylon;<a class='mr'></a> he also led away the king’s mother, the king’s wives, his court officials, and the foremost men of the land, taking them into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon. <span id='dcv_24_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>The king of Babylon also took into exile to Babylon all the warriors, 7,000, as well as 1,000 craftsmen and metalworkers,<a class='fn'></a> all of them mighty men and trained for war. <span id='dcv_24_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>The king of Babylon made Mat·ta·ni′ah, Je·hoi′a·chin’s uncle,<a class='mr'></a> king in his place and changed his name to Zed·e·ki′ah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p215' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_24_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Zed·e·ki′ah was 21 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·mu′tal<a class='mr'></a> the daughter of Jeremiah from Lib′nah. <span id='dcv_24_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Je·hoi′a·kim had done.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_24_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>It was because of Jehovah’s anger that these things took place in Jerusalem and in Judah, until he cast them out of his sight.<a class='mr'></a> And Zed·e·ki′ah rebelled against the king of Babylon.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="25"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p216' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_25_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>In the ninth year of Zed·e·ki′ah’s reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar<a class='mr'></a> of Babylon came with all his army against Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> He camped against it and built a siege wall all around it,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>and the city was under siege until the 11th year of King Zed·e·ki′ah. <span id='dcv_25_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>On the ninth day of the fourth month the famine was severe<a class='mr'></a> in the city, and there was no food for the people of the land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>The city wall was broken through,<a class='mr'></a> and all the soldiers fled by night through the gate between the double wall near the king’s garden, while the Chal·de′ans were surrounding the city; and the king went by the way of the Ar′a·bah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But the Chal·de′an army pursued the king, and they overtook him in the desert plains of Jer′i·cho, and all his troops were scattered from his side. <span id='dcv_25_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then they seized the king<a class='mr'></a> and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah, and they passed sentence on him. <span id='dcv_25_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>They slaughtered Zed·e·ki′ah’s sons before his eyes; then Neb·u·chad·nez′zar blinded Zed·e·ki′ah’s eyes, bound him with copper fetters, and brought him to Babylon.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p217' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_25_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>In the fifth month, on the seventh day of the month, that is, in the 19th year of King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon, Neb·u′zar·ad′an<a class='mr'></a> the chief of the guard, the servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He burned down the house of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> the king’s house,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and all the houses of Jerusalem;<a class='mr'></a> he also burned down the house of every prominent man.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>And the walls surrounding Jerusalem were pulled down by the entire Chal·de′an army that was with the chief of the guard.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard took into exile the rest of the people who were left in the city, the deserters who had gone over to the king of Babylon, and the rest of the population.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>But the chief of the guard left some of the poorest people of the land to serve as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>And the Chal·de′ans broke into pieces the copper pillars<a class='mr'></a> of the house of Jehovah and the carriages<a class='mr'></a> and the copper Sea<a class='mr'></a> that were in the house of Jehovah, and they carried the copper away to Babylon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>They also took the cans, the shovels, the extinguishers, the cups, and all the copper utensils used in the temple service. <span id='dcv_25_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>The chief of the guard took the fire holders and the bowls that were of genuine gold<a class='mr'></a> and silver.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>As for the two pillars, the Sea, and the carriages that Sol′o·mon had made for the house of Jehovah, the copper of all these articles was beyond weighing.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Each pillar was 18 cubits<a class='fn'></a> high,<a class='mr'></a> and the capital on it was of copper; and the height of the capital was three cubits, and the network and pomegranates all around on the capital were all made of copper.<a class='mr'></a> The second pillar with its network was like it.</p></div><div id='p218' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_25_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>The chief of the guard also took Se·rai′ah<a class='mr'></a> the chief priest, Zeph·a·ni′ah<a class='mr'></a> the second priest, and the three doorkeepers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>And he took from the city one court official who was the commissioner over the soldiers, five close associates of the king who were found in the city, as well as the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and 60 men of the common people of the land who were yet found in the city. <span id='dcv_25_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Neb·u′zar·ad′an<a class='mr'></a> the chief of the guard took them and brought them to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>The king of Babylon struck them down and put them to death at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math.<a class='mr'></a> Thus Judah went into exile from its land.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p219' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_25_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar of Babylon appointed Ged·a·li′ah<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·hi′kam<a class='mr'></a> the son of Sha′phan<a class='mr'></a> over the people whom he had left behind in the land of Judah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>When all the army chiefs and their men heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Ged·a·li′ah, they immediately came to Ged·a·li′ah at Miz′pah. They were Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah, Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah, Se·rai′ah the son of Tan·hu′meth the Ne·toph′a·thite, and Ja·az·a·ni′ah the son of the Ma·ac′a·thite, together with their men.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Ged·a·li′ah swore an oath to them and their men and said to them: “Do not be afraid of being servants to the Chal·de′ans. Live in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with you.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p220' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_25_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>And in the seventh month, Ish′ma·el<a class='mr'></a> son of Neth·a·ni′ah son of E·lish′a·ma, who was of the royal line,<a class='fn'></a> came with ten other men, and they struck down Ged·a·li′ah and he died, along with the Jews and the Chal·de′ans who were with him in Miz′pah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>After that all the people, from small to great, including the army chiefs, rose up and went to Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> for they were afraid of the Chal·de′ans.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p221' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_25_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>And in the 37th year of the exile of King Je·hoi′a·chin<a class='mr'></a> of Judah, in the 12th month, on the 27th day of the month, King E′vil-mer′o·dach of Babylon, in the year he became king, released<a class='fn'></a> King Je·hoi′a·chin of Judah from prison.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_25_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>He spoke kindly with him and put his throne higher than the thrones of the other kings who were with him in Babylon. <span id='dcv_25_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>So Je·hoi′a·chin took off his prison garments, and he regularly ate before him all the days of his life. <span id='dcv_25_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>A regular allowance of food was given him from the king, day after day, all the days of his life.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>