<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>In the eighth month in the second year of Da·ri′us,<a class='mr'></a> the word of Jehovah came to the prophet Zech·a·ri′ah<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> son of Ber·e·chi′ah son of Id′do, saying: <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Jehovah grew greatly indignant at your fathers.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>“Say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “‘Return to me,’ declares Jehovah of armies, ‘and I will return to you,’<a class='mr'></a> says Jehovah of armies.”’</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>“‘Do not become like your fathers, to whom the former prophets proclaimed: “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Turn away,<a class='fn'></a> please, from your evil ways and your evil deeds.’”’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'>“‘But they did not listen, and they paid no attention to me,’<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>“‘Where are your fathers now? And did the prophets live forever? <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>However, my words and my decrees that I commanded my servants, the prophets, caught up with your fathers, did they not?’<a class='mr'></a> So they returned to me and said: ‘Jehovah of armies has dealt with us according to our ways and our deeds, just as he had determined to do.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>On the 24th day of the 11th month, that is, the month of She′bat,<a class='fn'></a> in the second year of Da·ri′us,<a class='mr'></a> the word of Jehovah came to the prophet Zech·a·ri′ah son of Ber·e·chi′ah son of Id′do, saying: <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>“I saw a vision in the night. There was a man riding on a red horse, and he stood still among the myrtle trees in the ravine; and behind him there were red, reddish-brown, and white horses.”</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So I said: “Who are these, my lord?”</p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'>The angel who was speaking with me replied: “I will show you who these are.”</p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then the man who was standing still among the myrtle trees said: “These are the ones whom Jehovah has sent out to walk about in the earth.” <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And they said to the angel of Jehovah who was standing among the myrtle trees: “We have walked about in the earth, and look! the whole earth is quiet and undisturbed.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>So the angel of Jehovah said: “O Jehovah of armies, how long will you withhold your mercy from Jerusalem and the cities of Judah,<a class='mr'></a> with whom you have been indignant these 70 years?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Jehovah answered the angel who was speaking with me, with kind and comforting words. <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then the angel who was speaking with me told me: “Call out, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “I am zealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great zeal.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>With great indignation I am indignant with the nations that are at ease,<a class='mr'></a> because I felt indignant to a small extent,<a class='mr'></a> but they added to the calamity.”’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>“Therefore this is what Jehovah says: ‘“I will return to Jerusalem with mercy,<a class='mr'></a> and my own house will be built in her,”<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah of armies, “and a measuring line will be stretched out over Jerusalem.”’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>“Call out once more and say, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “My cities will again overflow with goodness; and Jehovah will again comfort Zion<a class='mr'></a> and again choose Jerusalem.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then I looked up and saw four horns.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>So I asked the angel who was speaking with me: “What are these?” He replied: “These are the horns that dispersed Judah,<a class='mr'></a> Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and Jerusalem.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Jehovah then showed me four craftsmen. <span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>I asked: “What are these coming to do?”</p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'>He said: “These are the horns that dispersed Judah to such an extent that no one was able to raise his head. These others will come to terrify them, to cast down the horns of the nations that lifted up their horns against the land of Judah, in order to disperse her.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>And I looked up and saw a man with a measuring line<a class='mr'></a> in his hand. <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So I asked: “Where are you going?”</p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'>He replied: “To measure Jerusalem, to see what is her width and what is her length.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>And look! the angel who was speaking with me went out, and another angel came to meet him. <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Then he said to him: “Run over there and tell that young man, ‘“Jerusalem will be inhabited<a class='mr'></a> as open rural country,<a class='fn'></a> because of all the men and livestock within her.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>And I will become to her,” declares Jehovah, “a wall of fire all around,<a class='mr'></a> and I will become the glory in her midst.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>“Come! Come! Flee from the land of the north,”<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'>“For I have scattered you to the four winds of the heavens,”<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>“Come, Zion! Make your escape, you who are dwelling with the daughter of Babylon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>For this is what Jehovah of armies says, who after being glorified<a class='fn'></a> has sent me to the nations that were plundering you:<a class='mr'></a> ‘Whoever touches you touches the pupil of my eye.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>For now I will wave my hand against them, and they will become plunder for their own slaves.’<a class='mr'></a> And you will certainly know that Jehovah of armies has sent me.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>“Shout for joy, O daughter of Zion;<a class='mr'></a> for I am coming,<a class='mr'></a> and I will reside in your midst,”<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah. <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>“Many nations will join themselves to Jehovah in that day,<a class='mr'></a> and they will become my people; and I will reside in your midst.” And you will have to know that Jehovah of armies has sent me to you. <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Jehovah will take possession of Judah as his portion on the holy ground, and he will again choose Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Be silent, all flesh,<a class='fn'></a> before Jehovah, for he is taking action from his holy dwelling.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And he showed me Joshua<a class='mr'></a> the high priest standing before the angel of Jehovah, and Satan<a class='mr'></a> was standing at his right hand to resist him. <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then the angel of Jehovah said to Satan: “May Jehovah rebuke you, O Satan,<a class='mr'></a> yes, may Jehovah, who has chosen Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> rebuke you! Is not this one a burning log snatched out of the fire?”</p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Now Joshua was clothed in filthy garments and standing before the angel. <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>The angel said to those standing before him, “Remove his filthy garments.” Then he said to him, “See, I have caused your error<a class='fn'></a> to pass away from you, and you will be clothed with fine garments.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So I said: “Let a clean turban be put on his head.”<a class='mr'></a> And they put the clean turban on his head and clothed him with garments; and the angel of Jehovah was standing nearby. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The angel of Jehovah then declared to Joshua: <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘If you will walk in my ways and carry out your responsibilities before me, then you will serve as a judge in my house<a class='mr'></a> and take care of<a class='fn'></a> my courtyards; and I will give you free access among these who are standing here.’</p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>“‘Hear, please, O High Priest Joshua, you and your companions who sit before you, for these men serve as a sign; look! I am bringing in my servant<a class='mr'></a> Sprout!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>See the stone that I have set before Joshua! On the one stone are seven eyes; and I am engraving an inscription on it,’ declares Jehovah of armies, ‘and I will take away the guilt of that land in one day.’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>“‘In that day,’ declares Jehovah of armies, ‘Each of you will invite your neighbor to come under your vine and under your fig tree.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dp'><a>4 </a></span>The angel who had been speaking with me came back and woke me up, as when waking someone from sleep. <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then he said to me: “What do you see?”</p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'>So I said: “I see, and look! a lampstand entirely of gold,<a class='mr'></a> with a bowl on top of it. There are seven lamps on it,<a class='mr'></a> yes, seven, and the lamps, which are at the top of it, have seven pipes. <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And next to it are two olive trees,<a class='mr'></a> one on the right of the bowl and one on the left.”</p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Then I asked the angel who was speaking with me: “What do these things mean, my lord?” <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So the angel who was speaking with me asked: “Do you not know what these things mean?”</p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'>I replied: “No, my lord.”</p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>He then said to me: “This is the word of Jehovah to Ze·rub′ba·bel: ‘“Not by a military force, nor by power,<a class='mr'></a> but by my spirit,”<a class='mr'></a> says Jehovah of armies. <span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Who are you, O great mountain? Before Ze·rub′ba·bel<a class='mr'></a> you will become a level land.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> And he will bring out the top stone<a class='fn'></a> amid shouts of: “How wonderful! How wonderful!”’”</p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>The word of Jehovah again came to me, saying: <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>“The hands of Ze·rub′ba·bel have laid the foundation of this house,<a class='mr'></a> and his own hands will finish it.<a class='mr'></a> And you will have to know that Jehovah of armies has sent me to you. <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For who has despised the day of small beginnings?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> For they will rejoice and see the plumb line<a class='fn'></a> in the hand of Ze·rub′ba·bel. These seven are the eyes of Jehovah, which are roving about in all the earth.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Then I asked him: “What is the meaning of these two olive trees on the right and on the left of the lampstand?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>I asked him a second time: “What is the meaning of the two bunches of twigs<a class='fn'></a> of the olive trees that are pouring out the golden liquid through the two golden tubes?”</p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>So he asked me: “Do you not know what these things mean?”</p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'>I replied: “No, my lord.”</p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>He said: “These are the two anointed ones who are standing alongside the Lord of the whole earth.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dp'><a>5 </a></span>Again I looked up, and I saw a flying scroll. <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He asked me: “What do you see?”</p></div><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sb'>I replied: “I see a flying scroll, which is 20 cubits<a class='fn'></a> long and 10 cubits wide.”</p></div><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then he said to me: “This is the curse that is going out over the face of all the earth, because everyone who steals,<a class='mr'></a> as written on its one side, has gone unpunished; and everyone who makes a sworn oath,<a class='mr'></a> as written on its other side, has gone unpunished. <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>‘I have sent it out,’ declares Jehovah of armies, ‘and it will enter into the house of the thief and into the house of the one who makes a false oath in my name; and it will remain inside that house and consume it and its timbers and its stones.’”</p></div><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then the angel who was speaking with me came forward and said to me: “Look up, please, and see what is going out.”</p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So I asked: “What is it?”</p></div><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sb'>He replied: “This is the e′phah container<a class='fn'></a> that is going out.” He continued: “This is their appearance in all the earth.” <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>And I saw that the round lid of lead was lifted up, and there was a woman sitting inside the container. <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So he said: “This is Wickedness.” Then he threw her back into the e′phah container, after which he thrust the lead weight over its mouth.</p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then I looked up and saw two women coming forward, and they were soaring in the wind. They had wings like the wings of a stork. And they lifted up the container between the earth and heaven. <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So I asked the angel who was speaking with me: “Where are they taking the e′phah container?”</p></div><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>He replied: “To the land of Shi′nar<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> to build her a house; and when it is prepared, she will be deposited there in her proper place.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then I looked up again and saw four chariots coming from between two mountains, and the mountains were of copper. <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The first chariot had red horses, and the second chariot, black horses.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>The third chariot had white horses, and the fourth chariot, speckled and dappled horses.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>I asked the angel who was speaking with me: “What are these, my lord?”</p></div><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>The angel answered me: “These are the four spirits<a class='mr'></a> of the heavens that are going out after having taken their station before the Lord of the whole earth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The one<a class='fn'></a> with the black horses is going out to the land of the north;<a class='mr'></a> the white ones are going out beyond the sea; and the speckled ones are going out to the land of the south. <span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>And the dappled ones were eager to go out to walk about through the earth.” Then he said: “Go, walk about through the earth.” And they began walking about through the earth.</p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>He then called out to me and said: “See, those going out to the land of the north have caused the spirit of Jehovah to rest in the land of the north.”</p></div><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The word of Jehovah again came to me, saying: <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>“Take from Hel′dai, To·bi′jah, and Je·da′iah what they brought from the people in exile; and on that day, you must go to the house of Jo·si′ah the son of Zeph·a·ni′ah along with these who have come from Babylon. <span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>You should take silver and gold and make a crown<a class='fn'></a> and put it on the head of Joshua<a class='mr'></a> son of Je·hoz′a·dak, the high priest. <span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>And say to him,</p><p class='sb'><span class='br'></span>“‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “Here is the man whose name is Sprout.<a class='mr'></a> He will sprout from his own place, and he will build the temple of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>He is the one who will build the temple of Jehovah, and he is the one who will assume the majesty. He will sit down on his throne and rule, and he will also be a priest on his throne,<a class='mr'></a> and there will be a peaceable agreement between the two.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>And the crown<a class='fn'></a> will serve as a memorial<a class='fn'></a> for He′lem, To·bi′jah, Je·da′iah,<a class='mr'></a> and Hen the son of Zeph·a·ni′ah, in the temple of Jehovah. <span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>And those who are far away will come and take part in building the temple of Jehovah.” And you will have to know that Jehovah of armies has sent me to you. And it will occur—if you do not fail to listen to the voice of Jehovah your God.’”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>And in the fourth year of King Da·ri′us, the word of Jehovah came to Zech·a·ri′ah<a class='mr'></a> on the fourth day of the ninth month, that is, the month of Chis′lev.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The people of Beth′el sent Shar·e′zer and Re′gem-mel′ech and his men to beg for the favor<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah, <span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>saying to the priests of the house<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah of armies and to the prophets: “Should I weep in the fifth month<a class='mr'></a> and abstain from food, as I have done for so many years?”</p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>The word of Jehovah of armies again came to me, saying: <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>“Say to all the people of the land and to the priests, ‘When you fasted and wailed in the fifth month and in the seventh month<a class='mr'></a> for 70 years,<a class='mr'></a> did you really fast for me? <span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>And when you would eat and drink, were you not eating for yourselves and drinking for yourselves? <span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Should you not obey the words that Jehovah proclaimed through the former prophets,<a class='mr'></a> while Jerusalem and her surrounding cities were inhabited and at peace, and while the Neg′eb and the She·phe′lah were inhabited?’”</p></div><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>The word of Jehovah again came to Zech·a·ri′ah, saying: <span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Judge with true justice,<a class='mr'></a> and deal with one another in loyal love<a class='mr'></a> and mercy. <span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Do not defraud the widow or the fatherless child,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> the foreigner<a class='mr'></a> or the poor;<a class='mr'></a> and do not scheme evil against one another in your hearts.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But they kept refusing to pay attention,<a class='mr'></a> and they stubbornly turned their backs,<a class='mr'></a> and they stopped up their ears so as not to hear.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>They made their heart like a diamond<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and would not obey the law<a class='fn'></a> and the words that Jehovah of armies sent by his spirit through the former prophets.<a class='mr'></a> So there came great indignation from Jehovah of armies.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>“‘Just as they did not listen when I<a class='fn'></a> called,<a class='mr'></a> so I would not listen when they called,’<a class='mr'></a> says Jehovah of armies. <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>‘And I scattered them with a storm wind throughout all the nations that they had not known,<a class='mr'></a> and the land was left desolate behind them, with no one passing through or returning;<a class='mr'></a> for they turned the desirable land into an object of horror.’”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dp'><a>8 </a></span>The word of Jehovah of armies again came, saying: <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘I will be zealous for Zion with a great zeal,<a class='mr'></a> and with great wrath I will be zealous for her.’”</p></div><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah says, ‘I will return to Zion<a class='mr'></a> and reside in Jerusalem;<a class='mr'></a> and Jerusalem will be called the city of truth,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and the mountain of Jehovah of armies, the holy mountain.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Old men and women will again sit in the public squares of Jerusalem, each with his staff in his hand because of his great age.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>And the public squares of the city will be filled with boys and girls playing there.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Although it may seem too difficult to the remaining ones of this people in those days, should it seem too difficult also to me?’ declares Jehovah of armies.”</p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Here I am saving my people from the lands of the east and the west.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>And I will bring them in, and they will reside in Jerusalem;<a class='mr'></a> and they will become my people, and I will become their God<a class='mr'></a> in truth<a class='fn'></a> and in righteousness.’”</p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Let your hands be strong,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> you who now hear these words from the mouth of the prophets,<a class='mr'></a> the same words that were spoken on the day the foundation of the house of Jehovah of armies was laid for the temple to be built. <span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For before that time, there were no wages being paid either for man or for beast;<a class='mr'></a> and it was not safe to come and go because of the adversary, for I turned all men one against another.’</p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>“‘But now I will not deal with the remaining ones of this people as in the former days,’<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah of armies. <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>‘For the seed of peace will be sown; the vine will produce its fruit and the earth its yield,<a class='mr'></a> and the heavens will give their dew; and I will cause the remaining ones of this people to inherit all these things.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>And just as you became an object of cursing among the nations,<a class='mr'></a> O house of Judah and house of Israel, so I will save you, and you will become a blessing.<a class='mr'></a> Do not be afraid!<a class='mr'></a> Let your hands be strong.’<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>“For this is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘“Just as I had determined to bring calamity on you because your forefathers made me indignant,” says Jehovah of armies, “and I felt no regret,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>so at this time I have determined to do good to Jerusalem and to the house of Judah.<a class='mr'></a> Do not be afraid!”’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>“‘These are the things you should do: Speak the truth with one another,<a class='mr'></a> and the judgments in your gates must promote truth and peace.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Do not scheme calamity against one another in your hearts,<a class='mr'></a> and do not love any false oath;<a class='mr'></a> for these are all things that I hate,’<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah.”</p></div><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>The word of Jehovah of armies again came to me, saying: <span id='dcv_8_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘The fast of the fourth month,<a class='mr'></a> the fast of the fifth month,<a class='mr'></a> the fast of the seventh month,<a class='mr'></a> and the fast of the tenth month<a class='mr'></a> will be occasions for exultation and joy for the house of Judah—festivals of rejoicing.<a class='mr'></a> So love truth and peace.’</p></div><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘It will yet come to pass that peoples and the inhabitants of many cities will come; <span id='dcv_8_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>and the inhabitants of one city will go to those of another and say: “Let us earnestly go to beg for the favor<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah and to seek Jehovah of armies. I am also going.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>And many peoples and mighty nations will come to seek Jehovah of armies in Jerusalem<a class='mr'></a> and to beg for the favor<a class='fn'></a> of Jehovah.’</p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘In those days ten men out of all the languages of the nations<a class='mr'></a> will take hold, yes, they will take firm hold of the robe<a class='fn'></a> of a Jew,<a class='fn'></a> saying: “We want to go with you,<a class='mr'></a> for we have heard that God is with you people.”’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>A pronouncement:</p></div><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sl'>“The word of Jehovah is against the land of Ha′drach,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And Damascus is its target<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>—For Jehovah’s eye is on mankind<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And on all the tribes of Israel—</p><p class='sl'><span class='br'></span> <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>And against Ha′math,<a class='mr'></a> which borders on her,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And against Tyre<a class='mr'></a> and Si′don,<a class='mr'></a> for they are so wise.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Tyre built herself a rampart.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sz'>She piled up silver like dust</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And gold like the dirt of the streets.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Look! Jehovah will take away her possessions,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And he will strike down her army into the sea;<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And she will be consumed in the fire.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Ash′ke·lon will see it and be afraid;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Gaz′a will feel great anguish,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Also Ek′ron, because her hope is put to shame.</p></div><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sz'>A king will perish from Gaz′a,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And Ash′ke·lon will not be inhabited.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>An illegitimate son will settle in Ash′dod,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will do away with the pride of the Phi·lis′tine.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>I will remove the bloodstained things from his mouth</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the disgusting things from between his teeth,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And he will be left remaining for our God;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And he will become like a sheikh<a class='fn'></a> in Judah,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And Ek′ron like the Jeb′u·site.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>I will encamp as a guard<a class='fn'></a> for my house,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>So that there will be no one passing through and no one returning;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And no taskmaster<a class='fn'></a> will pass through again,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For now I have seen it<a class='fn'></a> with my eyes.</p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion.</p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sz'>Shout in triumph, O daughter of Jerusalem.</p></div><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sz'>Look! Your king is coming to you.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sz'>He is righteous, bringing salvation,<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Humble<a class='mr'></a> and riding on a donkey,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>On a colt,<a class='fn'></a> the foal of a female donkey.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p82' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>I will take away the war chariot from E′phra·im</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the horse from Jerusalem.</p></div><div id='p83' class='par'><p class='sz'>The battle bow will be taken away.</p></div><div id='p84' class='par'><p class='sz'>And he will proclaim peace to the nations;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>His rulership will be from sea to sea</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And from the River<a class='fn'></a> to the ends of the earth.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p85' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>As for you, O woman, by the blood of your covenant,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>I will send your prisoners out of the waterless pit.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p86' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Return to the stronghold, you prisoners with hope.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p87' class='par'><p class='sz'>Today I am telling you,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>‘I will repay to you, O woman, a double portion.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p88' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>For I will bend<a class='fn'></a> Judah as my bow.</p></div><div id='p89' class='par'><p class='sz'>The bow I will fill with E′phra·im,<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will awaken your sons, O Zion,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Against your sons, O Greece,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will make you like a warrior’s sword.’</p></div><div id='p90' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Jehovah will be seen over them,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And his arrow will go out like lightning.</p></div><div id='p91' class='par'><p class='sz'>The Sovereign Lord Jehovah will sound the horn,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And he will advance with the windstorms of the south.</p></div><div id='p92' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Jehovah of armies will defend them,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And they will devour and subdue the slingstones.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p93' class='par'><p class='sz'>They will drink and be boisterous, as if with wine;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And they will be filled like the bowl,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Like the corners of the altar.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p94' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Jehovah their God will save them in that day</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>As the flock of his people;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For they will be like the gemstones of a crown<a class='fn'></a> glittering over his soil.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p95' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>For how great his goodness is,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And how great his handsomeness is!</p></div><div id='p96' class='par'><p class='sz'>Grain will make the young men thrive,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And new wine the virgins.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p97' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dp'><a>10 </a></span>“Ask Jehovah for rain in the time of the spring rain.</p></div><div id='p98' class='par'><p class='sz'>It is Jehovah who makes the storm clouds,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Who pours rain for them,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And gives vegetation in the field to everyone.</p></div><div id='p99' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For the teraphim statues<a class='fn'></a> have spoken deception;<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the diviners have visioned a lie.</p></div><div id='p100' class='par'><p class='sz'>They speak about worthless dreams,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And in vain they try to comfort.</p></div><div id='p101' class='par'><p class='sz'>That is why they will wander like sheep.</p></div><div id='p102' class='par'><p class='sz'>They will suffer, for there is no shepherd.</p></div><div id='p103' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Against the shepherds my anger burns,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And against the oppressive leaders<a class='fn'></a> I will hold an accounting;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For Jehovah of armies has turned his attention to his flock,<a class='mr'></a> to the house of Judah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And he has made them like his majestic horse in the battle.</p></div><div id='p104' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>From him comes the keyman,<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>From him comes the supporting ruler,<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>From him comes the battle bow;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>From him goes forth every overseer,<a class='fn'></a> all of them together.</p></div><div id='p105' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And they will become like warriors,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Trampling down the mud of the streets in the battle.</p></div><div id='p106' class='par'><p class='sz'>They will wage war, for Jehovah is with them;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the riders of horses will be put to shame.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p107' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>I will make the house of Judah superior,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the house of Joseph I will save.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p108' class='par'><p class='sz'>I will restore them,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For I will show them mercy;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And they will be as though I had never cast them off;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For I am Jehovah their God, and I will answer them.</p></div><div id='p109' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Those of E′phra·im must become like a mighty warrior,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And their heart will rejoice as though from wine.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p110' class='par'><p class='sz'>Their sons will see this and rejoice;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Their heart will be joyful in Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p111' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>‘I will whistle for them and gather them together;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For I will redeem them,<a class='mr'></a> and they will become many,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And continue to be many.</p></div><div id='p112' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Though I scatter them like seed among the peoples,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>They will remember me in the distant places;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>With their sons they will revive and return.</p></div><div id='p113' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>I will bring them back from the land of Egypt</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And gather them from As·syr′i·a;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>I will bring them to the land of Gil′e·ad<a class='mr'></a> and Leb′a·non,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And there will be no more room for them.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p114' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>He must pass through the sea with distress;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And in the sea he will strike down the waves;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>All the depths of the Nile will dry up.</p></div><div id='p115' class='par'><p class='sz'>The pride of As·syr′i·a will be brought down,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the scepter of Egypt will depart.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p116' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>I will make them superior in Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And they will walk about in his name,’<a class='mr'></a> declares Jehovah.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p117' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>“Open your doors, O Leb′a·non,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>So that a fire may consume your cedars.</p></div><div id='p118' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Wail, you juniper, for the cedar has fallen;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The majestic trees have been destroyed!</p></div><div id='p119' class='par'><p class='sz'>Wail, you oaks of Ba′shan,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For the dense forest has come down!</p></div><div id='p120' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Listen! The wailing of shepherds,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For their majesty has been devastated.</p></div><div id='p121' class='par'><p class='sz'>Listen! The roaring of young lions,<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For the dense thickets along the Jordan have been destroyed.</p></div><div id='p122' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>“This is what Jehovah my God says, ‘Shepherd the flock meant for the slaughter,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>whose buyers slaughtered them<a class='mr'></a> and are not held guilty. And those who sell them<a class='mr'></a> say, “May Jehovah be praised, for I will become rich.” And their shepherds have no compassion for them.’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p123' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>“‘For I will no longer show compassion on the inhabitants of the land,’ declares Jehovah. ‘So I will cause each man to fall into the hand of his neighbor and his king; and they will crush the land, and I will not rescue them out of their hand.’”</p></div><div id='p124' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>And I began to shepherd the flock meant for slaughter,<a class='mr'></a> in your behalf, O afflicted ones of the flock. So I took two staffs, and I called one Pleasantness, and the other Union,<a class='mr'></a> and I began to shepherd the flock. <span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>And I dismissed three shepherds in one month, for I<a class='fn'></a> became impatient with them, and they<a class='fn'></a> detested me as well. <span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>And I said: “I will not keep shepherding you. Let the one who is dying die, and let the one perishing perish. As for those who are left, let them devour one another’s flesh.” <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>So I took my staff Pleasantness<a class='mr'></a> and cut it up, breaking my covenant that I had made with all the peoples. <span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So it was broken in that day, and the afflicted ones of the flock who were watching me knew that it was the word of Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p125' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then I said to them: “If it seems good to you, give me my wages; but if not, withhold them.” And they paid<a class='fn'></a> my wages, 30 pieces of silver.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p126' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then Jehovah said to me: “Throw it into the treasury—the magnificent value with which they valued me.”<a class='mr'></a> So I took the 30 pieces of silver and threw it into the treasury at the house of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p127' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then I cut up my second staff, the Union,<a class='mr'></a> breaking the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p128' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>And Jehovah said to me: “Now take the equipment of a useless shepherd.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>For I am letting a shepherd rise up in the land. He will not take care of the sheep that are perishing;<a class='mr'></a> he will not seek out the young or heal the injured<a class='mr'></a> or feed those able to stand. Instead, he devours the flesh of the fat one<a class='mr'></a> and tears off the hooves of the sheep.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p129' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Woe to my worthless shepherd,<a class='mr'></a> who is abandoning the flock!<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p130' class='par'><p class='sz'>A sword will strike his arm and his right eye.</p></div><div id='p131' class='par'><p class='sz'>His arm will wither completely,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And his right eye will go completely blind.”<a class='fn'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p132' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dp'><a>12 </a></span>A pronouncement:</p></div><div id='p133' class='par'><p class='sz'>“The word of Jehovah concerning Israel,” declares Jehovah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The One who stretched out the heavens,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Who laid the foundation of the earth,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And who formed the spirit<a class='fn'></a> of man within him.</p></div><div id='p134' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Here I am making Jerusalem a cup<a class='fn'></a> that causes all the surrounding peoples to stagger; and there will be a siege against Judah as well as against Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>In that day I will make Jerusalem a heavy<a class='fn'></a> stone to all the peoples. All those who lift it are sure to be severely injured;<a class='mr'></a> and all the nations of the earth will be gathered against her.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>In that day,” declares Jehovah, “I will strike every horse with panic and its rider with madness. I will keep my eyes on the house of Judah, but I will strike every horse of the peoples with blindness. <span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>And the sheikhs<a class='fn'></a> of Judah will say in their heart, ‘The inhabitants of Jerusalem are a strength to me by means of Jehovah of armies their God.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>In that day I will make the sheikhs of Judah like a fiery pot among wood and like a fiery torch in a row of cut grain,<a class='mr'></a> and they will consume all the surrounding peoples on the right and on the left;<a class='mr'></a> and Jerusalem will again be inhabited in her place,<a class='fn'></a> in Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p135' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>“And Jehovah will save the tents of Judah first, so that the beauty<a class='fn'></a> of the house of David and the beauty<a class='fn'></a> of the inhabitants of Jerusalem may not be too great over Judah. <span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>In that day Jehovah will be a defense around the inhabitants of Jerusalem;<a class='mr'></a> in that day the one who stumbles<a class='fn'></a> among them will be like David, and the house of David like God, like Jehovah’s angel who goes before them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And in that day I will be certain to annihilate all the nations that come against Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p136' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>“I will pour out on the house of David and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem the spirit of favor and supplication, and they will look to the one whom they pierced,<a class='mr'></a> and they will wail over him as they would wail over an only son; and they will grieve bitterly over him as they would grieve over a firstborn son. <span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>In that day the wailing in Jerusalem will be great, like the wailing at Ha·dad·rim′mon in the Plain of Me·gid′do.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>And the land will wail, each family by itself; the family of David’s house by itself, and their women by themselves; the family of Nathan’s<a class='mr'></a> house by itself, and their women by themselves; <span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>the family of Le′vi’s<a class='mr'></a> house by itself, and their women by themselves; the family of the Shim′e·ites<a class='mr'></a> by itself, and their women by themselves; <span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>and all the families that are left remaining, each family by itself, and their women by themselves.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p137' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dp'><a>13 </a></span>“In that day a well will be opened to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem for cleansing sin and impurity.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p138' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“In that day,” declares Jehovah of armies, “I will erase the names of the idols from the land,<a class='mr'></a> and they will no longer be remembered; and I will rid the land of the prophets<a class='mr'></a> and the spirit of uncleanness. <span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And if a man should prophesy again, his father and his mother who caused his birth will say to him, ‘You will not live, because you have spoken lies in the name of Jehovah.’ And his father and his mother who caused his birth will pierce him through because of his prophesying.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p139' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>“In that day each of the prophets will be ashamed of his vision when he prophesies; and they will not wear an official garment of hair<a class='mr'></a> in order to deceive. <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And he will say, ‘I am no prophet. I am a man cultivating the soil, because a man bought me when I was young.’ <span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>And if someone asks him, ‘What are these wounds between your shoulders?’<a class='fn'></a> he will answer, ‘Wounds I received in the house of my friends.’”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p140' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>“O sword, awake against my shepherd,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Against the man who is my companion,” declares Jehovah of armies.</p></div><div id='p141' class='par'><p class='sz'>“Strike the shepherd,<a class='mr'></a> and let the flock<a class='fn'></a> be scattered;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will turn my hand against those who are insignificant.”</p></div><div id='p142' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>“And in all the land,” declares Jehovah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>“Two parts in it will be cut off and perish;<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And the third part will be left remaining in it.</p></div><div id='p143' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And I will bring the third part through the fire;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will refine them as silver is refined,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And test them as gold is tested.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p144' class='par'><p class='sz'>They will call on my name,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And I will answer them.</p></div><div id='p145' class='par'><p class='sz'>I will say, ‘They are my people,’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p146' class='par'><p class='sz'>And they will say, ‘Jehovah is our God.’”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="14"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p147' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>“Look! The day is coming, a day belonging to Jehovah, when the spoil from you<a class='fn'></a> will be divided in your midst. <span id='dcv_14_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>I will gather all the nations against Jerusalem for the war; and the city will be captured and the houses plundered and the women raped. And half of the city will go into exile, but the remaining ones of the people will not be cut off from the city.</p></div><div id='p148' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>“Jehovah will go out and war against those nations<a class='mr'></a> as when he fights in the day of a battle.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>In that day his feet will stand on the Mount of Olives,<a class='mr'></a> which faces Jerusalem on the east; and the Mount of Olives will be split in half, from east<a class='fn'></a> to west,<a class='fn'></a> forming a very great valley; and half of the mountain will move to the north, and half of it to the south. <span id='dcv_14_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>You will flee to the valley of my mountains, for the valley of the mountains will extend all the way to A′zel. You will have to flee, just as you fled because of the earthquake in the days of King Uz·zi′ah of Judah.<a class='mr'></a> And Jehovah my God will come, and all the holy ones will be with him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p149' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>“In that day there will be no precious light<a class='mr'></a>—things will be congealed.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>And it will become one day that is known as belonging to Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> It will not be day, nor will it be night; and at evening time there will be light. <span id='dcv_14_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>In that day living waters<a class='mr'></a> will flow out from Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> half of them toward the eastern sea<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and half of them toward the western sea.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> It will happen in summer and in winter. <span id='dcv_14_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And Jehovah will be King over all the earth.<a class='mr'></a> In that day Jehovah will be one,<a class='mr'></a> and his name one.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p150' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>“The whole land will become like the Ar′a·bah,<a class='mr'></a> from Ge′ba<a class='mr'></a> to Rim′mon<a class='mr'></a> south of Jerusalem; and she will rise and be inhabited in her place,<a class='mr'></a> from the Gate of Benjamin<a class='mr'></a> all the way to the site of the First Gate, all the way to the Corner Gate, and from the Tower of Ha·nan′el<a class='mr'></a> all the way to the winepresses<a class='fn'></a> of the king. <span id='dcv_14_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>And people will inhabit her; and there will never again be a curse of destruction,<a class='mr'></a> and Jerusalem will be inhabited in security.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p151' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>“And this is the scourge with which Jehovah will scourge all the peoples who wage war against Jerusalem:<a class='mr'></a> Their flesh will rot away while they stand on their feet, their eyes will rot away in their sockets, and their tongues will rot away in their mouths.</p></div><div id='p152' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>“In that day confusion from Jehovah will be widespread among them; and each one will grab hold of the hand of his companion, and his hand will come against the hand of his companion.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Judah will also be involved in the war at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the surrounding nations will be gathered, gold and silver and garments in vast quantity.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p153' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>“And a scourge like that scourge will also come against the horses, the mules, the camels, the donkeys, and all the livestock that are in those camps.</p></div><div id='p154' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>“Everyone who is left remaining out of all the nations that come against Jerusalem will go up from year to year<a class='mr'></a> to bow down to<a class='fn'></a> the King, Jehovah of armies,<a class='mr'></a> and to celebrate the Festival of Booths.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But if anyone among the families of the earth does not go up to Jerusalem to bow down to the King, Jehovah of armies, no rain will fall on them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>And if the family of Egypt does not come up and does not come in, they will have no rain. Instead, they will have the scourge with which Jehovah scourges the nations that do not come up to celebrate the Festival of Booths. <span id='dcv_14_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>This will be the punishment for the sin of Egypt and the sin of all the nations that do not come up to celebrate the Festival of Booths.</p></div><div id='p155' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>“In that day the words ‘Holiness belongs to Jehovah!’<a class='mr'></a> will be written on the bells of the horses. And the cooking pots<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> in the house of Jehovah will be like the bowls<a class='mr'></a> before the altar. <span id='dcv_14_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>And every cooking pot<a class='fn'></a> in Jerusalem and in Judah will be holy and will belong to Jehovah of armies, and all those who are sacrificing will come in and use some of them for boiling. In that day there will no longer be a Ca′naan·ite<a class='fn'></a> in the house of Jehovah of armies.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
</bible>
