<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dp'><a>1 </a></span>Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through God’s will, and Timothy<a class='mr'></a> our brother, <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>to the holy ones and faithful brothers in union with Christ at Co·los′sae:</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'>May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>We always thank God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, when we pray for you, <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus and the love you have for all the holy ones <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>because of the hope that is being reserved for you in the heavens.<a class='mr'></a> You previously heard about this hope through the message of truth of the good news <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>that has come to you. Just as the good news is bearing fruit and increasing in all the world,<a class='mr'></a> so it is also doing among you from the day you heard and accurately knew the undeserved kindness of God in truth. <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>That is what you have learned from our beloved fellow slave Ep′a·phras,<a class='mr'></a> who is a faithful minister of the Christ on our behalf. <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>He also made known to us your love in a spiritual way.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>That is also why from the day we heard of it, we have never stopped praying for you<a class='mr'></a> and asking that you may be filled with the accurate knowledge<a class='mr'></a> of his will in all wisdom and spiritual comprehension,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>so as to walk worthily of Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> in order to please him fully as you go on bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in the accurate knowledge of God;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>and may you be strengthened with all power according to his glorious might<a class='mr'></a> so that you may endure fully with patience and joy, <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>as you thank the Father, who made you qualify to share in the inheritance of the holy ones<a class='mr'></a> in the light.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>He rescued us from the authority of the darkness<a class='mr'></a> and transferred us into the kingdom of his beloved Son, <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>by means of whom we have our release by ransom, the forgiveness of our sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He is the image of the invisible God,<a class='mr'></a> the firstborn of all creation;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>because by means of him all other things were created in the heavens and on the earth, the things visible and the things invisible,<a class='mr'></a> whether they are thrones or lordships or governments or authorities. All other things have been created through him<a class='mr'></a> and for him. <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Also, he is before all other things,<a class='mr'></a> and by means of him all other things were made to exist, <span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>and he is the head of the body, the congregation.<a class='mr'></a> He is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead,<a class='mr'></a> so that he might become the one who is first in all things; <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>because God was pleased to have all fullness to dwell in him,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>and through him to reconcile to himself all other things<a class='mr'></a> by making peace through the blood<a class='mr'></a> he shed on the torture stake,<a class='fn'></a> whether the things on the earth or the things in the heavens.</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Indeed, you who were once alienated and enemies because your minds were on the works that were wicked, <span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>he has now reconciled by means of that one’s fleshly body through his death, in order to present you holy and unblemished and open to no accusation before him<a class='mr'></a>— <span id='dcv_1_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>provided, of course, that you continue in the faith,<a class='mr'></a> established on the foundation<a class='mr'></a> and steadfast,<a class='mr'></a> not being shifted away from the hope of that good news that you heard and that was preached in all creation under heaven.<a class='mr'></a> Of this good news I, Paul, became a minister.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>I am now rejoicing in my sufferings for your sake,<a class='mr'></a> and I am undergoing the tribulations of the Christ that are yet lacking in my flesh in behalf of his body,<a class='mr'></a> which is the congregation.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>I became a minister of this congregation in accord with the stewardship<a class='mr'></a> from God that was given to me in your behalf to preach the word of God fully, <span id='dcv_1_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>the sacred secret<a class='mr'></a> that was hidden from the past systems of things<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and from the past generations. But now it has been revealed to his holy ones,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>to whom God has been pleased to make known among the nations the glorious riches of this sacred secret,<a class='mr'></a> which is Christ in union with you, the hope of his glory.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>He is the one we are proclaiming, admonishing everyone and teaching everyone in all wisdom, so that we may present every person complete in union with Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>To this end I am indeed working hard, exerting myself with his strength that is operating powerfully within me.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>For I want you to realize how great a struggle I am having in your behalf and in behalf of those at La·o·di·ce′a<a class='mr'></a> and in behalf of all those who have not personally seen me.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>This is so that their hearts may be comforted<a class='mr'></a> and that they may be harmoniously joined together in love<a class='mr'></a> and may have all the riches that result from the full assurance of their understanding, in order to gain an accurate knowledge of the sacred secret of God, namely, Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Carefully concealed in him are all the treasures of wisdom and of knowledge.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>I am saying this so that no one may delude you with persuasive arguments. <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Though I am absent in body, I am with you in spirit, rejoicing to see your good order<a class='mr'></a> and the firmness of your faith in Christ.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Therefore, just as you have accepted Christ Jesus the Lord, go on walking in union with him, <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>being rooted and built up in him<a class='mr'></a> and being stabilized in the faith,<a class='mr'></a> just as you were taught, and overflowing with thanksgiving.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Look out that no one takes you captive<a class='fn'></a> by means of the philosophy and empty deception<a class='mr'></a> according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ; <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>because it is in him that all the fullness of the divine quality dwells bodily.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So you have acquired a fullness by means of him, the one who is the head of all government and authority.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>By your relationship with him, you were also circumcised with a circumcision performed without hands by stripping off the fleshly body,<a class='mr'></a> by the circumcision that belongs to the Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>For you were buried with him in his baptism,<a class='mr'></a> and by your relationship with him you were also raised up<a class='mr'></a> together through your faith in the powerful work of God, who raised him up from the dead.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Furthermore, though you were dead in your trespasses and in the uncircumcised state of your flesh, God made you alive together with him.<a class='mr'></a> He kindly forgave us all our trespasses<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>and erased<a class='fn'></a> the handwritten document<a class='mr'></a> that consisted of decrees<a class='mr'></a> and was in opposition to us.<a class='mr'></a> He has taken it out of the way by nailing it to the torture stake.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He has stripped the governments and the authorities bare and has publicly exhibited them as conquered,<a class='mr'></a> leading them in a triumphal procession by means of it.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Therefore, do not let anyone judge you about what you eat and drink<a class='mr'></a> or about the observance of a festival or of the new moon<a class='mr'></a> or of a sabbath.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Those things are a shadow of the things to come,<a class='mr'></a> but the reality belongs to the Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Let no man deprive you of the prize<a class='mr'></a> who takes delight in a false humility and a form of worship of the angels, “taking his stand on”<a class='fn'></a> the things he has seen. He is actually puffed up without proper cause by his fleshly frame of mind, <span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>and he is not holding fast to the head,<a class='mr'></a> to the one through whom the whole body is supplied and harmoniously joined together by means of its joints and ligaments and made to grow with the growth that is from God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>If you died together with Christ with respect to the elementary things of the world,<a class='mr'></a> why do you live as if still part of the world by further subjecting yourselves to the decrees:<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>“Do not handle, nor taste, nor touch,” <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>referring to things that all perish with their use, according to the commands and teachings of men?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Although those things have an appearance of wisdom in a self-imposed form of worship and a false humility, a harsh treatment of the body,<a class='mr'></a> they are of no value in combating the satisfying of the flesh.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dp'><a>3 </a></span>If, however, you were raised up with the Christ,<a class='mr'></a> go on seeking the things above, where the Christ is seated at the right hand of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Keep your minds fixed on the things above,<a class='mr'></a> not on the things on the earth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>For you died, and your life has been hidden with the Christ in union with God. <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>When the Christ, our life,<a class='mr'></a> is made manifest, then you also will be made manifest with him in glory.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Deaden, therefore, your body members<a class='mr'></a> that are on the earth as respects sexual immorality,<a class='fn'></a> uncleanness, uncontrolled sexual passion,<a class='mr'></a> hurtful desire, and greediness, which is idolatry. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>On account of those things the wrath of God is coming. <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>That is how you too used to conduct yourselves<a class='fn'></a> in your former way of life.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But now you must put them all away from you: wrath, anger, badness,<a class='mr'></a> abusive speech,<a class='mr'></a> and obscene talk<a class='mr'></a> out of your mouth. <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Do not lie to one another.<a class='mr'></a> Strip off the old personality<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> with its practices, <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>and clothe yourselves with the new personality,<a class='mr'></a> which through accurate knowledge is being made new according to the image of the One who created it,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, foreigner, Scyth′i·an,<a class='fn'></a> slave, or freeman; but Christ is all things and in all.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Accordingly, as God’s chosen ones,<a class='mr'></a> holy and loved, clothe yourselves with the tender affections of compassion,<a class='mr'></a> kindness, humility,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> mildness,<a class='mr'></a> and patience.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely<a class='mr'></a> even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another.<a class='mr'></a> Just as Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> freely forgave you, you must also do the same.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>But besides all these things, clothe yourselves with love,<a class='mr'></a> for it is a perfect bond of union.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Also, let the peace of the Christ rule in your hearts,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> for you were called to that peace in one body. And show yourselves thankful. <span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Let the word of the Christ reside in you richly in all wisdom. Keep on teaching and encouraging<a class='fn'></a> one another with psalms,<a class='mr'></a> praises to God, spiritual songs sung with gratitude,<a class='fn'></a> singing in your hearts to Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Whatever it is that you do in word or in deed, do everything in the name of the Lord Jesus, thanking God the Father through him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>You wives, be in subjection to your husbands,<a class='mr'></a> as it is becoming in the Lord. <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>You husbands, keep on loving your wives<a class='mr'></a> and do not be bitterly angry<a class='fn'></a> with them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>You children, be obedient to your parents in everything,<a class='mr'></a> for this is well-pleasing to the Lord. <span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>You fathers, do not be exasperating<a class='fn'></a> your children,<a class='mr'></a> so that they do not become downhearted.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>You slaves, be obedient in everything to those who are your human<a class='fn'></a> masters,<a class='mr'></a> not only when they are watching, just to please men,<a class='fn'></a> but with sincerity of heart, with fear of Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled<a class='fn'></a> as for Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and not for men, <span id='dcv_3_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>for you know that it is from Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> you will receive the inheritance as a reward.<a class='mr'></a> Slave for the Master, Christ. <span id='dcv_3_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Certainly the one who does wrong will be repaid for the wrong he has done,<a class='mr'></a> and there is no partiality.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dp'><a>4 </a></span>You masters, treat your slaves in a righteous and fair way, knowing that you also have a Master in heaven.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Persevere in prayer,<a class='mr'></a> remaining awake in it with thanksgiving.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>At the same time, pray also for us,<a class='mr'></a> that God may open a door for the word so that we can declare the sacred secret about the Christ, for which I am in prison bonds,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>and that I may proclaim it as clearly as I ought to.</p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Go on walking in wisdom toward those on the outside, making the best use of your time.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Let your words always be gracious, seasoned with salt,<a class='mr'></a> so that you will know how you should answer each person.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Tych′i·cus,<a class='mr'></a> my beloved brother and faithful minister and fellow slave in the Lord, will tell you all the news about me. <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>I am sending him to you so that you will know how we are and that he may comfort your hearts. <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He is coming along with O·nes′i·mus,<a class='mr'></a> my faithful and beloved brother, who is from among you; they will tell you all the things happening here.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Ar·is·tar′chus,<a class='mr'></a> my fellow captive, sends you his greetings, and so does Mark,<a class='mr'></a> the cousin of Bar′na·bas (concerning whom you received instructions to welcome him<a class='mr'></a> if he comes to you), <span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of those circumcised. Only these are my fellow workers for the Kingdom of God, and they have become a source of great comfort<a class='fn'></a> to me. <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Ep′a·phras,<a class='mr'></a> a slave of Christ Jesus who is from among you, sends you his greetings. He is always exerting himself in your behalf in his prayers, so that you may finally stand complete and with firm conviction in all the will of God. <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>For I bear him witness that he makes great efforts in your behalf and in behalf of those in La·o·di·ce′a and Hi·e·rap′o·lis.</p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Luke,<a class='mr'></a> the beloved physician, sends you his greetings, and so does De′mas.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Give my greetings to the brothers in La·o·di·ce′a and to Nym′pha and to the congregation at her house.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And when this letter has been read among you, arrange for it also to be read<a class='mr'></a> in the congregation of the La·o·di·ce′ans and for you also to read the one from La·o·di·ce′a. <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Also, tell Ar·chip′pus:<a class='mr'></a> “Pay attention to the ministry that you accepted in the Lord, in order to fulfill it.”</p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand.<a class='mr'></a> Keep my prison bonds<a class='mr'></a> in mind. The undeserved kindness be with you.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>
