<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>The older man<a class='fn'></a> to Ga′ius, the beloved, whom I truly love.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Beloved one, I pray that in all things you continue to prosper and enjoy good health, just as you are<a class='fn'></a> now prospering. <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For I rejoiced very much when brothers came and bore witness about the truth you hold, as you go on walking in the truth.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>No greater joy<a class='fn'></a> do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Beloved one, you show your faithfulness in what you do for the brothers, even though they are strangers to you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>They have given a witness about your love before the congregation. Please send them on their way in a manner worthy of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>For it was in behalf of his name that they went out, not taking anything<a class='mr'></a> from the people of the nations. <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>So we are under obligation to show hospitality to such ones,<a class='mr'></a> so that we may become fellow workers in the truth.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>I wrote something to the congregation, but Di·ot′re·phes, who likes to have the first place among them,<a class='mr'></a> does not accept anything from us with respect.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>That is why if I come, I will call attention to the works he is doing in spreading malicious talk about us.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> Not being content with this, he refuses to welcome the brothers<a class='mr'></a> with respect; and those who want to welcome them, he tries to hinder and to throw out of the congregation.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Beloved one, do not imitate what is bad, but imitate what is good.<a class='mr'></a> The one who does good originates with God.<a class='mr'></a> The one who does bad has not seen God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>De·me′tri·us has been well-reported-on by them all and by the truth itself. In fact, we too are bearing witness about him, and you know that the witness we give is true.</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>I had many things to write you, but I do not wish to go on writing you with pen and ink. <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>However, I am hoping to see you soon, and we will speak face-to-face.</p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'>May you have peace.</p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'>The friends send you their greetings. Give my greetings to the friends by name.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>
