<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><bible><text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>Paul, called to be an apostle<a class='mr'></a> of Christ Jesus by God’s will, and Sos′the·nes our brother, <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>to the congregation of God that is in Corinth,<a class='mr'></a> to you who have been sanctified in union with Christ Jesus,<a class='mr'></a> called to be holy ones, together with all those everywhere who are calling on the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,<a class='mr'></a> their Lord and ours:</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>I always thank my God for you in view of the undeserved kindness of God given to you in Christ Jesus; <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>because in everything you have been enriched in him, in full ability to speak and in full knowledge,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>just as the witness about the Christ<a class='mr'></a> has been made firm among you, <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>so that you do not lack in any gift at all, while you are eagerly waiting for the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>He will also make you firm to the end so that you may be open to no accusation in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>God is faithful,<a class='mr'></a> by whom you were called into fellowship<a class='fn'></a> with his Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.</p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now I urge you, brothers, through the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you should all speak in agreement and that there should be no divisions among you,<a class='mr'></a> but that you may be completely united in the same mind and in the same line of thought.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For some from the house of Chlo′e have informed me regarding you, my brothers, that there are dissensions among you. <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>What I mean is this, that each one of you says: “I belong to Paul,” “But I to A·pol′los,”<a class='mr'></a> “But I to Ce′phas,”<a class='fn'></a> “But I to Christ.” <span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Is the Christ divided? Paul was not executed on the stake for you, was he? Or were you baptized in the name of Paul? <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>I thank God that I baptized none of you except Cris′pus<a class='mr'></a> and Ga′ius,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>so that no one may say that you were baptized in my name. <span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Yes, I also baptized the household of Steph′a·nas.<a class='mr'></a> As for the rest, I do not know whether I baptized anyone else. <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>For Christ sent me, not to baptize, but to declare the good news;<a class='mr'></a> and not with wisdom of speech,<a class='fn'></a> so that the torture stake<a class='fn'></a> of the Christ should not be made useless.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>For the speech about the torture stake<a class='fn'></a> is foolishness to those who are perishing,<a class='mr'></a> but to us who are being saved, it is God’s power.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For it is written: “I will make the wisdom of the wise men perish, and the intelligence of the intellectuals I will reject.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Where is the wise man? Where is the scribe?<a class='fn'></a> Where is the debater of this system of things?<a class='fn'></a> Has not God made the wisdom of the world foolish? <span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>For since, in the wisdom of God, the world did not get to know God<a class='mr'></a> through its wisdom,<a class='mr'></a> God was pleased through the foolishness<a class='mr'></a> of what is preached to save those believing.</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>For the Jews ask for signs<a class='mr'></a> and the Greeks look for wisdom; <span id='dcv_1_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>but we preach Christ executed on the stake, to the Jews a cause for stumbling but to the nations foolishness.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>However, to those who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Because a foolish thing of God is wiser than men, and a weak thing of God is stronger than men.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>For you see his calling of you, brothers, that there are not many wise in a fleshly way,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> not many powerful, not many of noble birth,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>but God chose the foolish things of the world to put the wise men to shame; and God chose the weak things of the world to put the strong things to shame;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>and God chose the insignificant things of the world and the things looked down on, the things that are not, to bring to nothing the things that are,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>so that no one<a class='fn'></a> might boast in the sight of God. <span id='dcv_1_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>But it is due to him that you are in union with Christ Jesus, who has become to us wisdom from God, also righteousness<a class='mr'></a> and sanctification<a class='mr'></a> and release by ransom,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>so that it may be just as it is written: “The one who boasts, let him boast in Jehovah.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So when I came to you, brothers, I did not come with extravagant speech<a class='mr'></a> or wisdom declaring the sacred secret<a class='mr'></a> of God to you. <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For I decided not to know anything among you except Jesus Christ, and him executed on the stake.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And I came to you in weakness and in fear and with much trembling; <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>and my speech and what I preached were not with persuasive words of wisdom but with a demonstration of spirit and power,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>so that your faith might be, not in men’s wisdom, but in God’s power.</p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Now we speak wisdom among those who are mature,<a class='mr'></a> but not the wisdom of this system of things<a class='fn'></a> nor that of the rulers of this system of things, who are to come to nothing.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>But we speak God’s wisdom in a sacred secret,<a class='mr'></a> the hidden wisdom, which God foreordained before the systems of things for our glory. <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>It is this wisdom that none of the rulers of this system of things<a class='fn'></a> came to know,<a class='mr'></a> for if they had known it, they would not have executed<a class='fn'></a> the glorious Lord. <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But just as it is written: “Eye has not seen and ear has not heard, nor have there been conceived in the heart of man the things that God has prepared for those who love him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For it is to us God has revealed them<a class='mr'></a> through his spirit,<a class='mr'></a> for the spirit searches into all things, even the deep things of God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For who among men knows the things of a man except the man’s spirit within him? So, too, no one has come to know the things of God except the spirit of God. <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now we received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit that is from God,<a class='mr'></a> so that we might know the things that have been kindly given us by God. <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>These things we also speak, not with words taught by human wisdom,<a class='mr'></a> but with those taught by the spirit,<a class='mr'></a> as we explain<a class='fn'></a> spiritual matters with spiritual words.</p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>But a physical man does not accept<a class='fn'></a> the things of the spirit of God, for they are foolishness to him; and he cannot get to know them, because they are examined spiritually. <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>However, the spiritual man examines all things,<a class='mr'></a> but he himself is not examined by any man. <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>For “who has come to know the mind of Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a> so that he may instruct him?”<a class='mr'></a> But we do have the mind of Christ.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dp'><a>3 </a></span>So, brothers, I was not able to speak to you as to spiritual men,<a class='mr'></a> but as to fleshly men, as to infants<a class='mr'></a> in Christ. <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>I fed you milk, not solid food, for you were not yet strong enough. In fact, neither are you strong enough now,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>for you are still fleshly.<a class='mr'></a> Since there are jealousy and strife among you, are you not fleshly<a class='mr'></a> and are you not walking as men do? <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>For when one says, “I belong to Paul,” but another says, “I to A·pol′los,”<a class='mr'></a> are you not acting like mere men?</p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>What, then, is A·pol′los? Yes, what is Paul? Ministers<a class='mr'></a> through whom you became believers, just as the Lord granted each one. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>I planted,<a class='mr'></a> A·pol′los watered,<a class='mr'></a> but God kept making it grow, <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>so that neither is the one who plants anything nor is the one who waters, but God who makes it grow.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Now the one who plants and the one who waters are one,<a class='fn'></a> but each person will receive his own reward according to his own work.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>According to the undeserved kindness of God that was given to me, I laid a foundation<a class='mr'></a> as a skilled master builder,<a class='fn'></a> but someone else is building on it. But let each one keep watching how he is building on it. <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>For no one can lay any other foundation than what is laid, which is Jesus Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now if anyone builds on the foundation gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, or straw, <span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>each one’s work will be shown for what it is,<a class='fn'></a> for the day will show it up, because it will be revealed by means of fire,<a class='mr'></a> and the fire itself will prove what sort of work each one has built. <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>If anyone’s work that he has built on it remains, he will receive a reward; <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>if anyone’s work is burned up, he will suffer loss, but he himself will be saved; yet, if so, it will be as through fire.</p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Do you not know that you yourselves are God’s temple<a class='mr'></a> and that the spirit of God dwells in you?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>If anyone destroys the temple of God, God will destroy him; for the temple of God is holy, and you are that temple.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Let no one deceive himself: If anyone among you thinks he is wise in this system of things,<a class='fn'></a> let him become a fool, so that he may become wise. <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God, for it is written: “He catches the wise in their own cunning.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>And again: “Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> knows that the reasonings of the wise men are futile.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>So let no one boast in men; for all things belong to you, <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>whether Paul or A·pol′los or Ce′phas<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> or the world or life or death or things now here or things to come, all things belong to you; <span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>in turn you belong to Christ;<a class='mr'></a> Christ, in turn, belongs to God.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>A man should regard us as attendants<a class='fn'></a> of Christ and stewards of God’s sacred secrets.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>In this regard, what is expected of stewards is that they be found faithful. <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Now to me it is of very little importance to be examined by you or by a human tribunal.<a class='fn'></a> In fact, I do not even examine myself. <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>For I am not conscious of anything against myself. But by this I am not proved righteous; the one who examines me is Jehovah.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Therefore, do not judge<a class='mr'></a> anything before the due time, until the Lord comes. He will bring the secret things of darkness to light and make known the intentions of the hearts, and then each one will receive his praise from God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Now, brothers, these things I have applied<a class='fn'></a> to myself and A·pol′los<a class='mr'></a> for your good, that through us you may learn the rule: “Do not go beyond the things that are written,” so that you may not be puffed up with pride,<a class='mr'></a> favoring one against the other. <span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>For who makes you different from another? Indeed, what do you have that you did not receive?<a class='mr'></a> If, in fact, you did receive it, why do you boast as though you did not receive it?</p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Are you already satisfied? Are you already rich? Have you begun ruling as kings<a class='mr'></a> without us? I really wish that you had begun ruling as kings, so that we also might rule with you as kings.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>For it seems to me that God has put us the apostles last on exhibition as men condemned to death,<a class='mr'></a> because we have become a theatrical spectacle to the world,<a class='mr'></a> and to angels and to men. <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>We are fools<a class='mr'></a> because of Christ, but you are discreet in Christ; we are weak, but you are strong; you are held in honor, but we in dishonor. <span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Down to this very hour we continue to hunger<a class='mr'></a> and thirst<a class='mr'></a> and to be poorly clothed<a class='fn'></a> and to be beaten<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and to be homeless <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>and to toil, working with our own hands.<a class='mr'></a> When insulted, we bless;<a class='mr'></a> when persecuted, we patiently endure;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>when slandered, we answer mildly;<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> we have become as the refuse<a class='fn'></a> of the world, the offscouring of all things, until now.</p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>I am writing these things, not to put you to shame, but to admonish you as my beloved children. <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>For though you may have 10,000 guardians<a class='fn'></a> in Christ, you certainly do not have many fathers; for in Christ Jesus, I have become your father through the good news.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>I urge you, therefore, become imitators of me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>That is why I am sending Timothy to you, because he is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord. He will remind you of my methods<a class='fn'></a> in connection with Christ Jesus,<a class='mr'></a> just as I am teaching everywhere in every congregation.</p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Some are puffed up with pride, as though I were not coming to you. <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But I will come to you shortly, if Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> wills, and I will get to know, not the speech of those who are puffed up with pride, but their power. <span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>For the Kingdom of God is a matter not of speech but of power. <span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Which do you prefer? Shall I come to you with a rod<a class='mr'></a> or with love and mildness of spirit?</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Actually sexual immorality<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> is reported among you, and such immorality<a class='fn'></a> as is not even found among the nations—of a man living with<a class='fn'></a> his father’s wife.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>And are you proud of it? Should you not rather mourn,<a class='mr'></a> so that the man who committed this deed should be taken away from your midst?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Although absent in body, I am present in spirit, and I have already judged the man who has done this, as if I were actually with you. <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>When you are gathered together in the name of our Lord Jesus, and knowing that I am with you in spirit along with the power of our Lord Jesus, <span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>you must hand such a man over to Satan<a class='mr'></a> for the destruction of the flesh, so that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Your boasting is not good. Do you not know that a little leaven ferments<a class='fn'></a> the whole batch of dough?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Clear away the old leaven so that you may be a new batch, inasmuch as you are free from ferment.<a class='fn'></a> For, indeed, Christ our Passover lamb<a class='mr'></a> has been sacrificed.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>So, then, let us keep the festival,<a class='mr'></a> not with old leaven, nor with leaven of badness and wickedness, but with unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.</p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>In my letter I wrote you to stop keeping company<a class='fn'></a> with sexually immoral people,<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>not meaning entirely with the sexually immoral people<a class='fn'></a> of this world<a class='mr'></a> or the greedy people or extortioners or idolaters. Otherwise, you would actually have to get out of the world.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But now I am writing you to stop keeping company<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> with anyone called a brother who is sexually immoral<a class='fn'></a> or a greedy person<a class='mr'></a> or an idolater or a reviler<a class='fn'></a> or a drunkard<a class='mr'></a> or an extortioner,<a class='mr'></a> not even eating with such a man. <span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>For what do I have to do with judging those outside? Do you not judge those inside, <span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>while God judges those outside?<a class='mr'></a> “Remove the wicked person from among yourselves.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Does any one of you who has a dispute with another<a class='mr'></a> dare to go to court before unrighteous men, and not before the holy ones? <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Or do you not know that the holy ones will judge the world?<a class='mr'></a> And if the world is to be judged by you, are you not competent to try very trivial matters? <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Do you not know that we will judge angels?<a class='mr'></a> Then why not matters of this life? <span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>If, then, you do have matters of this life to be tried,<a class='mr'></a> is it the men looked down on in the congregation whom you assign as judges? <span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>I am speaking to move you to shame. Is there not one wise man among you who is able to judge between his brothers? <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Instead, brother goes to court against brother, and before unbelievers at that!</p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Really, it is already a defeat for you when you have lawsuits with one another. Why not rather let yourselves be wronged?<a class='mr'></a> Why do you not rather let yourselves be defrauded? <span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Instead, you wrong and defraud, and your brothers at that!</p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom?<a class='mr'></a> Do not be misled.<a class='fn'></a> Those who are sexually immoral,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> idolaters,<a class='mr'></a> adulterers,<a class='mr'></a> men who submit to homosexual acts,<a class='mr'></a> men who practice homosexuality,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>thieves, greedy people,<a class='mr'></a> drunkards,<a class='mr'></a> revilers,<a class='fn'></a> and extortioners will not inherit God’s Kingdom.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And yet that is what some of you were. But you have been washed clean;<a class='mr'></a> you have been sanctified;<a class='mr'></a> you have been declared righteous<a class='mr'></a> in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ and with the spirit of our God.</p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>All things are lawful<a class='fn'></a> for me, but not all things are advantageous.<a class='mr'></a> All things are lawful for me, but I will not let myself be controlled<a class='fn'></a> by anything. <span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Food is for the stomach and the stomach is for food, but God will bring both of them to nothing.<a class='mr'></a> The body is not for sexual immorality<a class='fn'></a> but for the Lord,<a class='mr'></a> and the Lord is for the body. <span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But God raised up the Lord<a class='mr'></a> and will also raise us up out of death<a class='mr'></a> through his power.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Do you not know that your bodies are members of Christ?<a class='mr'></a> Should I, then, take the members of the Christ away and join them to a prostitute? By no means! <span id='dcv_6_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Do you not know that anyone who is joined to a prostitute is one body with her? For “the two,” says he, “will be one flesh.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>But whoever is joined to the Lord is one with him in spirit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Flee from sexual immorality!<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> Every other sin that a man may commit is outside his body, but whoever practices sexual immorality is sinning against his own body.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Do you not know that your body is the temple<a class='mr'></a> of the holy spirit within you, which you have from God?<a class='mr'></a> Also, you do not belong to yourselves,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>for you were bought with a price.<a class='mr'></a> By all means, glorify God<a class='mr'></a> in your body.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Now concerning the things about which you wrote, it is better for a man not to touch<a class='fn'></a> a woman; <span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>but because of the prevalence of sexual immorality,<a class='fn'></a> let each man have his own wife<a class='mr'></a> and each woman have her own husband.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Let the husband give to his wife her due, and let the wife also do likewise to her husband.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>The wife does not have authority over her own body, but her husband does; likewise, the husband does not have authority over his own body, but his wife does. <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Do not deprive each other except by mutual consent for an appointed time, so that you may devote time to prayer and may come together again, in order that Satan may not keep tempting you for your lack of self-control. <span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>However, I say this by way of concession, not as a command. <span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>But I wish all men were as I am. Nevertheless, each one has his own gift<a class='mr'></a> from God, one in this way, another in that way.</p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Now I say to those who are unmarried and to the widows that it is better for them if they remain as I am.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But if they do not have self-control, let them marry, for it is better to marry than to be inflamed with passion.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>To the married people I give instructions, not I but the Lord, that a wife should not separate from her husband.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>But if she does separate, let her remain unmarried or else be reconciled with her husband; and a husband should not leave his wife.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>But to the others I say, yes, I, not the Lord:<a class='mr'></a> If any brother has an unbelieving wife and she is agreeable to staying with him, let him not leave her; <span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>and if a woman has an unbelieving husband and he is agreeable to staying with her, let her not leave her husband. <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in relation to his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in relation to the brother; otherwise, your children would be unclean, but now they are holy. <span id='dcv_7_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>But if the unbelieving one chooses to depart,<a class='fn'></a> let him depart; a brother or a sister is not bound under such circumstances, but God has called you to peace.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>For wife, how do you know whether you will save your husband?<a class='mr'></a> Or, husband, how do you know whether you will save your wife?</p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Nevertheless, just as Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> has given each one a portion, let each one so walk as God has called him.<a class='mr'></a> And so I give this directive in all the congregations. <span id='dcv_7_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Was any man already circumcised when he was called?<a class='mr'></a> Let him not undo his circumcision. Has any man been called while uncircumcised? Let him not get circumcised.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Circumcision means nothing, and uncircumcision means nothing;<a class='mr'></a> what means something is the observing of God’s commandments.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>In whatever state each one was called, let him remain in it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Were you called when a slave? Do not let it concern you;<a class='mr'></a> but if you can become free, then seize the opportunity. <span id='dcv_7_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>For anyone who was called in the Lord when a slave is the Lord’s freedman;<a class='mr'></a> likewise anyone who was called when a freeman is a slave of Christ. <span id='dcv_7_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>You were bought with a price;<a class='mr'></a> stop becoming slaves of men. <span id='dcv_7_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>In whatever state each one was called, brothers, let him remain in it before God.</p></div><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Now concerning virgins,<a class='fn'></a> I have no command from the Lord, but I give my opinion<a class='mr'></a> as one who had mercy shown him by the Lord to be faithful. <span id='dcv_7_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Therefore, I think that it is best for a man to continue as he is in view of the present difficulty. <span id='dcv_7_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Are you bound to a wife? Stop seeking a release.<a class='mr'></a> Are you freed from a wife? Stop seeking a wife. <span id='dcv_7_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>But even if you did marry, you would commit no sin. And if a virgin married, such a person would commit no sin. However, those who do will have tribulation in their flesh. But I am trying to spare you.</p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Moreover, this I say, brothers, the time left is reduced.<a class='mr'></a> From now on, let those who have wives be as though they had none, <span id='dcv_7_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>and those who weep as those who do not weep, and those who rejoice as those who do not rejoice, and those who buy as those who do not possess, <span id='dcv_7_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>and those making use of the world as those not using it to the full; for the scene of this world is changing. <span id='dcv_7_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>Indeed, I want you to be free from anxiety. The unmarried man is anxious for the things of the Lord, how he may gain the Lord’s approval. <span id='dcv_7_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>But the married man is anxious for the things of the world,<a class='mr'></a> how he may gain the approval of his wife, <span id='dcv_7_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>and he is divided. Further, the unmarried woman, as well as the virgin, is anxious for the things of the Lord,<a class='mr'></a> that she may be holy both in her body and in her spirit. However, the married woman is anxious for the things of the world, how she may gain the approval of her husband. <span id='dcv_7_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>But I am saying this for your personal advantage, not to restrict<a class='fn'></a> you, but to move you to what is appropriate and to constant devotion to the Lord without distraction.</p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>But if anyone thinks he is behaving improperly by remaining unmarried,<a class='fn'></a> and if he is past the bloom of youth, then this is what should take place: Let him do what he wants; he does not sin. Let them marry.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>But if anyone stands settled in his heart and has no necessity, but has authority over his own will and has made the decision in his own heart to remain unmarried,<a class='fn'></a> he will do well.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>So also, whoever marries<a class='fn'></a> does well, but whoever does not marry will do better.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>A wife is bound as long as her husband is alive.<a class='mr'></a> But if her husband should fall asleep in death, she is free to be married to whomever she wants, only in the Lord.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>But in my opinion, she is happier if she remains as she is; and I certainly think I also have God’s spirit.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Now concerning food offered to idols:<a class='mr'></a> We know we all have knowledge.<a class='mr'></a> Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>If anyone thinks he knows something, he does not yet know it as he should know it. <span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But if anyone loves God, this one is known by him.</p></div><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now concerning the eating of food offered to idols, we know that an idol is nothing<a class='mr'></a> in the world and that there is no God but one.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>For even though there are so-called gods, whether in heaven or on earth,<a class='mr'></a> just as there are many “gods” and many “lords,” <span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>there is actually to us one God,<a class='mr'></a> the Father,<a class='mr'></a> from whom all things are and we for him;<a class='mr'></a> and there is one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom all things are<a class='mr'></a> and we through him.</p></div><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>However, not all have this knowledge.<a class='mr'></a> But some, because of their former association with the idol, eat food as something sacrificed to an idol,<a class='mr'></a> and their conscience, being weak, is defiled.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But food will not bring us nearer to God;<a class='mr'></a> we are no worse off if we do not eat, nor better off if we eat.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>But keep watching that your right to choose does not somehow become a stumbling block to those who are weak.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>For if anyone should see you who have knowledge having a meal in an idol temple, will not the conscience of that one who is weak be emboldened to the point of eating food offered to idols? <span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So by your knowledge the man who is weak is being ruined, your brother for whose sake Christ died.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>When you sin against your brothers in this way and wound their weak conscience,<a class='mr'></a> you are sinning against Christ. <span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>That is why if food makes my brother stumble, I will never again eat meat at all, so that I will not make my brother stumble.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dp'><a>9 </a></span>Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Have I not seen Jesus our Lord?<a class='mr'></a> Are you not my work in the Lord? <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Even if I am not an apostle to others, I most certainly am to you! For you are the seal confirming my apostleship in the Lord.</p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>My defense to those who examine me is as follows: <span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>We have the right<a class='fn'></a> to eat and drink, do we not? <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>We have the right to be accompanied by a believing wife,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> as the rest of the apostles and the Lord’s brothers<a class='mr'></a> and Ce′phas,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> do we not? <span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Or is it only Bar′na·bas<a class='mr'></a> and I who do not have the right to refrain from working for a living? <span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>What soldier ever serves at his own expense? Who plants a vineyard and does not eat of its fruit?<a class='mr'></a> Or who shepherds a flock and does not partake of some of the milk of the flock?</p></div><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Am I saying these things from a human viewpoint? Or does not the Law also say these things? <span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>For it is written in the Law of Moses: “You must not muzzle a bull when it is threshing out the grain.”<a class='mr'></a> Is it bulls that God is concerned about? <span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Or is it actually for our sakes that he says it? It was really written for our sakes, because the man who plows and the man who threshes ought to do so in the hope of receiving a share.</p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>If we have sown spiritual things among you, is it too much if we reap material support from you?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>If other men have this rightful claim over you, do we not have it much more so? Nevertheless, we have not made use of this right,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> but we are enduring all things so that we might not in any way hinder the good news about the Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Do you not know that the men performing sacred duties eat the things of the temple, and that those regularly serving at the altar receive a share from the altar?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>In this way, too, the Lord commanded for those proclaiming the good news to live by means of the good news.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>But I have not made use of a single one of these provisions.<a class='mr'></a> Indeed, I have not written these things so that this would be done for me, for it would be better to die than—no man will take away my grounds for boasting!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Now if I am declaring the good news, it is no reason for me to boast, for necessity is laid upon me. Really, woe to me if I do not declare the good news!<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>If I do this willingly, I have a reward; but even if I do it against my will, I still have a stewardship entrusted to me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>What, then, is my reward? That when I declare the good news, I may offer the good news without cost, to avoid abusing my authority<a class='fn'></a> in the good news.</p></div><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For though I am free from all people, I have made myself the slave to all, so that I may gain as many people as possible. <span id='dcv_9_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>To the Jews I became as a Jew in order to gain Jews;<a class='mr'></a> to those under law I became as under law, though I myself am not under law, in order to gain those under law.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>To those without law I became as without law, although I am not without law toward God but under law toward Christ,<a class='mr'></a> in order to gain those without law. <span id='dcv_9_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>To the weak I became weak, in order to gain the weak.<a class='mr'></a> I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some. <span id='dcv_9_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Do you not know that the runners in a race all run, but only one receives the prize? Run in such a way that you may win it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Now everyone competing in a contest<a class='fn'></a> exercises self-control in all things. Of course, they do it to receive a crown that can perish,<a class='mr'></a> but we, one that does not perish.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Therefore, the way I am running is not aimlessly;<a class='mr'></a> the way I am aiming my blows is so as not to be striking the air; <span id='dcv_9_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>but I pummel<a class='fn'></a> my body<a class='mr'></a> and lead it as a slave, so that after I have preached to others, I myself should not become disapproved<a class='fn'></a> somehow.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now I want you to know, brothers, that our forefathers were all under the cloud<a class='mr'></a> and all passed through the sea<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>and all got baptized into Moses by means of the cloud and of the sea, <span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>and all ate the same spiritual food<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>and all drank the same spiritual drink.<a class='mr'></a> For they used to drink from the spiritual rock that followed them, and that rock meant<a class='fn'></a> the Christ.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Nevertheless, God was not pleased with most of them, for they were struck down in the wilderness.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Now these things became examples for us, in order for us not to desire injurious things, as they desired them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Neither become idolaters, as some of them did; just as it is written: “The people sat down to eat and drink. Then they got up to have a good time.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Neither let us practice sexual immorality,<a class='fn'></a> as some of them committed sexual immorality,<a class='fn'></a> only to fall, 23,000 of them in one day.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Neither let us put Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> to the test,<a class='mr'></a> as some of them put him to the test, only to perish by the serpents.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Neither be murmurers, as some of them murmured,<a class='mr'></a> only to perish by the destroyer.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Now these things happened to them as examples, and they were written for a warning to us<a class='mr'></a> upon whom the ends of the systems of things have come.</p></div><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>So let the one who thinks he is standing beware that he does not fall.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>No temptation has come upon you except what is common to men.<a class='mr'></a> But God is faithful, and he will not let you be tempted beyond what you can bear,<a class='mr'></a> but along with the temptation he will also make the way out so that you may be able to endure it.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Therefore, my beloved ones, flee from idolatry.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>I speak as to men with discernment; judge for yourselves what I say. <span id='dcv_10_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>The cup of blessing that we bless, is it not a sharing in the blood of the Christ?<a class='mr'></a> The loaf that we break, is it not a sharing in the body of the Christ?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Because there is one loaf, we, although many, are one body,<a class='mr'></a> for we are all partaking of that one loaf.</p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Look at Israel in the fleshly sense: Are not those who eat the sacrifices sharers with the altar?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>What, then, am I saying? That what is sacrificed to an idol is anything, or that an idol is anything? <span id='dcv_10_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>No; but I say that what the nations sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God;<a class='mr'></a> and I do not want you to become sharers with the demons.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>You cannot be drinking the cup of Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> and the cup of demons; you cannot be partaking of “the table of Jehovah”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and the table of demons. <span id='dcv_10_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Or ‘are we inciting Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> to jealousy’?<a class='mr'></a> We are not stronger than he is, are we?</p></div><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>All things are lawful,<a class='fn'></a> but not all things are advantageous. All things are lawful, but not all things build up.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Let each one keep seeking, not his own advantage, but that of the other person.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>Eat whatever is sold in a meat market, making no inquiry because of your conscience, <span id='dcv_10_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>for “to Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> belong the earth and everything in it.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>If an unbeliever invites you and you want to go, eat whatever is set before you, making no inquiry on account of your conscience. <span id='dcv_10_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>But if anyone says to you, “This is something offered in sacrifice,” do not eat because of the one who told you and because of conscience.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>I do not mean your own conscience, but that of the other person. For why should my freedom be judged by another person’s conscience?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>If I am partaking with thanks, why am I to be spoken of abusively over that for which I give thanks?<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>Therefore, whether you are eating or drinking or doing anything else, do all things for God’s glory.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>Keep from becoming causes for stumbling to Jews as well as Greeks and to the congregation of God,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>just as I am trying to please all people in all things, not seeking my own advantage,<a class='mr'></a> but that of the many, so that they may be saved.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Become imitators of me, just as I am of Christ.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>I commend you because in all things you remember me and you are holding fast the traditions just as I handed them on to you. <span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But I want you to know that the head of every man is the Christ;<a class='mr'></a> in turn, the head of a woman is the man;<a class='mr'></a> in turn, the head of the Christ is God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Every man who prays or prophesies with something on his head shames his head; <span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>but every woman who prays or prophesies<a class='mr'></a> with her head uncovered shames her head, for it is one and the same as if she were a woman with a shaved head. <span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>For if a woman does not cover herself, she should have her hair cut off; but if it is disgraceful for a woman to have her hair cut off or shaved, she should be covered.</p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>For a man should not have his head covered, as he is God’s image<a class='mr'></a> and glory, but the woman is man’s glory. <span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>For man did not come from woman, but woman came from man.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>And what is more, man was not created for the sake of the woman, but woman for the sake of the man.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>That is why the woman ought to have a sign of authority on her head, because of the angels.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Besides, in connection with the Lord, neither is woman separate from man nor is man separate from woman. <span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>For just as the woman is from the man,<a class='mr'></a> so also the man is through the woman; but all things are from God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Judge for yourselves: Is it fitting for a woman to pray to God with her head uncovered? <span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Does not nature itself teach you that long hair is a dishonor to a man, <span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>but if a woman has long hair, it is a glory to her? For her hair is given to her instead of a covering. <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>However, if anyone wants to argue in favor of some other custom, we have no other, nor do the congregations of God.</p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But while giving these instructions, I do not commend you, because it is, not for the better, but for the worse that you meet together. <span id='dcv_11_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>For first of all, I hear that when you come together in a congregation, divisions exist among you; and to an extent I believe it. <span id='dcv_11_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>For there will certainly also be sects among you,<a class='mr'></a> so that those of you who are approved may also become evident.</p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>When you come together in one place, it is not really to eat the Lord’s Evening Meal.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>For when you eat it, each one takes his own evening meal beforehand, so that one is hungry but another is intoxicated. <span id='dcv_11_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Do you not have houses for eating and drinking? Or do you despise the congregation of God and make those who have nothing feel ashamed? What can I say to you? Should I commend you? In this I do not commend you.</p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>For I received from the Lord what I also handed on to you, that the Lord Jesus on the night<a class='mr'></a> on which he was going to be betrayed took a loaf, <span id='dcv_11_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>and after giving thanks, he broke it and said: “This means my body,<a class='mr'></a> which is in your behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>He did the same with the cup<a class='mr'></a> also, after they had the evening meal, saying: “This cup means the new covenant<a class='mr'></a> by virtue of my blood.<a class='mr'></a> Keep doing this, whenever you drink it, in remembrance of me.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>For whenever you eat this loaf and drink this cup, you keep proclaiming the death of the Lord, until he comes.</p></div><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Therefore, whoever eats the loaf or drinks the cup of the Lord unworthily will be guilty respecting the body and the blood of the Lord. <span id='dcv_11_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>First let a man approve himself after scrutiny,<a class='mr'></a> and only then let him eat of the loaf and drink of the cup. <span id='dcv_11_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>For the one who eats and drinks without discerning the body eats and drinks judgment against himself. <span id='dcv_11_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>That is why many among you are weak and sick, and quite a few are sleeping in death.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>But if we would discern what we ourselves are, we would not be judged. <span id='dcv_11_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>However, when we are judged, we are disciplined by Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> so that we may not become condemned with the world.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>Consequently, my brothers, when you come together to eat it, wait for one another. <span id='dcv_11_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>If anyone is hungry, let him eat at home, so that when you come together it is not for judgment.<a class='mr'></a> But as for the remaining matters, I will put them in order when I get there.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now concerning the spiritual gifts,<a class='mr'></a> brothers, I do not want you to be uninformed. <span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>You know that when you were people of the nations,<a class='fn'></a> you were influenced and led astray to those voiceless idols,<a class='mr'></a> following wherever they might lead you. <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Now I would have you know that nobody when speaking by God’s spirit says: “Jesus is accursed!” and nobody can say: “Jesus is Lord!” except by holy spirit.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now there are different gifts, but there is the same spirit;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>and there are different ministries,<a class='mr'></a> and yet there is the same Lord; <span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>and there are different activities,<a class='fn'></a> and yet it is the same God who performs them all in everyone.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>But the manifestation of the spirit is given to each one for a beneficial purpose.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>For to one is given speech<a class='fn'></a> of wisdom through the spirit, to another speech of knowledge according to the same spirit, <span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>to another faith<a class='mr'></a> by the same spirit, to another gifts of healing<a class='mr'></a> by that one spirit, <span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>to yet another operations of powerful works,<a class='mr'></a> to another prophesying, to another discernment of inspired expressions,<a class='mr'></a> to another different tongues,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and to another interpretation of tongues.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But all these operations are performed by the very same spirit, distributing to each one respectively just as it wills.</p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>For just as the body is one but has many members, and all the members of that body, although many, are one body,<a class='mr'></a> so too is the Christ. <span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>For by one spirit we were all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether slaves or free, and we were all made to drink one spirit.</p></div><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>For, indeed, the body is made up not of one member but of many.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>If the foot should say, “Because I am not a hand, I am no part of the body,” that does not make it no part of the body. <span id='dcv_12_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>And if the ear should say, “Because I am not an eye, I am no part of the body,” that does not make it no part of the body. <span id='dcv_12_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>If the whole body were an eye, where would the sense of hearing be? If it were all hearing, where would the sense of smell be? <span id='dcv_12_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>But now God has arranged each of the body members just as he pleased.</p></div><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>If they were all the same member, where would the body be? <span id='dcv_12_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>But now they are many members, yet one body. <span id='dcv_12_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>The eye cannot say to the hand, “I do not need you,” or again, the head cannot say to the feet, “I do not need you.” <span id='dcv_12_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>On the contrary, the members of the body that seem to be weaker are necessary, <span id='dcv_12_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>and the parts of the body that we think to be less honorable we surround with greater honor,<a class='mr'></a> so our unseemly parts are treated with greater modesty, <span id='dcv_12_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>whereas our attractive parts do not need anything. Nevertheless, God has so composed the body, giving greater honor to the part that had a lack, <span id='dcv_12_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>so that there should be no division in the body, but its members should have mutual concern for one another.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>If one member suffers, all the other members suffer with it;<a class='mr'></a> or if a member is glorified, all the other members rejoice with it.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Now you are Christ’s body,<a class='mr'></a> and each of you individually is a member.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>And God has assigned the respective ones in the congregation: first, apostles;<a class='mr'></a> second, prophets;<a class='mr'></a> third, teachers;<a class='mr'></a> then powerful works;<a class='mr'></a> then gifts of healings;<a class='mr'></a> helpful services; abilities to direct;<a class='mr'></a> different tongues.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Not all are apostles, are they? Not all are prophets, are they? Not all are teachers, are they? Not all perform powerful works, do they? <span id='dcv_12_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Not all have gifts of healings, do they? Not all speak in tongues, do they?<a class='mr'></a> Not all are interpreters,<a class='fn'></a> are they?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>But keep striving for<a class='fn'></a> the greater gifts.<a class='mr'></a> And yet I will show you a surpassing way.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>If I speak in the tongues of men and of angels but do not have love, I have become a clanging gong or a clashing cymbal. <span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>And if I have the gift of prophecy and understand all the sacred secrets and all knowledge,<a class='mr'></a> and if I have all the faith so as to move<a class='fn'></a> mountains, but do not have love, I am nothing.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>And if I give all my belongings to feed others,<a class='mr'></a> and if I hand over my body so that I may boast, but do not have love,<a class='mr'></a> I do not benefit at all.</p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Love<a class='mr'></a> is patient<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and kind.<a class='mr'></a> Love is not jealous.<a class='mr'></a> It does not brag, does not get puffed up,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>does not behave indecently,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> does not look for its own interests,<a class='mr'></a> does not become provoked.<a class='mr'></a> It does not keep account of the injury.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>It does not rejoice over unrighteousness,<a class='mr'></a> but rejoices with the truth. <span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>It bears all things,<a class='mr'></a> believes all things,<a class='mr'></a> hopes all things,<a class='mr'></a> endures all things.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Love never fails. But if there are gifts of prophecy, they will be done away with; if there are tongues,<a class='fn'></a> they will cease; if there is knowledge, it will be done away with. <span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>For we have partial knowledge<a class='mr'></a> and we prophesy partially, <span id='dcv_13_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>but when what is complete comes, what is partial will be done away with. <span id='dcv_13_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>When I was a child, I used to speak as a child, to think as a child, to reason as a child; but now that I have become a man, I have done away with the traits of a child. <span id='dcv_13_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>For now we see in hazy outline<a class='fn'></a> by means of a metal mirror, but then it will be face-to-face. At present I know partially, but then I will know accurately,<a class='fn'></a> just as I am accurately known. <span id='dcv_13_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Now, however, these three remain: faith, hope, love; but the greatest of these is love.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="14"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Pursue love, yet keep striving for<a class='fn'></a> the spiritual gifts, but preferably that you may prophesy.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For the one who speaks in a tongue speaks, not to men, but to God, for no one listens,<a class='mr'></a> but he speaks sacred secrets<a class='mr'></a> by the spirit. <span id='dcv_14_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>However, the one who prophesies builds up and encourages and consoles men by his speech. <span id='dcv_14_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>The one who speaks in a tongue builds up himself, but the one who prophesies builds up a congregation. <span id='dcv_14_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Now I would like for all of you to speak in tongues,<a class='mr'></a> but I prefer that you prophesy.<a class='mr'></a> Indeed, the one who prophesies is greater than the one who speaks in tongues, unless he interprets,<a class='fn'></a> so that the congregation may be built up. <span id='dcv_14_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But at this time, brothers, if I should come speaking to you in tongues, what good would I do you unless I spoke to you either with a revelation<a class='mr'></a> or with knowledge<a class='mr'></a> or with a prophecy or with a teaching?</p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>It is the same with the inanimate things that produce sound, whether a flute or a harp. Unless there is an interval to the tones, how can what is being played on the flute or on the harp be recognized? <span id='dcv_14_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>For if the trumpet sounds an indistinct call, who will get ready for battle? <span id='dcv_14_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>In the same way, unless you with the tongue use speech that is easily understood, how will anyone know what is being said? You will, in fact, be speaking into the air. <span id='dcv_14_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>It may be that there are many kinds of speech in the world, and yet no kind is without meaning. <span id='dcv_14_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>For if I do not understand the sense of the speech, I will be a foreigner to the one speaking, and the one speaking will be a foreigner to me. <span id='dcv_14_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>So also with you, since you eagerly desire the gifts of the spirit, seek to abound in gifts that will build up the congregation.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Therefore, let the one who speaks in a tongue pray that he may interpret.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>For if I am praying in a tongue, it is my gift of the spirit that is praying, but my mind is unproductive. <span id='dcv_14_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>What is to be done, then? I will pray with the gift of the spirit, but I will also pray with my mind. I will sing praise with the gift of the spirit, but I will also sing praise with my mind. <span id='dcv_14_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Otherwise, if you offer praise with a gift of the spirit, how will the ordinary person in your midst say “Amen” to your giving of thanks, since he does not know what you are saying? <span id='dcv_14_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>True, you are giving thanks in a fine way, but the other man is not being built up. <span id='dcv_14_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>I thank God that I speak in more tongues than all of you do. <span id='dcv_14_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Nevertheless, in a congregation I would rather speak five words with my mind,<a class='fn'></a> that I might also instruct<a class='fn'></a> others, than ten thousand words in a tongue.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Brothers, do not become young children in your understanding,<a class='mr'></a> but be young children as to badness;<a class='mr'></a> and become full-grown in your understanding.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>In the Law it is written: “‘With the tongues of foreigners and with the lips of strangers I will speak to this people, and even then they will refuse to listen to me,’ says Jehovah.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Therefore, tongues are not a sign for the believers but for the unbelievers,<a class='mr'></a> whereas prophecy is not for the unbelievers but for the believers. <span id='dcv_14_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So if the whole congregation comes together to one place and they all speak in tongues, but ordinary people or unbelievers come in, will they not say that you have lost your minds? <span id='dcv_14_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>But if you are all prophesying and an unbeliever or an ordinary person comes in, he will be reproved and closely examined by them all. <span id='dcv_14_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>The secrets of his heart then become evident, so that he will fall facedown and worship God, declaring: “God is really among you.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>What is to be done, then, brothers? When you come together, one has a psalm, another has a teaching, another has a revelation, another has a tongue, and another has an interpretation.<a class='mr'></a> Let all things take place for building up. <span id='dcv_14_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>And if someone speaks in a tongue, let it be limited to two or three at the most, and in turns, and someone must interpret.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>But if there is no interpreter,<a class='fn'></a> he must keep silent in the congregation and speak to himself and to God. <span id='dcv_14_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Let two or three prophets<a class='mr'></a> speak, and let the others discern the meaning. <span id='dcv_14_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>But if another one receives a revelation while sitting there, let the first speaker keep silent. <span id='dcv_14_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>For you can all prophesy one at a time, so that all may learn and all may be encouraged.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>And gifts of the spirit of the prophets are to be controlled by the prophets. <span id='dcv_14_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>For God is a God not of disorder but of peace.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sb'>As in all the congregations of the holy ones, <span id='dcv_14_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>let the women keep silent in the congregations, for it is not permitted for them to speak.<a class='mr'></a> Rather, let them be in subjection,<a class='mr'></a> as the Law also says. <span id='dcv_14_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>If they want to learn something, let them ask their husbands at home, for it is disgraceful for a woman to speak in the congregation.</p></div><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>Was it from you that the word of God originated, or did it reach only as far as you?</p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>If anyone thinks he is a prophet or is gifted with the spirit, he must acknowledge that the things I am writing to you are the Lord’s commandment. <span id='dcv_14_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>But if anyone disregards this, he will be disregarded.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>So, my brothers, keep striving to prophesy,<a class='mr'></a> and yet do not forbid the speaking in tongues.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>But let all things take place decently and by arrangement.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="15"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p82' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Now I remind you, brothers, of the good news that I declared to you,<a class='mr'></a> which you also accepted, and for which you have taken your stand. <span id='dcv_15_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Through it you are also being saved if you hold firmly to the good news I declared to you, unless you became believers for nothing.</p></div><div id='p83' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>For among the first things I handed on to you was what I also received, that Christ died for our sins according to the Scriptures;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>and that he was buried,<a class='mr'></a> yes, that he was raised up<a class='mr'></a> on the third day<a class='mr'></a> according to the Scriptures;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>and that he appeared to Ce′phas,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and then to the Twelve.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>After that he appeared to more than 500 brothers at one time,<a class='mr'></a> most of whom are still with us, though some have fallen asleep in death. <span id='dcv_15_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>After that he appeared to James,<a class='mr'></a> then to all the apostles.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But last of all he appeared also to me<a class='mr'></a> as if to one born prematurely.</p></div><div id='p84' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>For I am the least of the apostles, and I am not worthy of being called an apostle, because I persecuted the congregation of God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>But by God’s undeserved kindness I am what I am. And his undeserved kindness to me was not in vain, but I labored more than all of them; yet it was not I, but the undeserved kindness of God that is with me. <span id='dcv_15_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Whether, then, it is I or they, this is the way we preach, and this is the way you believed.</p></div><div id='p85' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now if it is being preached that Christ has been raised from the dead,<a class='mr'></a> how is it that some among you say there is no resurrection of the dead? <span id='dcv_15_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>If, indeed, there is no resurrection of the dead, then Christ has not been raised up. <span id='dcv_15_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>But if Christ has not been raised up, our preaching is certainly in vain, and your faith is also in vain. <span id='dcv_15_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Moreover, we are also found to be false witnesses of God,<a class='mr'></a> because we have given witness against God by saying that he raised up the Christ,<a class='mr'></a> whom he did not raise up if the dead are really not to be raised up. <span id='dcv_15_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>For if the dead are not to be raised up, neither has Christ been raised up. <span id='dcv_15_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Further, if Christ has not been raised up, your faith is useless; you remain in your sins.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then also those who have fallen asleep in death in union with Christ have perished.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>If in this life only we have hoped in Christ, we are to be pitied more than anyone.</p></div><div id='p86' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>But now Christ has been raised from the dead, the firstfruits of those who have fallen asleep in death.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>For since death came through a man,<a class='mr'></a> resurrection of the dead also comes through a man.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>For just as in Adam all are dying,<a class='mr'></a> so also in the Christ all will be made alive.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>But each one in his own proper order: Christ the firstfruits,<a class='mr'></a> afterward those who belong to the Christ during his presence.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Next, the end, when he hands over the Kingdom to his God and Father, when he has brought to nothing all government and all authority and power.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>For he must rule as king until God has put all enemies under his feet.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>And the last enemy, death, is to be brought to nothing.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>For God “subjected all things under his feet.”<a class='mr'></a> But when he says that ‘all things have been subjected,’<a class='mr'></a> it is evident that this does not include the One who subjected all things to him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>But when all things will have been subjected to him, then the Son himself will also subject himself to the One who subjected all things to him,<a class='mr'></a> that God may be all things to everyone.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p87' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Otherwise, what will they do who are being baptized for the purpose of being dead ones?<a class='mr'></a> If the dead are not to be raised up at all, why are they also being baptized for the purpose of being such? <span id='dcv_15_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>Why are we also in danger every hour?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>Daily I face death. This is as sure as my exultation over you, brothers, which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord. <span id='dcv_15_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>If like other men,<a class='fn'></a> I have fought with wild beasts at Eph′e·sus,<a class='mr'></a> of what good is it to me? If the dead are not to be raised up, “let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we are to die.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Come to your senses in a righteous way and do not practice sin, for some have no knowledge of God. I am speaking to move you to shame.</p></div><div id='p88' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>Nevertheless, someone will say: “How are the dead to be raised up? Yes, with what sort of body are they coming?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>You unreasonable person! What you sow is not made alive unless first it dies. <span id='dcv_15_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>And as for what you sow, you sow, not the body that will develop, but just a bare grain, whether of wheat or of some other kind of seed; <span id='dcv_15_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>but God gives it a body just as it has pleased him, and gives to each of the seeds its own body. <span id='dcv_15_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>Not all flesh is the same flesh, but there is one of mankind, there is another flesh of cattle, another flesh of birds, and another of fish. <span id='dcv_15_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>And there are heavenly bodies<a class='mr'></a> and earthly bodies;<a class='mr'></a> but the glory of the heavenly bodies is one sort, and that of the earthly bodies is a different sort. <span id='dcv_15_41' class='dv dx dp'><a>41 </a></span>The glory of the sun is one sort, and the glory of the moon is another,<a class='mr'></a> and the glory of the stars is another; in fact, one star differs from another star in glory.</p></div><div id='p89' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_42' class='dv dx dp'><a>42 </a></span>So it is with the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised up in incorruption.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>It is sown in dishonor; it is raised up in glory.<a class='mr'></a> It is sown in weakness; it is raised up in power.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_44' class='dv dx dp'><a>44 </a></span>It is sown a physical body; it is raised up a spiritual body. If there is a physical body, there is also a spiritual one. <span id='dcv_15_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>So it is written: “The first man Adam became a living person.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> The last Adam became a life-giving spirit.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>However, what is spiritual is not first. What is physical is first, and afterward what is spiritual. <span id='dcv_15_47' class='dv dx dp'><a>47 </a></span>The first man is from the earth and made of dust;<a class='mr'></a> the second man is from heaven.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>Like the one made of dust, so too are those made of dust; and like the heavenly one, so too are those who are heavenly.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_49' class='dv dx dp'><a>49 </a></span>And just as we have borne the image of the one made of dust,<a class='mr'></a> we will bear also the image of the heavenly one.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p90' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_50' class='dv dx dp'><a>50 </a></span>But I tell you this, brothers, that flesh and blood cannot inherit God’s Kingdom, nor does corruption inherit incorruption. <span id='dcv_15_51' class='dv dx dp'><a>51 </a></span>Look! I tell you a sacred secret: We will not all fall asleep in death, but we will all be changed,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_52' class='dv dx dp'><a>52 </a></span>in a moment, in the blink<a class='fn'></a> of an eye, during the last trumpet. For the trumpet will sound,<a class='mr'></a> and the dead will be raised up incorruptible, and we will be changed. <span id='dcv_15_53' class='dv dx dp'><a>53 </a></span>For this which is corruptible must put on incorruption,<a class='mr'></a> and this which is mortal must put on immortality.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_54' class='dv dx dp'><a>54 </a></span>But when this which is corruptible puts on incorruption and this which is mortal puts on immortality, then the saying that is written will take place: “Death is swallowed up forever.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_55' class='dv dx dp'><a>55 </a></span>“Death, where is your victory? Death, where is your sting?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_56' class='dv dx dp'><a>56 </a></span>The sting producing death is sin,<a class='mr'></a> and the power for sin is the Law.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_57' class='dv dx dp'><a>57 </a></span>But thanks to God, for he gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ!<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p91' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_58' class='dv dx dp'><a>58 </a></span>Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast,<a class='mr'></a> immovable, always having plenty to do<a class='mr'></a> in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain<a class='mr'></a> in connection with the Lord.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="16"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p92' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Now concerning the collection for the holy ones,<a class='mr'></a> you may follow the directions I gave to the congregations of Ga·la′ti·a. <span id='dcv_16_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>On the first day of every week, each of you should set something aside according to his own means, so that collections will not take place when I arrive. <span id='dcv_16_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>But when I get there, I will send the men you approve of in your letters<a class='mr'></a> to take your kind gift to Jerusalem. <span id='dcv_16_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>However, if it seems advisable for me to go there also, they will go there with me.</p></div><div id='p93' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>But I will come to you when I have gone through Mac·e·do′ni·a, for I will be going through Mac·e·do′ni·a;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>and perhaps I will stay or even spend the winter with you, so that you may accompany me partway to where I may be going. <span id='dcv_16_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>For I do not want to see you now just in passing, since I hope to spend some time with you,<a class='mr'></a> if Jehovah<a class='fn'></a> permits. <span id='dcv_16_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>But I am remaining in Eph′e·sus<a class='mr'></a> until the Festival of Pentecost, <span id='dcv_16_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>because a large door that leads to activity has been opened to me,<a class='mr'></a> but there are many opposers.</p></div><div id='p94' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now if Timothy<a class='mr'></a> arrives, make sure that he has nothing to fear while among you, for he is performing the work of Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> just as I am. <span id='dcv_16_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Therefore, let no one look down on him. Send him on his way in peace, so that he may come to me, for I am waiting for him together with the brothers.</p></div><div id='p95' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now concerning A·pol′los<a class='mr'></a> our brother, I strongly urged him to come to you with the brothers. It was not his intention to come now, but he will come when he has the opportunity.</p></div><div id='p96' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Stay awake,<a class='mr'></a> stand firm in the faith,<a class='mr'></a> carry on in a manly way,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> grow mighty.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Let everything you do be done with love.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p97' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Now I urge you, brothers: You know that the household of Steph′a·nas is the firstfruits of A·cha′ia and that they devoted themselves to ministering to the holy ones. <span id='dcv_16_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>May you also keep submitting yourselves to people like that and to all those cooperating and working hard.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>But I rejoice over the presence of Steph′a·nas<a class='mr'></a> and For·tu·na′tus and A·cha′i·cus, because they have made up for your not being here. <span id='dcv_16_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>For they have refreshed my spirit and yours. Therefore, give recognition to men of that sort.</p></div><div id='p98' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>The congregations of Asia send you their greetings. Aq′ui·la and Pris′ca together with the congregation that is in their house<a class='mr'></a> greet you heartily in the Lord. <span id='dcv_16_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>All the brothers greet you. Greet one another with a holy kiss.</p></div><div id='p99' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand.</p></div><div id='p100' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>If anyone has no affection for the Lord, let him be accursed. O our Lord, come! <span id='dcv_16_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>May the undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus be with you. <span id='dcv_16_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>May my love be with all of you in union with Christ Jesus.</p></div></div></text>
</bible>
