<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
<text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>After the death of Joshua,<a class='mr'></a> the Israelites<a class='fn'></a> inquired of Jehovah:<a class='mr'></a> “Who of us will go up first to fight against the Ca′naan·ites?” <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Jehovah replied: “Judah will go up.<a class='mr'></a> Look! I am giving<a class='fn'></a> the land into his hand.” <span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then Judah said to his brother Sim′e·on: “Come up with me into my assigned territory<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> to fight against the Ca′naan·ites. Then I will go with you into your assigned territory.” So Sim′e·on went with him.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>When Judah went up, Jehovah gave the Ca′naan·ites and the Per′iz·zites into their hands,<a class='mr'></a> and they defeated 10,000 men in Be′zek. <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>They found A·do′ni-be′zek in Be′zek, and there they fought against him and defeated the Ca′naan·ites<a class='mr'></a> and the Per′iz·zites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>When A·do′ni-be′zek fled, they chased him and caught him and cut off his thumbs and his big toes. <span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then A·do′ni-be′zek said: “There are 70 kings whose thumbs and big toes were cut off and who are picking up food under my table. Just as I have done, so God has repaid me.” After that they brought him to Jerusalem,<a class='mr'></a> and he died there.</p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Furthermore, the men of Judah fought against Jerusalem<a class='mr'></a> and captured it; they struck it with the sword and set the city on fire. <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Afterward, the men of Judah went down to fight against the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting the mountainous region and the Neg′eb and the She·phe′lah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>So Judah marched against the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in Heb′ron (the name of Heb′ron was previously Kir′i·ath-ar′ba), and they struck down She′shai, A·hi′man, and Tal′mai.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>They marched from there against the inhabitants of De′bir.<a class='mr'></a> (The name of De′bir was previously Kir′i·ath-se′pher.)<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then Ca′leb<a class='mr'></a> said: “To the man who strikes Kir′i·ath-se′pher and captures it, I will give my daughter Ach′sah as a wife.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>And Oth′ni·el<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ke′naz,<a class='mr'></a> Ca′leb’s younger brother, captured it. So he gave him his daughter Ach′sah as a wife. <span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>While she was going home, she urged him to ask her father for a field. Then she dismounted from her donkey.<a class='fn'></a> Ca′leb asked her: “What do you want?” <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>She said to him: “Please grant me a blessing, for you have given me a piece of land in the south;<a class='fn'></a> give me also Gul′loth-ma′im.”<a class='fn'></a> So Ca′leb gave her Upper Gul′loth and Lower Gul′loth.</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>And the descendants of the Ken′ite,<a class='mr'></a> Moses’ father-in-law,<a class='mr'></a> came up from the city of palm trees<a class='mr'></a> with the people of Judah to the wilderness of Judah south of A′rad.<a class='mr'></a> They went there and settled among the people.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>But Judah marched on with his brother Sim′e·on, and they attacked the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting Ze′phath and devoted it to destruction.<a class='mr'></a> So they named the city Hor′mah.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then Judah captured Gaz′a<a class='mr'></a> and its territory, Ash′ke·lon<a class='mr'></a> and its territory, and Ek′ron<a class='mr'></a> and its territory. <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Jehovah was with Judah, and they took possession of the mountainous region, but they could not drive out the inhabitants of the plain,<a class='fn'></a> because they had war chariots with iron scythes.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>They gave Heb′ron to Ca′leb, just as Moses had promised,<a class='mr'></a> and he drove out from there the three sons of A′nak.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>But the Ben′ja·min·ites did not drive out the Jeb′u·sites inhabiting Jerusalem, so the Jeb′u·sites continue dwelling with the Ben′ja·min·ites in Jerusalem down to this day.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Meantime, the house of Joseph<a class='mr'></a> went up against Beth′el, and Jehovah was with them.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>The house of Joseph was spying on Beth′el (incidentally, the name of the city was previously Luz),<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>and the spies saw a man going out of the city. So they said to him: “Show us, please, the way into the city, and we will treat you kindly.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_1_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>So the man showed them the way into the city, and they struck the city with the sword, but they let the man and all his family go free.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>The man went to the land of the Hit′tites and built a city and named it Luz, which is its name to this day.</p></div><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Ma·nas′seh did not take possession of Beth-she′an and its dependent<a class='fn'></a> towns, Ta′a·nach<a class='mr'></a> and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Dor and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Ib′le·am and its dependent towns, and the inhabitants of Me·gid′do and its dependent towns.<a class='mr'></a> The Ca′naan·ites persisted in dwelling in this land. <span id='dcv_1_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>When Israel grew stronger, they subjected the Ca′naan·ites to forced labor,<a class='mr'></a> but they did not drive them out completely.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Nor did E′phra·im drive out the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in Ge′zer. The Ca′naan·ites continued to dwell among them in Ge′zer.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Zeb′u·lun did not drive out the inhabitants of Kit′ron and the inhabitants of Na′ha·lol.<a class='mr'></a> The Ca′naan·ites continued to dwell among them and were subjected to forced labor.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>Ash′er did not drive out the inhabitants of Ac′co and the inhabitants of Si′don,<a class='mr'></a> Ah′lab, Ach′zib,<a class='mr'></a> Hel′bah, A′phik,<a class='mr'></a> and Re′hob.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>So the Ash′er·ites continued to dwell among the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting the land, because they did not drive them out.</p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>Naph′ta·li did not drive out the inhabitants of Beth-she′mesh and the inhabitants of Beth-a′nath,<a class='mr'></a> but they continued to dwell among the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting the land.<a class='mr'></a> The inhabitants of Beth-she′mesh and Beth-a′nath became forced laborers for them.</p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>The Am′or·ites confined the Dan′ites to the mountainous region, for they would not let them come down into the plain.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_35' class='dv dx dp'><a>35 </a></span>So the Am′or·ites persisted in dwelling in Mount He′res, Ai′ja·lon,<a class='mr'></a> and Sha·al′bim.<a class='mr'></a> But when the power<a class='fn'></a> of the house of Joseph increased,<a class='fn'></a> they were forced into hard labor. <span id='dcv_1_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>The territory of the Am′or·ites was from the ascent of A·krab′bim,<a class='mr'></a> from Se′la upward.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then Jehovah’s angel<a class='mr'></a> went up from Gil′gal<a class='mr'></a> to Bo′chim and said: “I brought you up out of Egypt into the land about which I swore to your forefathers.<a class='mr'></a> Furthermore, I said, ‘I will never break my covenant with you.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>For your part, you must not make a covenant with the inhabitants of this land<a class='mr'></a> and you should pull down their altars.’<a class='mr'></a> But you have not obeyed my voice.<a class='mr'></a> Why have you done this? <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>That is why I also said, ‘I will not drive them away from before you,<a class='mr'></a> and they will ensnare you,<a class='mr'></a> and their gods will lure you away.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>When Jehovah’s angel spoke these words to all the Israelites, the people began to weep loudly. <span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So they named that place Bo′chim,<a class='fn'></a> and they sacrificed there to Jehovah.</p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>When Joshua sent the people away, each of the Israelites went to his inheritance to take possession of the land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>The people continued to serve Jehovah all the days of Joshua and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua and who had seen all of Jehovah’s great deeds in behalf of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Jehovah, died at the age of 110.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So they buried him in the territory of his inheritance in Tim′nath-he′res,<a class='mr'></a> in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, north of Mount Ga′ash.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>All that generation were gathered to their ancestors,<a class='fn'></a> and another generation arose after them that did not know Jehovah or what he had done for Israel.</p></div><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>So the Israelites did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and served<a class='fn'></a> the Ba′als.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Thus they abandoned Jehovah, the God of their fathers, who brought them out of the land of Egypt.<a class='mr'></a> And they followed other gods, the gods of the peoples who were all around them,<a class='mr'></a> and they bowed down to them and offended Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>They abandoned Jehovah and served Ba′al and the Ash′to·reth images.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>At this Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, so he handed them over to plunderers who pillaged them.<a class='mr'></a> He sold them into the hand of the enemies around them,<a class='mr'></a> and they were no longer able to hold their own against their enemies.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Wherever they went, the hand of Jehovah was against them, bringing disaster on them,<a class='mr'></a> just as Jehovah had said and just as Jehovah had sworn to them,<a class='mr'></a> and they were in great distress.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>So Jehovah would raise up judges who would save them from the hand of their plunderers.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But they refused to listen even to the judges and would prostitute themselves to other gods and bow down to them. They quickly turned aside from the way in which their forefathers had walked, those who had obeyed the commandments of Jehovah.<a class='mr'></a> They failed to do that. <span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Whenever Jehovah did raise up judges for them,<a class='mr'></a> Jehovah would be with the judge and save them from the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge; for Jehovah was moved to pity<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> over their groaning caused by those who oppressed them<a class='mr'></a> and those who were treating them abusively.</p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But when the judge died, they would again act more corruptly than their fathers by following other gods, serving them and bowing down to them.<a class='mr'></a> They did not abandon their practices and their stubborn behavior. <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Finally Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and he said: “Because this nation has violated my covenant<a class='mr'></a> that I commanded their forefathers and they have disobeyed me,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>I for my part will not drive out from before them even one of the nations that Joshua left behind when he died.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>This is to test whether Israel will keep Jehovah’s way<a class='mr'></a> by walking in it as their fathers did.” <span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So Jehovah allowed these nations to remain. He did not drive them out quickly, and he did not give them into Joshua’s hand.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>These are the nations that Jehovah allowed to remain so that they could test all those of Israel who had not experienced any of the wars of Ca′naan<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>(this was so that succeeding generations of Israelites would experience war, those who had not experienced such things before): <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>the five lords of the Phi·lis′tines,<a class='mr'></a> and all the Ca′naan·ites, the Si·do′ni·ans,<a class='mr'></a> and the Hi′vites<a class='mr'></a> inhabiting Mount Leb′a·non<a class='mr'></a> from Mount Ba′al-her′mon as far as Le′bo-ha′math.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>They served as a means of testing Israel to determine whether Israel would obey Jehovah’s commandments that he had given their fathers through Moses.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So the Israelites lived among the Ca′naan·ites,<a class='mr'></a> the Hit′tites, the Am′or·ites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites, and the Jeb′u·sites. <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>They would take their daughters as wives, and their own daughters they gave to their sons, and they began serving their gods.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>So the Israelites did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and they forgot Jehovah their God and were serving the Ba′als<a class='mr'></a> and the sacred poles.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>At this Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im the king of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a.<a class='fn'></a> The Israelites served Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im for eight years. <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>When the Israelites called to Jehovah for help,<a class='mr'></a> Jehovah raised up a savior to rescue the Israelites,<a class='mr'></a> Oth′ni·el<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ke′naz, the younger brother of Ca′leb. <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>The spirit of Jehovah came upon him,<a class='mr'></a> and he became the judge of Israel. When he went out to battle, Jehovah gave Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im the king of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a<a class='fn'></a> into his hand so that he prevailed over Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im. <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>After that the land had rest<a class='fn'></a> for 40 years. Then Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz died.</p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>And once again the Israelites began doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes.<a class='mr'></a> So Jehovah let Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab<a class='mr'></a> prevail over Israel, because they did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. <span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Furthermore, he brought against them the Am′mon·ites<a class='mr'></a> and the A·mal′ek·ites.<a class='mr'></a> They attacked Israel and captured the city of palm trees.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>The Israelites served Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab for 18 years.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Then the Israelites called to Jehovah for help,<a class='mr'></a> so Jehovah raised up for them a savior,<a class='mr'></a> E′hud<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ge′ra, a Ben′ja·min·ite<a class='mr'></a> who was left-handed.<a class='mr'></a> In time the Israelites sent tribute through him to Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab. <span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Meanwhile, E′hud made for himself a two-edged sword, a cubit<a class='fn'></a> long, and he strapped it underneath his garment on his right thigh. <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>He then presented the tribute to Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab. Now Eg′lon was a very fat man.</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>When E′hud finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who had carried the tribute. <span id='dcv_3_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>But after reaching the carved images<a class='fn'></a> at Gil′gal,<a class='mr'></a> he himself went back and said: “I have a secret message for you, O king.” So the king said: “Silence!” With that all his attendants left him. <span id='dcv_3_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>So E′hud came to him as he was sitting alone in his cool roof chamber. Then E′hud said: “I have a message from God for you.” So he rose up from his throne.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_3_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then E′hud drew the sword from his right thigh with his left hand and plunged it into his belly. <span id='dcv_3_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>The handle went in after the blade, and the fat closed in over the blade, for he did not draw the sword out of his belly, and the fecal matter came out. <span id='dcv_3_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>E′hud went out through the porch,<a class='fn'></a> closing the doors of the roof chamber behind him and locking them. <span id='dcv_3_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>After he left, the servants returned and saw that the doors of the roof chamber were locked. So they said: “He must be relieving himself<a class='fn'></a> in the cool interior room.” <span id='dcv_3_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>They kept waiting until they were embarrassed, but when they saw that he was still not opening the doors of the roof chamber, they took the key and opened them and saw their lord fallen to the floor<a class='fn'></a> dead!</p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>E′hud escaped while they were lingering, and he passed by the carved images<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and made it safely to Se·i′rah. <span id='dcv_3_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>When he arrived, he sounded the horn<a class='mr'></a> in the mountainous region of E′phra·im;<a class='mr'></a> and the Israelites went down out of the mountainous region, with him at their head. <span id='dcv_3_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then he said to them: “Follow me, because Jehovah has given your enemies, the Mo′ab·ites, into your hand.” So they followed him and captured the fords of the Jordan against the Mo′ab·ites, and they did not allow anyone to cross. <span id='dcv_3_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>At that time they struck down about 10,000 Mo′ab·ites,<a class='mr'></a> all strong and valiant men; not a single one escaped.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So Mo′ab was subdued on that day under Israel’s hand; and the land had rest<a class='fn'></a> for 80 years.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>After him was Sham′gar<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′nath, who struck down 600 Phi·lis′tine men<a class='mr'></a> with a cattle goad;<a class='mr'></a> he too saved Israel.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dp'><a>4 </a></span>But after E′hud died, the Israelites again did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So Jehovah sold them into the hand of Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan,<a class='mr'></a> who reigned in Ha′zor. The chief of his army was Sis′e·ra, who lived in Ha·ro′sheth<a class='mr'></a> of the nations.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>The Israelites cried out to Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> because Ja′bin<a class='fn'></a> had 900 war chariots with iron scythes,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and he harshly oppressed the Israelites<a class='mr'></a> for 20 years.</p></div><div id='p27' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now Deb′o·rah, a prophetess,<a class='mr'></a> the wife of Lap′pi·doth, was judging Israel at that time. <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>She used to sit under Deb′o·rah’s palm tree between Ra′mah<a class='mr'></a> and Beth′el<a class='mr'></a> in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; the Israelites would go up to her for judgment. <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>She sent for Ba′rak<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·bin′o·am out of Ke′desh-naph′ta·li<a class='mr'></a> and said to him: “Has not Jehovah the God of Israel given the command? ‘Go and march to<a class='fn'></a> Mount Ta′bor, and take 10,000 men of Naph′ta·li and Zeb′u·lun with you. <span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>I will bring to you Sis′e·ra, the chief of Ja′bin’s army, along with his war chariots and his troops to the stream<a class='fn'></a> of Ki′shon,<a class='mr'></a> and I will give him into your hand.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p28' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>At this Ba′rak said to her: “If you go with me, I will go, but if you do not go with me, I will not go.” <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>To this she said: “I will certainly go with you. However, the campaign you are going on will not bring you glory, for it will be into the hand of a woman that Jehovah will give Sis′e·ra.”<a class='mr'></a> Then Deb′o·rah got up and went with Ba′rak to Ke′desh.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Ba′rak summoned Zeb′u·lun and Naph′ta·li<a class='mr'></a> to Ke′desh, and 10,000 men followed his steps. Deb′o·rah also went up with him.</p></div><div id='p29' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Incidentally, He′ber the Ken′ite had separated from the Ken′ites,<a class='mr'></a> the descendants of Ho′bab, Moses’ father-in-law,<a class='mr'></a> and his tent was pitched near the big tree in Za·a·nan′nim, which is at Ke′desh.</p></div><div id='p30' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>They reported to Sis′e·ra that Ba′rak the son of A·bin′o·am had gone up to Mount Ta′bor.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>At once Sis′e·ra assembled all his war chariots—900 chariots with iron scythes<a class='fn'></a>—and all the troops that were with him from Ha·ro′sheth of the nations to go to the stream<a class='fn'></a> of Ki′shon.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Deb′o·rah now said to Ba′rak: “Rise up, for this is the day that Jehovah will give Sis′e·ra into your hand. Is Jehovah not going out before you?” And Ba′rak descended from Mount Ta′bor with 10,000 men following him. <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Then Jehovah threw Sis′e·ra and all his war chariots and all the army into confusion<a class='mr'></a> before the sword of Ba′rak. Finally Sis′e·ra got down from his chariot and fled on foot. <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Ba′rak chased after the war chariots and the army as far as Ha·ro′sheth of the nations. So Sis′e·ra’s whole army fell by the sword; not even one remained.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p31' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>But Sis′e·ra fled on foot to the tent of Ja′el<a class='mr'></a> the wife of He′ber<a class='mr'></a> the Ken′ite, for there was peace between Ja′bin<a class='mr'></a> the king of Ha′zor and the house of He′ber the Ken′ite. <span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then Ja′el came out to meet Sis′e·ra and said to him: “Come in, my lord, come in here. Do not be afraid.” So he went into her tent, and she covered him with a blanket. <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Then he said to her: “Give me, please, a little water to drink, for I am thirsty.” So she opened a skin bottle of milk and gave him a drink,<a class='mr'></a> after which she again covered him. <span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>He told her: “Stand at the entrance of the tent, and if anybody comes and asks you, ‘Is there a man here?’ say, ‘No!’”</p></div><div id='p32' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>But Ja′el the wife of He′ber took a tent pin and a hammer in her hand. Then while he was fast asleep and exhausted, she stealthily approached him and drove the pin through his temples and beat it into the ground, and he died.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p33' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Ba′rak went there in pursuit of Sis′e·ra, and Ja′el now came out to meet him and said: “Come and I will show you the man you are looking for.” He went in with her and saw Sis′e·ra lying dead, with the tent pin through his temples.</p></div><div id='p34' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So on that day, God subdued Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan before the Israelites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>The hand of the Israelites came down harder and harder against Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan,<a class='mr'></a> until they destroyed Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="5"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p35' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_5_1' class='dc dp'><a>5 </a></span>On that day Deb′o·rah<a class='mr'></a> along with Ba′rak<a class='mr'></a> the son of A·bin′o·am sang this song:<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p36' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Because of the unbound hair<a class='fn'></a> in Israel,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Because of the people’s volunteering,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Praise Jehovah!</p></div><div id='p37' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Listen, you kings! Give ear, you rulers!</p></div><div id='p38' class='par'><p class='sz'>To Jehovah I will sing.</p></div><div id='p39' class='par'><p class='sz'>I will sing praises<a class='fn'></a> to Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> Israel’s God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p40' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Jehovah, when you went out from Se′ir,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>When you marched out of the territory of E′dom,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The earth shook, and the heavens poured,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The clouds poured down water.</p></div><div id='p41' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Mountains melted<a class='fn'></a> before the face of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Even Si′nai before the face of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> Israel’s God.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p42' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>In the days of Sham′gar<a class='mr'></a> the son of A′nath,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>In the days of Ja′el,<a class='mr'></a> the roads were deserted;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Travelers kept to the back roads.</p></div><div id='p43' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>The villagers in Israel were no more;<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>They were no more until I, Deb′o·rah,<a class='mr'></a> rose up,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Until I arose as a mother in Israel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p44' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>They chose new gods;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Then there was war in the gates.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p45' class='par'><p class='sz'>A shield could not be seen, nor a lance,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Among 40,000 in Israel.</p></div><div id='p46' class='par'><p class='sl'> <span id='dcv_5_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>My heart is with the commanders of Israel,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Who went as volunteers with the people.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p47' class='par'><p class='sz'>Praise Jehovah!</p></div><div id='p48' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>You riders on tawny donkeys,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>You who sit on fine carpets,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And you who walk on the road,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Consider!</p></div><div id='p49' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>The voices of the water distributors were heard at the watering places;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>There they were recounting the righteous acts of Jehovah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The righteous acts of his villagers in Israel.</p></div><div id='p50' class='par'><p class='sz'>Then Jehovah’s people went down to the gates.</p></div><div id='p51' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Awake, awake, O Deb′o·rah!<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p52' class='par'><p class='sz'>Awake, awake, sing a song!<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p53' class='par'><p class='sz'>Rise up, Ba′rak!<a class='mr'></a> Lead your captives away, you son of A·bin′o·am!</p></div><div id='p54' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then those who were left came down to the nobles;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Jehovah’s people came down to me against the mighty.</p></div><div id='p55' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Out of E′phra·im was their origin, those in the valley;<a class='fn'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>They are following you, O Benjamin, among your peoples.</p></div><div id='p56' class='par'><p class='sz'>From Ma′chir<a class='mr'></a> the commanders went down,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And from Zeb′u·lun those who bear the recruiter’s staff.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p57' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>The princes in Is′sa·char were with Deb′o·rah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>As was Is′sa·char, so was Ba′rak.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p58' class='par'><p class='sz'>Into the valley plain<a class='fn'></a> he was sent on foot.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p59' class='par'><p class='sz'>Among the divisions of Reu′ben there was intense heart-searching.</p></div><div id='p60' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Why did you sit down between the two saddlebags,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Listening to them playing their pipes for the flocks?<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p61' class='par'><p class='sz'>For the divisions of Reu′ben, there was intense heart-searching.</p></div><div id='p62' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Gil′e·ad remained beyond the Jordan;<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And Dan, why did he stay with the ships?<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p63' class='par'><p class='sz'>Ash′er sat idle at the seashore,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And by his harbors<a class='fn'></a> he remained.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p64' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Zeb′u·lun was a people who risked their lives<a class='fn'></a> to the point of death;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Naph′ta·li also,<a class='mr'></a> on the open heights.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p65' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Kings came, they fought;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The kings of Ca′naan then fought<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>In Ta′a·nach, by the waters of Me·gid′do.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p66' class='par'><p class='sz'>No spoil of silver did they take.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p67' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>From heaven the stars fought;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>From their orbits they fought against Sis′e·ra.</p></div><div id='p68' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>The torrent<a class='fn'></a> of Ki′shon washed them away,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The ancient torrent,<a class='fn'></a> the torrent<a class='fn'></a> of Ki′shon.</p></div><div id='p69' class='par'><p class='sz'>You trampled down the powerful, O my soul.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p70' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Then the hooves of horses pounded</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>As his stallions galloped furiously.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p71' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>‘Curse Me′roz,’ said the angel of Jehovah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>‘Yes, curse its inhabitants,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For they did not come to the assistance of Jehovah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>To the assistance of Jehovah with the mighty ones.’</p></div><div id='p72' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Most blessed of women is Ja′el<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>The wife of He′ber<a class='mr'></a> the Ken′ite;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>She is most blessed of women living in tents.</p></div><div id='p73' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>He asked for water; she gave him milk.</p></div><div id='p74' class='par'><p class='sz'>In a majestic banquet bowl she offered curdled milk.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p75' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>With her hand she reached for the tent pin,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Her right hand for the workman’s mallet.</p></div><div id='p76' class='par'><p class='sz'>And she hammered Sis′e·ra, she crushed his head,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And she smashed and pierced his temples.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p77' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>Between her feet he collapsed; he fell and lay still;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Between her feet he collapsed and fell;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Where he collapsed, there he fell defeated.</p></div><div id='p78' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>From the window a woman looked out,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Sis′e·ra’s mother peered out from the lattice,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>‘Why is his chariot delayed in coming?</p></div><div id='p79' class='par'><p class='sz'>Why are the hoofbeats of his chariots so late?’<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p80' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>The wisest of her noble ladies would answer her;</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Yes, she too would repeat to herself,</p><p class='sl'><span class='br'></span><span id='dcv_5_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>‘They must be dividing the spoil they found,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>A girl,<a class='fn'></a> two girls,<a class='fn'></a> to every warrior,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>Spoil of dyed cloth for Sis′e·ra, spoil of dyed cloth,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>An embroidered garment, dyed cloth, two embroidered garments</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>For the necks of the plunderers.’</p></div><div id='p81' class='par'><p class='sl'><span id='dcv_5_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>So let all your enemies perish,<a class='mr'></a> O Jehovah,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>But let those who love you be like the sun rising in its glory.”</p></div><div id='p82' class='par'><p class='sb'>And the land had rest<a class='fn'></a> for 40 years.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="6"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p83' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_1' class='dc dp'><a>6 </a></span>But the Israelites again did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> so Jehovah gave them into the hand of Mid′i·an for seven years.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The hand of Mid′i·an dominated over Israel.<a class='mr'></a> Because of Mid′i·an, the Israelites made hiding places<a class='fn'></a> for themselves in the mountains, in the caves, and in the places difficult to approach.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>If Israel sowed seed, Mid′i·an and Am′a·lek<a class='mr'></a> and the Easterners<a class='mr'></a> would attack them. <span id='dcv_6_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>They would camp against them and ruin the produce of the land all the way to Gaz′a, and they left nothing for Israel to eat and no sheep or bull or donkey.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>For they would come up with their livestock and tents as numerous as the locusts,<a class='mr'></a> and they and their camels could not be numbered,<a class='mr'></a> and they would come into the land to destroy it. <span id='dcv_6_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So Israel became greatly impoverished on account of Mid′i·an; and the Israelites called to Jehovah for help.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p84' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>When the Israelites called to Jehovah for help because of Mid′i·an,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Jehovah sent to the Israelites a prophet who said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘I brought you up from Egypt and thus brought you out of the house of slavery.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So I rescued you from the hand of Egypt and from all your oppressors and drove them out from before you and gave you their land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>And I said to you: “I am Jehovah your God.<a class='mr'></a> You must not fear the gods of the Am′or·ites in whose land you are dwelling.”<a class='mr'></a> But you did not obey me.’”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p85' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Later Jehovah’s angel came<a class='mr'></a> and sat under the big tree that was in Oph′rah, which belonged to Jo′ash the Abi-ez′rite.<a class='mr'></a> His son Gid′e·on<a class='mr'></a> was beating out wheat in the winepress in order to hide it from Mid′i·an. <span id='dcv_6_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Jehovah’s angel appeared to him and said: “Jehovah is with you,<a class='mr'></a> you mighty warrior.” <span id='dcv_6_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>At this Gid′e·on said to him: “Pardon me, my lord, but if Jehovah is with us, why has all of this come upon us?<a class='mr'></a> Where are all his wonderful acts that our fathers related to us,<a class='mr'></a> saying, ‘Did Jehovah not bring us up out of Egypt?’<a class='mr'></a> Now Jehovah has deserted us<a class='mr'></a> and given us into Mid′i·an’s hand.” <span id='dcv_6_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Jehovah faced him and said: “Go with the strength you have, and you will save Israel out of Mid′i·an’s hand.<a class='mr'></a> Is it not I who send you?” <span id='dcv_6_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>Gid′e·on answered him: “Pardon me, Jehovah. How can I save Israel? Look! My clan<a class='fn'></a> is the least in Ma·nas′seh, and I am the most insignificant in my father’s house.” <span id='dcv_6_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>But Jehovah said to him: “Because I will be with you,<a class='mr'></a> you will strike down Mid′i·an as if they were one man.”</p></div><div id='p86' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then he said to him: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, show me a sign that you are the one speaking with me. <span id='dcv_6_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Please do not depart from here until I return with my gift and set it before you.”<a class='mr'></a> So he said: “I will stay here until you return.” <span id='dcv_6_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>And Gid′e·on went in and prepared a young goat and made unleavened bread from an e′phah<a class='fn'></a> of flour.<a class='mr'></a> He put the meat in the basket and the broth in the cooking pot; then he brought them out to him and served them under the big tree.</p></div><div id='p87' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>The angel of the true God now said to him: “Take the meat and the unleavened bread and place them on the big rock there, and pour out the broth.” And he did so. <span id='dcv_6_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then Jehovah’s angel stretched out the tip of the staff that was in his hand and touched the meat and the unleavened bread, and fire flared up from the rock and consumed the meat and the unleavened bread.<a class='mr'></a> Jehovah’s angel then vanished from his sight. <span id='dcv_6_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Gid′e·on now realized that it was Jehovah’s angel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p88' class='par'><p class='sb'>At once Gid′e·on said: “Alas, Sovereign Lord Jehovah, for I have seen Jehovah’s angel face-to-face!”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>But Jehovah said to him: “Peace be with you. Have no fear;<a class='mr'></a> you will not die.” <span id='dcv_6_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>So Gid′e·on built an altar there to Jehovah, and it is called Je·ho′vah-sha′lom<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> down to this day. It is still in Oph′rah of the Abi-ez′rites.</p></div><div id='p89' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>That night Jehovah said to him: “Take the young bull that belongs to your father, the second young bull that is seven years old, and tear down the altar of Ba′al that belongs to your father, and cut down the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a> next to it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>After you build an altar to Jehovah your God on top of this stronghold with the row of stones, take the second young bull and offer it as a burnt offering on the pieces of wood from the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a> that you cut down.” <span id='dcv_6_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>So Gid′e·on took ten men of his servants and did just as Jehovah told him. But he feared the household of his father and the men of the city too much to do it by day, so he did it at night.</p></div><div id='p90' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>When the men of the city got up early the next morning, they saw that the altar of Ba′al had been pulled down and the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a> beside it had been cut down and the second young bull had been offered up on the altar that had been built. <span id='dcv_6_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>They asked one another: “Who did this?” After they investigated, they said: “Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash did this.” <span id='dcv_6_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>So the men of the city said to Jo′ash: “Bring your son out that he may die, because he pulled down the altar of Ba′al and cut down the sacred pole<a class='fn'></a> next to it.” <span id='dcv_6_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Jo′ash<a class='mr'></a> then said to all those who confronted him: “Do you have to defend Ba′al? Do you have to save him? Whoever defends him should be put to death this morning.<a class='mr'></a> If he is a god, let him defend himself,<a class='mr'></a> since someone pulled down his altar.” <span id='dcv_6_32' class='dv dx dp'><a>32 </a></span>And he called Gid′e·on Jer·ub·ba′al<a class='fn'></a> on that day, saying: “Let Ba′al defend himself, for someone has pulled down his altar.”</p></div><div id='p91' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>All Mid′i·an<a class='mr'></a> and Am′a·lek<a class='mr'></a> and the Easterners joined forces;<a class='mr'></a> and they crossed over<a class='fn'></a> into the Valley<a class='fn'></a> of Jez′re·el and camped. <span id='dcv_6_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>Then Jehovah’s spirit came upon<a class='fn'></a> Gid′e·on<a class='mr'></a> and he sounded the horn,<a class='mr'></a> and the Abi-ez′rites<a class='mr'></a> rallied behind him. <span id='dcv_6_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>He sent out messengers through all of Ma·nas′seh, and they too rallied behind him. He also sent out messengers through Ash′er, Zeb′u·lun, and Naph′ta·li, and they came up to meet him.</p></div><div id='p92' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_6_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>Then Gid′e·on said to the true God: “If you are saving Israel by means of me, just as you have promised,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_6_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>here I am laying a fleece of wool on the threshing floor. If there is dew on the fleece only but all the ground around it is dry, then I will know that you will save Israel by means of me, just as you have promised.” <span id='dcv_6_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>And that is how it happened. When he rose up early the next day and wrung the fleece, he squeezed off enough dew from the fleece to fill a large banquet bowl with water. <span id='dcv_6_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>However, Gid′e·on said to the true God: “Do not let your anger burn against me, but let me ask just once more. Let me, please, make just one more test with the fleece. Please let the fleece alone be dry while there is dew all over the ground.” <span id='dcv_6_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>So that is what God did that night; only the fleece was dry, and there was dew all over the ground.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="7"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p93' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then Jer·ub·ba′al, that is, Gid′e·on,<a class='mr'></a> and all the people with him rose early and encamped at the well of Ha′rod, while the camp of Mid′i·an was north of him at the hill of Mo′reh in the valley plain.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_7_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Jehovah now said to Gid′e·on: “There are too many people with you for me to give Mid′i·an into their hand.<a class='mr'></a> Otherwise, Israel might brag about itself against me and say, ‘My own hand saved me.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Now, please, announce in the presence of the people: ‘Whoever is afraid and trembling, let him return home.’”<a class='mr'></a> So Gid′e·on put them to the test. With that, 22,000 of the people returned home, and 10,000 remained.</p></div><div id='p94' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Still Jehovah said to Gid′e·on: “There are yet too many people. Have them go down to the water so that I may test them for you there. When I say to you, ‘This one will go with you,’ he will go with you, but when I say to you, ‘This one will not go along with you,’ he will not go along.” <span id='dcv_7_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So he took the people down to the water.</p></div><div id='p95' class='par'><p class='sb'>Then Jehovah said to Gid′e·on: “Separate everyone who laps up the water with his tongue just as a dog laps, from those who bend down on their knees to drink.” <span id='dcv_7_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>The number of those lapping up the water, putting their hand to their mouth, was 300 men. The rest of the people bent down on their knees to drink.</p></div><div id='p96' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Jehovah now said to Gid′e·on: “I will save you with the 300 men who lapped the water, and I will give Mid′i·an into your hand.<a class='mr'></a> But let all the other people go back home.” <span id='dcv_7_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So after they took the provisions and the horns from the people, he sent all the other men of Israel back home, and he kept only the 300 men. The camp of Mid′i·an was below him in the valley plain.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p97' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>During that night, Jehovah said to him: “Get up, attack the camp, for I have given it into your hand.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>But if you are afraid to attack, go down to the camp with Pu′rah your attendant. <span id='dcv_7_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Listen to what they say, and afterward you will have the courage<a class='fn'></a> to attack the camp.” At that he and Pu′rah his attendant went down to the edge of the encamped army.</p></div><div id='p98' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Now Mid′i·an and Am′a·lek and all the Easterners<a class='mr'></a> covered the valley plain like a swarm of locusts, and their camels were without number,<a class='mr'></a> as many as the grains of sand on the seashore. <span id='dcv_7_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Gid′e·on now came, and there was a man relating a dream to his companion, and he said: “This is the dream I had. There was a round loaf of barley bread rolling into the camp of Mid′i·an. It came to a tent and struck it so hard that it collapsed.<a class='mr'></a> Yes, it turned the tent upside down, and the tent fell flat.” <span id='dcv_7_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>At this his companion said: “This can only be the sword of Gid′e·on<a class='mr'></a> the son of Jo′ash, a man of Israel. God has given Mid′i·an and all the camp into his hand.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p99' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>As soon as Gid′e·on heard him relate the dream and its interpretation,<a class='mr'></a> he bowed down to worship. After that he returned to the camp of Israel and said: “Get up, for Jehovah has given the camp of Mid′i·an into your hand.” <span id='dcv_7_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then he divided the 300 men into three bands and gave all of them horns<a class='mr'></a> and large empty jars with torches inside the jars. <span id='dcv_7_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then he said to them: “Watch me and do exactly what I do. When I come to the edge of the camp, you should do just as I do. <span id='dcv_7_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>When I blow the horn, I and all who are with me, you also must blow the horns all around the camp and shout, ‘For Jehovah and for Gid′e·on!’”</p></div><div id='p100' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Gid′e·on and the 100 men who were with him came to the edge of the camp at the start of the middle night watch,<a class='fn'></a> just after the sentries were posted. They blew the horns<a class='mr'></a> and smashed the large water jars that were in their hands.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>So the three bands blew the horns and shattered the large jars. They held the torches in their left hands and blew the horns in their right hands and they called out: “The sword of Jehovah and of Gid′e·on!” <span id='dcv_7_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>All the while each man stood in his place all around the camp, and the whole army ran away, shouting as they fled.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_7_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>The 300 continued to blow the horns, and Jehovah turned the sword of each one against the other throughout the camp;<a class='mr'></a> and the army fled as far as Beth-shit′tah, on to Zer′e·rah, as far as the outskirts of A′bel-me·ho′lah<a class='mr'></a> by Tab′bath.</p></div><div id='p101' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_7_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>And the men of Israel were called together from Naph′ta·li, Ash′er, and all of Ma·nas′seh,<a class='mr'></a> and they chased after Mid′i·an. <span id='dcv_7_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Gid′e·on sent messengers into all the mountainous region of E′phra·im, saying: “Go down to attack Mid′i·an, and capture the access to the waters as far as Beth-bar′ah and the Jordan.” So all the men of E′phra·im were gathered together, and they captured the waters as far as Beth-bar′ah and the Jordan. <span id='dcv_7_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>They also captured the two princes of Mid′i·an, O′reb and Ze′eb; they killed O′reb on the rock of O′reb,<a class='mr'></a> and they killed Ze′eb at the winepress of Ze′eb. They kept on pursuing Mid′i·an,<a class='mr'></a> and they brought the heads of O′reb and Ze′eb to Gid′e·on in the region of the Jordan.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="8"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p102' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then the men of E′phra·im said to him: “What have you done to us? Why did you not call us when you went to fight against Mid′i·an?”<a class='mr'></a> And they quarreled bitterly with him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>But he said to them: “What have I done compared with you? Are not the gleanings of E′phra·im<a class='mr'></a> better than the grape harvest of Abi-e′zer?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>It was into your hand that God gave Mid′i·an’s princes O′reb and Ze′eb,<a class='mr'></a> and what have I done compared with you?” When he spoke this way,<a class='fn'></a> they calmed down.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p103' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Gid′e·on then came to the Jordan and crossed it. He and the 300 men with him were tired, but they kept up the pursuit. <span id='dcv_8_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So he said to the men of Suc′coth: “Please give loaves of bread to the people following me, for they are tired and I am chasing after Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na, the kings of Mid′i·an.” <span id='dcv_8_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>But the princes of Suc′coth said: “Are the palms of Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na already in your hand so that we should give bread to your army?” <span id='dcv_8_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>At this Gid′e·on said: “Just for that, when Jehovah gives Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na into my hand, I will give you a thrashing with the thorns and the briars of the wilderness.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>And he went up from there to Pe·nu′el and made the same request, but the men of Pe·nu′el gave him the same answer as the men of Suc′coth. <span id='dcv_8_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So he said also to the men of Pe·nu′el: “When I return in peace, I will pull down this tower.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p104' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>Now Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na were in Kar′kor with their armies, about 15,000 men. These were all who remained of the entire army of the Easterners,<a class='mr'></a> for 120,000 men armed with swords had fallen. <span id='dcv_8_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Gid′e·on continued up by the way of the tent dwellers east of No′bah and Jog′be·hah<a class='mr'></a> and attacked the camp, which was off guard. <span id='dcv_8_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>When Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na fled, he pursued and captured the two Mid′i·an·ite kings, Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na, throwing the whole camp into a panic.</p></div><div id='p105' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash then returned from the war by way of the pass that goes up to He′res. <span id='dcv_8_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>En route he captured and interrogated a young man from Suc′coth. So the young man wrote out for him the names of the princes and elders of Suc′coth, 77 men. <span id='dcv_8_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>With that he went to the men of Suc′coth and said: “Here are Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na about whom you taunted me, saying, ‘Are the palms of Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na already in your hand so that we should give bread to your exhausted men?’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then he took the elders of the city and with thorns and briars of the wilderness, he taught the men of Suc′coth a lesson.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>And he pulled down the tower of Pe·nu′el<a class='mr'></a> and killed the men of the city.</p></div><div id='p106' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>He asked Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na: “What sort of men did you kill in Ta′bor?” To this they said: “They were like you, each one looked like the son of a king.” <span id='dcv_8_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>At that he said: “They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. As surely as Jehovah lives, if you had spared their lives, I would not have to kill you.” <span id='dcv_8_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>Then he said to Je′ther his firstborn: “Get up, kill them.” But the young man did not draw his sword; he was afraid, for he was still a young man. <span id='dcv_8_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>So Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na said: “Get up yourself and slay us, for a man is judged by his mightiness.”<a class='fn'></a> So Gid′e·on got up and killed Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na<a class='mr'></a> and took the crescent-shaped ornaments that were on the necks of their camels.</p></div><div id='p107' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Later the men of Israel said to Gid′e·on: “Rule over us, you and your son and your grandson as well, for you saved us out of the hand of Mid′i·an.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>But Gid′e·on said to them: “I will not rule over you, nor will my son rule over you. Jehovah is the one who will rule over you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Gid′e·on continued: “Let me make one request of you: that each of you give me a nose ring from his spoil.” (For they had gold nose rings because they were Ish′ma·el·ites.)<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>They replied: “We will surely give them.” With that they spread out a robe and each man threw a nose ring from his spoil on it. <span id='dcv_8_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>The weight of the gold nose rings that he had requested amounted to 1,700 gold shekels,<a class='fn'></a> besides the crescent-shaped ornaments, the pendants, the purple wool garments worn by the kings of Mid′i·an, and the necklaces from the camels.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p108' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>Gid′e·on made it into an eph′od<a class='mr'></a> and exhibited it in his city Oph′rah;<a class='mr'></a> and all Israel committed spiritual prostitution with it there,<a class='mr'></a> and it served as a snare to Gid′e·on and to his household.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p109' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Thus Mid′i·an<a class='mr'></a> was subdued before the Israelites, and they did not challenge them<a class='fn'></a> again; and the land had rest<a class='fn'></a> for 40 years in the days of Gid′e·on.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p110' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>So Jer·ub·ba′al<a class='mr'></a> the son of Jo′ash returned to his home and stayed there.</p></div><div id='p111' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Gid′e·on became father to 70 sons,<a class='fn'></a> for he had many wives. <span id='dcv_8_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>His concubine in She′chem also bore him a son, and he named him A·bim′e·lech.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>And Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash died at a good old age and was buried in the tomb of Jo′ash his father in Oph′rah of the Abi-ez′rites.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p112' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_8_33' class='dv dp'><a>33 </a></span>As soon as Gid′e·on died, the Israelites again committed spiritual prostitution with the Ba′als,<a class='mr'></a> and they appointed Ba′al-be′rith as their god.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>The Israelites did not remember Jehovah their God,<a class='mr'></a> who had rescued them from the hand of all their enemies around them;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_8_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>nor did they show loyal love toward the household of Jer·ub·ba′al, that is Gid′e·on, in return for all the good that he had done for Israel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="9"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p113' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_1' class='dc dp'><a>9 </a></span>In time A·bim′e·lech<a class='mr'></a> the son of Jer·ub·ba′al went to his mother’s brothers in She′chem, and he said to them and to all the family of his grandfather:<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_9_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>“Please ask all the leaders<a class='fn'></a> of She′chem, ‘Which is better for you, for all 70 sons of Jer·ub·ba′al<a class='mr'></a> to rule over you or for one man to rule over you? And remember that I am your own bone and flesh.’”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p114' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>So his mother’s brothers said this in his behalf to all the leaders of She′chem, and their hearts were inclined to follow A·bim′e·lech, for they said: “He is our own brother.” <span id='dcv_9_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Then they gave him 70 pieces of silver from the house<a class='fn'></a> of Ba′al-be′rith,<a class='mr'></a> and A·bim′e·lech used it to hire idle and insolent men to accompany him. <span id='dcv_9_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>After that he went to his father’s house at Oph′rah<a class='mr'></a> and killed his brothers,<a class='mr'></a> the sons of Jer·ub·ba′al, 70 men, on one stone. The only survivor was Jo′tham, the youngest son of Jer·ub·ba′al, because he hid.</p></div><div id='p115' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then all the leaders of She′chem and all Beth-mil′lo gathered together and made A·bim′e·lech king,<a class='mr'></a> close by the big tree, by the pillar that was in She′chem.</p></div><div id='p116' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>When they reported it to Jo′tham, he at once went and stood on the top of Mount Ger′i·zim<a class='mr'></a> and called out in a loud voice to them: “Listen to me, you leaders of She′chem, and then God will listen to you.</p></div><div id='p117' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>“Once there were trees that went to anoint a king over them. So they said to the olive tree, ‘Rule over us.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>But the olive tree said to them, ‘Must I give up my oil,<a class='fn'></a> which they use to glorify God and men, to go and wave over the other trees?’ <span id='dcv_9_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then the trees said to the fig tree, ‘Come and rule over us.’ <span id='dcv_9_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But the fig tree said to them, ‘Must I give up my sweetness and my good fruitage to go and wave over the other trees?’ <span id='dcv_9_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Next the trees said to the vine, ‘Come and rule over us.’ <span id='dcv_9_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>The vine replied to them, ‘Must I give up my new wine that makes God and men rejoice to go and wave over the trees?’ <span id='dcv_9_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Finally all the other trees said to the bramble, ‘Come and rule over us.’<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>At this the bramble said to the trees, ‘If you are really anointing me as king over you, come and seek refuge under my shadow. But if not, let fire come out of the bramble and consume the cedars of Leb′a·non.’</p></div><div id='p118' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>“Now have you acted sincerely and honorably in making A·bim′e·lech king,<a class='mr'></a> and have you shown goodness toward Jer·ub·ba′al and his household, and have you treated him as he deserves? <span id='dcv_9_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>When my father fought for you,<a class='mr'></a> he risked his life<a class='fn'></a> to save you from Mid′i·an’s hand.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>But today you have risen up against my father’s household and killed his sons, 70 men, on one stone.<a class='mr'></a> Then you made A·bim′e·lech, the son of his slave girl,<a class='mr'></a> king over the leaders of She′chem just because he is your brother. <span id='dcv_9_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Yes, if you are acting sincerely and honorably toward Jer·ub·ba′al and his household this day, rejoice over A·bim′e·lech and let him also rejoice over you. <span id='dcv_9_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>But if not, may fire come out of A·bim′e·lech and consume the leaders of She′chem and Beth-mil′lo,<a class='mr'></a> and may fire come out of the leaders of She′chem and Beth-mil′lo and consume A·bim′e·lech.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p119' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then Jo′tham<a class='mr'></a> fled and escaped to Be′er, and he lived there because of his brother A·bim′e·lech.</p></div><div id='p120' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech ruled<a class='fn'></a> over Israel for three years. <span id='dcv_9_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Then God let hostility develop<a class='fn'></a> between A·bim′e·lech and the leaders of She′chem, and they dealt treacherously with A·bim′e·lech. <span id='dcv_9_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>This was so that the violence done to the 70 sons of Jer·ub·ba′al might be avenged, so as to place responsibility for their blood on their brother A·bim′e·lech for killing them<a class='mr'></a> and on the leaders of She′chem for helping him to kill his brothers. <span id='dcv_9_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>So the leaders of She′chem set men to ambush him on the mountaintops, and they would rob everyone who passed by them on the road. In time it was reported to A·bim′e·lech.</p></div><div id='p121' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>Then Ga′al son of E′bed and his brothers crossed over into She′chem,<a class='mr'></a> and the leaders of She′chem put their trust in him. <span id='dcv_9_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>They went out into the field and gathered the grapes of their vineyards, trod them out, and held a festival, after which they went into the house of their god<a class='mr'></a> and ate and drank and cursed A·bim′e·lech. <span id='dcv_9_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Then Ga′al the son of E′bed said: “Who is A·bim′e·lech, and who is She′chem that we should serve him? Is he not the son of Jer·ub·ba′al,<a class='mr'></a> and is not Ze′bul his commissioner? Serve the men of Ha′mor, She′chem’s father! But why should we serve him? <span id='dcv_9_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>If only this people were under my command, I would depose A·bim′e·lech.” Then he said to A·bim′e·lech: “Increase your army and come out.”</p></div><div id='p122' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>When Ze′bul the prince of the city heard the words of Ga′al the son of E′bed, his anger blazed. <span id='dcv_9_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>So he secretly<a class='fn'></a> sent messengers to A·bim′e·lech, saying: “Look! Ga′al the son of E′bed and his brothers are now in She′chem, and here they are inciting the city against you. <span id='dcv_9_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>Now come up by night, you and your men, and lie in wait in the field. <span id='dcv_9_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>As soon as the sun rises in the morning, you should get up early and attack the city; and when he and his men come out against you, do whatever you can to defeat him.”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p123' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>So A·bim′e·lech and all the people with him rose up by night, and in four bands they lay in wait against She′chem. <span id='dcv_9_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>When Ga′al the son of E′bed went out and stood at the entrance of the city gate, A·bim′e·lech and the people with him rose up from the ambush. <span id='dcv_9_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>When Ga′al saw the people, he said to Ze′bul: “Look! There are people coming down from the mountaintops.” But Ze′bul said to him: “You are seeing the shadows of the mountains as if they were men.”</p></div><div id='p124' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>Ga′al later said: “Look! People are coming down from the center of the land, and one band is coming by the way of the big tree of Me·on′e·nim.” <span id='dcv_9_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>Ze′bul replied to him: “Where now is your boast, ‘Who is A·bim′e·lech that we should serve him?’<a class='mr'></a> Are these not the people you rejected? Go out now and fight against them.”</p></div><div id='p125' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>So Ga′al went out at the head of the leaders of She′chem and fought against A·bim′e·lech. <span id='dcv_9_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech pursued him, and Ga′al fled from him, and many fell slain as far as the entrance of the city gate.</p></div><div id='p126' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>And A·bim′e·lech continued to dwell in A·ru′mah, and Ze′bul<a class='mr'></a> drove Ga′al and his brothers out of She′chem. <span id='dcv_9_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>The next day the people went out into the field, and A·bim′e·lech was told about it. <span id='dcv_9_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>So he took the people and divided them into three bands and lay in wait in the field. When he saw the people going out of the city, he attacked them and struck them down. <span id='dcv_9_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech and the bands with him charged forward and took a position at the entrance of the city gate, while two bands attacked all who were in the field, and they struck them down. <span id='dcv_9_45' class='dv dx dp'><a>45 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech fought against the city all that day and captured it. He killed the people in it, and then he pulled the city down<a class='mr'></a> and sowed it with salt.</p></div><div id='p127' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>When all the leaders of the tower of She′chem heard about this, they immediately went to the vault<a class='fn'></a> of the house<a class='fn'></a> of El-be′rith.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>As soon as it was reported to A·bim′e·lech that all the leaders of the tower of She′chem had gathered together, <span id='dcv_9_48' class='dv dx dp'><a>48 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech and all the men with him went up Mount Zal′mon. A·bim′e·lech took an ax in his hand and cut off a tree branch and lifted it on his shoulder and said to the people with him: “What you saw me do, hurry and do the same!” <span id='dcv_9_49' class='dv dp'><a>49 </a></span>So all the people also cut off branches and followed A·bim′e·lech. Then they put the branches against the vault and set the vault on fire. So all the people of the tower of She′chem also died, about 1,000 men and women.</p></div><div id='p128' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_50' class='dv dp'><a>50 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech then went to The′bez; he camped against The′bez and captured it. <span id='dcv_9_51' class='dv dx dp'><a>51 </a></span>There was a strong tower in the middle of the city, and all the men and women and all the city leaders fled there. They shut themselves in and climbed onto the roof of the tower. <span id='dcv_9_52' class='dv dp'><a>52 </a></span>A·bim′e·lech made his way to the tower and attacked it. He approached the entrance of the tower to set it on fire. <span id='dcv_9_53' class='dv dp'><a>53 </a></span>Then one of the women dropped an upper millstone on A·bim′e·lech’s head and crushed his skull.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_54' class='dv dp'><a>54 </a></span>He quickly called the attendant bearing his weapons and said to him: “Draw your sword and put me to death, so that they may not say about me, ‘A woman killed him.’” So his attendant ran him through, and he died.</p></div><div id='p129' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_9_55' class='dv dp'><a>55 </a></span>When the men of Israel saw that A·bim′e·lech was dead, they all went back home. <span id='dcv_9_56' class='dv dp'><a>56 </a></span>Thus God repaid A·bim′e·lech for the evil that he had done to his father by killing his 70 brothers.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_9_57' class='dv dp'><a>57 </a></span>God also made all the evil of the men of She′chem come back on their own heads. So the curse of Jo′tham<a class='mr'></a> the son of Jer·ub·ba′al<a class='mr'></a> came upon them.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="10"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p130' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>After A·bim′e·lech, To′la the son of Pu′ah, the son of Do′do, a man of Is′sa·char, rose up to save Israel.<a class='mr'></a> He lived in Sha′mir in the mountainous region of E′phra·im. <span id='dcv_10_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He judged Israel for 23 years. Then he died and was buried in Sha′mir.</p></div><div id='p131' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>After him Ja′ir the Gil′e·ad·ite rose up and judged Israel for 22 years. <span id='dcv_10_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>He had 30 sons who rode on 30 donkeys, and they had 30 cities, which to this day are called Hav′voth-ja′ir;<a class='mr'></a> they are in the land of Gil′e·ad. <span id='dcv_10_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>After that Ja′ir died and was buried in Ka′mon.</p></div><div id='p132' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Again the Israelites did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> and they began to serve the Ba′als,<a class='mr'></a> the Ash′to·reth images, the gods of A′ram,<a class='fn'></a> the gods of Si′don, the gods of Mo′ab,<a class='mr'></a> the gods of the Am′mon·ites,<a class='mr'></a> and the gods of the Phi·lis′tines.<a class='mr'></a> They abandoned Jehovah and did not serve him. <span id='dcv_10_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, and he sold them into the hands of the Phi·lis′tines and the Am′mon·ites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>So they crushed and greatly oppressed the Israelites in that year—for 18 years they oppressed all the Israelites on the side of the Jordan that had been the land of the Am′or·ites in Gil′e·ad. <span id='dcv_10_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>The Am′mon·ites would also cross the Jordan to fight against Judah and Benjamin and the house of E′phra·im; and Israel was greatly distressed. <span id='dcv_10_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then the Israelites called to Jehovah for help,<a class='mr'></a> saying: “We have sinned against you, for we abandoned our God and served the Ba′als.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p133' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But Jehovah said to the Israelites: “Did I not save you from Egypt<a class='mr'></a> and from the Am′or·ites,<a class='mr'></a> the Am′mon·ites, the Phi·lis′tines,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>the Si·do′ni·ans, Am′a·lek, and Mid′i·an when they oppressed you? When you cried out to me, I saved you out of their hand. <span id='dcv_10_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>But you abandoned me and served other gods.<a class='mr'></a> That is why I will not save you again.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Go to the gods whom you have chosen and call for help.<a class='mr'></a> Let them save you in your time of distress.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_10_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>But the Israelites said to Jehovah: “We have sinned. Do to us whatever is good in your eyes. Only save us, please, this day.” <span id='dcv_10_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>And they removed the foreign gods from their midst and served Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> so that he could no longer tolerate<a class='fn'></a> Israel’s suffering.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p134' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_10_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>In time the Am′mon·ites<a class='mr'></a> were called together, and they pitched camp in Gil′e·ad. So the Israelites gathered together and pitched camp in Miz′pah. <span id='dcv_10_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>The people and the princes of Gil′e·ad said to one another: “Who will take the lead in fighting against the Am′mon·ites?<a class='mr'></a> Let him become the chief over all the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="11"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p135' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Now Jeph′thah<a class='mr'></a> the Gil′e·ad·ite was a mighty warrior; he was the son of a prostitute, and Gil′e·ad was Jeph′thah’s father. <span id='dcv_11_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>But Gil′e·ad’s wife also bore him sons. When the sons of his wife grew up, they drove Jeph′thah out and said to him: “You will have no inheritance in our father’s household, for you are the son of another woman.” <span id='dcv_11_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>So Jeph′thah fled from his brothers and settled in the land of Tob. And idle men joined company with Jeph′thah, and they followed him.</p></div><div id='p136' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>After a while, the Am′mon·ites fought against Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>And when the Am′mon·ites fought against Israel, the elders of Gil′e·ad immediately went to bring Jeph′thah back from the land of Tob. <span id='dcv_11_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>They said to Jeph′thah: “Come and serve as our commander, so that we can fight against the Am′mon·ites.” <span id='dcv_11_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But Jeph′thah said to the elders of Gil′e·ad: “Was it not you who hated me so much that you drove me out of my father’s house?<a class='mr'></a> Why have you come to me now when you are in distress?” <span id='dcv_11_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>At this the elders of Gil′e·ad said to Jeph′thah: “That is why now we have returned to you. If you go with us and fight against the Am′mon·ites, you will become our leader over all the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>So Jeph′thah said to the elders of Gil′e·ad: “If you bring me back to fight against the Am′mon·ites and Jehovah defeats them for me, then I will indeed become your leader!” <span id='dcv_11_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>The elders of Gil′e·ad said to Jeph′thah: “Let Jehovah be the witness<a class='fn'></a> between us if we do not do as you say.” <span id='dcv_11_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So Jeph′thah went with the elders of Gil′e·ad, and the people made him their leader and commander. And Jeph′thah repeated all his words before Jehovah in Miz′pah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p137' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Jeph′thah then sent messengers to the king of the Am′mon·ites,<a class='mr'></a> saying: “What do you have against me<a class='fn'></a> that you have come to attack my land?” <span id='dcv_11_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>So the king of the Am′mon·ites said to the messengers of Jeph′thah: “It is because Israel took my land when they came up out of Egypt,<a class='mr'></a> from the Ar′non<a class='mr'></a> to the Jab′bok and as far as the Jordan.<a class='mr'></a> Now return it peaceably.” <span id='dcv_11_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>But Jeph′thah sent messengers back to the king of the Am′mon·ites <span id='dcv_11_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>to say to him:</p></div><div id='p138' class='par'><p class='sb'>“This is what Jeph′thah says: ‘Israel did not take the land of the Mo′ab·ites<a class='mr'></a> and the land of the Am′mon·ites,<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>for when they came up out of Egypt, Israel walked through the wilderness as far as the Red Sea<a class='mr'></a> and came to Ka′desh.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then Israel sent messengers to the king of E′dom,<a class='mr'></a> saying: “Please let us pass through your land,” but the king of E′dom did not listen. Also to the king of Mo′ab<a class='mr'></a> they sent word, but he did not consent. So Israel kept dwelling in Ka′desh.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>When they walked through the wilderness, they bypassed the land of E′dom<a class='mr'></a> and the land of Mo′ab. They traveled east of the land of Mo′ab<a class='mr'></a> and camped in the region of the Ar′non; they did not come within the boundary of Mo′ab,<a class='mr'></a> for the Ar′non was the boundary of Mo′ab.</p></div><div id='p139' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>“‘After that Israel sent messengers to Si′hon king of the Am′or·ites, king of Hesh′bon, and Israel said to him: “Please let us pass through your land to our own place.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>But Si′hon did not trust Israel to cross through his territory, so Si′hon gathered all his people together and encamped in Ja′haz and fought against Israel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>At this Jehovah the God of Israel gave Si′hon and all his people into Israel’s hand, so that they defeated them and Israel took possession of all the land of the Am′or·ites, the inhabitants of that land.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>Thus they took possession of all the territory of the Am′or·ites from the Ar′non to the Jab′bok and from the wilderness to the Jordan.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p140' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>“‘It was Jehovah the God of Israel who drove out the Am′or·ites from before his people Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and now would you drive them out? <span id='dcv_11_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>Do you not possess whatever your god Che′mosh<a class='mr'></a> gives you to possess? So everyone whom Jehovah our God has driven out from before us is the one we will drive out.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Now are you any better than Ba′lak<a class='mr'></a> the son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab? Did he ever contend with Israel, or did he ever fight against them? <span id='dcv_11_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>While Israel was dwelling in Hesh′bon and its dependent<a class='fn'></a> towns<a class='mr'></a> and in A·ro′er and its dependent towns and in all the cities that are by the banks of the Ar′non for 300 years, why did you never try to take them back during that time?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_11_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>I have not sinned against you, but you are wrong to attack me. Let Jehovah the Judge<a class='mr'></a> be judge today between the people of Israel and the people of Am′mon.’”</p></div><div id='p141' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>But the king of the Am′mon·ites would not listen to the message that Jeph′thah sent to him.</p></div><div id='p142' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Jehovah’s spirit came upon Jeph′thah,<a class='mr'></a> and he passed through Gil′e·ad and Ma·nas′seh to go to Miz′peh of Gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> and from Miz′peh of Gil′e·ad he continued on to the Am′mon·ites.</p></div><div id='p143' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Then Jeph′thah made a vow<a class='mr'></a> to Jehovah and said: “If you give the Am′mon·ites into my hand, <span id='dcv_11_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>then whoever comes out of the door of my house to meet me when I return in peace from the Am′mon·ites will become Jehovah’s,<a class='mr'></a> and I will offer that one up as a burnt offering.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p144' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>So Jeph′thah went to fight against the Am′mon·ites, and Jehovah gave them into his hand. <span id='dcv_11_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>He struck them down with a very great slaughter from A·ro′er all the way to Min′nith—20 cities—and as far as A′bel-ker′a·mim. Thus the Am′mon·ites were subdued before the Israelites.</p></div><div id='p145' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_34' class='dv dx dp'><a>34 </a></span>Finally Jeph′thah came to his home in Miz′pah,<a class='mr'></a> and look! his daughter was coming out to meet him, playing the tambourine and dancing! Now she was his one and only child. Besides her, he had neither son nor daughter. <span id='dcv_11_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>When he saw her, he ripped his garments and said: “Oh no, my daughter! You have broken my heart,<a class='fn'></a> for you have become the one I have banished. Now I have opened my mouth to Jehovah, and I am unable to turn back.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p146' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_36' class='dv dx dp'><a>36 </a></span>But she said to him: “My father, if you have opened your mouth to Jehovah, do to me as you have promised,<a class='mr'></a> since Jehovah has executed vengeance for you upon your enemies, the Am′mon·ites.” <span id='dcv_11_37' class='dv dx dp'><a>37 </a></span>She then said to her father: “Let this be done for me: Let me be alone for two months, and let me go away into the mountains, and let me weep over my virginity with my female companions.”<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p147' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_11_38' class='dv dx dp'><a>38 </a></span>At this he said: “Go!” So he sent her away for two months, and she went to the mountains with her companions to weep over her virginity. <span id='dcv_11_39' class='dv dx dp'><a>39 </a></span>At the end of two months, she returned to her father, after which he carried out the vow he had made regarding her.<a class='mr'></a> She never had relations with a man. And it became a custom<a class='fn'></a> in Israel: <span id='dcv_11_40' class='dv dx dp'><a>40 </a></span>From year to year, the young women of Israel would go to give commendation to the daughter of Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite four days in the year.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="12"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p148' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_1' class='dc dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then the men of E′phra·im were summoned, and they crossed over to Za′phon<a class='fn'></a> and said to Jeph′thah: “Why did you not call us to go with you when you crossed over to fight against the Am′mon·ites?<a class='mr'></a> We will burn your house down with you in it.” <span id='dcv_12_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>But Jeph′thah said to them: “Along with my people, I was engaged in a great conflict with the Am′mon·ites. I did call to you for help, but you did not save me from their hand. <span id='dcv_12_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>When I saw that you would not save me, then I decided to risk my life<a class='fn'></a> and go against the Am′mon·ites,<a class='mr'></a> and Jehovah handed them over to me. So why have you come today to fight against me?”</p></div><div id='p149' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Jeph′thah then gathered all the men of Gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> and they fought E′phra·im; the men of Gil′e·ad defeated E′phra·im, who had said: “You are only fugitives from E′phra·im, you Gil′e·ad·ites in E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh.” <span id='dcv_12_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Gil′e·ad captured the fords of the Jordan<a class='mr'></a> ahead of E′phra·im; and when the men of E′phra·im were trying to escape, they would say, “Let me cross over”; then the men of Gil′e·ad would ask each one, “Are you an E′phra·im·ite?” When he would reply, “No!” <span id='dcv_12_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>they would say to him, “Please say Shib′bo·leth.” But he would say, “Sib′bo·leth,” as he was unable to say the word correctly. Then they would seize him and slay him at the fords of the Jordan. So 42,000 E′phra·im·ites fell at that time.</p></div><div id='p150' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Jeph′thah judged Israel for six years, after which Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite died and was buried in his city in Gil′e·ad.</p></div><div id='p151' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Ib′zan from Beth′le·hem judged Israel after him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_12_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>He had 30 sons and 30 daughters. He sent his daughters to marry men outside his clan, and he brought in 30 women to marry his sons. He judged Israel for seven years. <span id='dcv_12_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then Ib′zan died and was buried in Beth′le·hem.</p></div><div id='p152' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>After him E′lon the Ze·bu′lu·nite judged Israel; he judged Israel for ten years. <span id='dcv_12_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then E′lon the Ze·bu′lu·nite died and was buried in Ai′ja·lon in the land of Zeb′u·lun.</p></div><div id='p153' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_12_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>After him Ab′don the son of Hil′lel the Pir′a·thon·ite judged Israel. <span id='dcv_12_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>He had 40 sons and 30 grandsons who rode on 70 donkeys. He judged Israel for eight years. <span id='dcv_12_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Then Ab′don the son of Hil′lel the Pir′a·thon·ite died and was buried in Pir′a·thon in the land of E′phra·im in the mountain of the A·mal′ek·ite.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="13"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p154' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_1' class='dc dp'><a>13 </a></span>Again the Israelites did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes,<a class='mr'></a> and Jehovah gave them into the hand of the Phi·lis′tines<a class='mr'></a> for 40 years.</p></div><div id='p155' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Meanwhile, there was a man of Zo′rah<a class='mr'></a> of the family of the Dan′ites,<a class='mr'></a> whose name was Ma·no′ah.<a class='mr'></a> His wife was barren and childless.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>In time Jehovah’s angel appeared to the woman and said to her: “Look, you are barren and childless. But you will conceive and give birth to a son.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now be careful not to drink wine or anything alcoholic,<a class='mr'></a> and do not eat anything unclean.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Look! You will conceive and give birth to a son, and no razor should touch his head,<a class='mr'></a> because the child will be a Naz′i·rite of God from birth,<a class='fn'></a> and he will take the lead in saving Israel out of the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p156' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then the woman went and told her husband: “A man of the true God came to me, and his appearance was like an angel of the true God, very awe-inspiring. I did not ask him where he was from, nor did he tell me his name.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>But he said to me, ‘Look! You will conceive and give birth to a son. Now do not drink wine or anything alcoholic, and do not eat anything unclean, because the child will be a Naz′i·rite of God from birth<a class='fn'></a> until the day of his death.’”</p></div><div id='p157' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Ma·no′ah pleaded with Jehovah and said: “Pardon me, Jehovah. Please let the man of the true God whom you just sent come again to instruct us about what we should do with the child who will be born.” <span id='dcv_13_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>So the true God listened to Ma·no′ah, and the angel of the true God came again to the woman while she was sitting in the field; her husband Ma·no′ah was not with her. <span id='dcv_13_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>The woman quickly ran and told her husband: “Look! The man who came to me the other day has appeared to me.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p158' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Then Ma·no′ah got up and went with his wife. He came to the man and said to him: “Are you the man who spoke to my wife?” He said: “I am.” <span id='dcv_13_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then Ma·no′ah said: “May your words come true! What will be the child’s manner of life, and what will be his work?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>So Jehovah’s angel said to Ma·no′ah: “Your wife should keep herself from everything that I mentioned to her.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>She should not eat anything that the grapevine produces, she should not drink wine or anything alcoholic,<a class='mr'></a> and she should not eat anything unclean.<a class='mr'></a> Everything that I commanded her, let her observe.”</p></div><div id='p159' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>Ma·no′ah now said to Jehovah’s angel: “Please stay, and let us prepare a young goat for you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>But Jehovah’s angel said to Ma·no′ah: “If I stay, I will not eat your food; but if you wish to present a burnt offering to Jehovah, you may offer it up.” Ma·no′ah did not know that he was Jehovah’s angel. <span id='dcv_13_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then Ma·no′ah said to Jehovah’s angel: “What is your name,<a class='mr'></a> so that we may honor you when your word comes true?” <span id='dcv_13_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>However, Jehovah’s angel said to him: “Why are you asking about my name, seeing that it is a wonderful one?”</p></div><div id='p160' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Then Ma·no′ah took the young goat and the grain offering and offered them on the rock to Jehovah. And He was doing something amazing while Ma·no′ah and his wife were looking on. <span id='dcv_13_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>As the flame ascended from the altar heavenward, Jehovah’s angel ascended in the flame from the altar while Ma·no′ah and his wife were looking on. At once they fell with their faces to the ground. <span id='dcv_13_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Jehovah’s angel did not appear again to Ma·no′ah and his wife. Then Ma·no′ah realized that he was Jehovah’s angel.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Ma·no′ah then said to his wife: “We are sure to die, because it is God whom we have seen.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_13_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>But his wife said to him: “If Jehovah wanted to put us to death, he would not have accepted a burnt offering<a class='mr'></a> and a grain offering from our hand, he would not have shown us all these things, and he would not have told us any of these things.”</p></div><div id='p161' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_13_24' class='dv dx dp'><a>24 </a></span>The woman later gave birth to a son and named him Samson;<a class='mr'></a> and as the boy grew, Jehovah continued to bless him. <span id='dcv_13_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>In time Jehovah’s spirit started to impel him<a class='mr'></a> in Ma′ha·neh-dan,<a class='mr'></a> between Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="14"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p162' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_1' class='dc dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then Samson went down to Tim′nah, and in Tim′nah he saw a Phi·lis′tine woman.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>So he went up and told his father and mother: “In Tim′nah a Phi·lis′tine woman caught my eye, and I want you to get her for me as a wife.” <span id='dcv_14_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>But his father and mother said to him: “Can you not find a woman among your relatives and among all our people?<a class='mr'></a> Must you go and take a wife from among the uncircumcised Phi·lis′tines?” But Samson said to his father: “Get her for me, because she is the right one for me.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_14_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>His father and mother did not realize that this was from Jehovah, for He was looking for an opportunity against the Phi·lis′tines, as the Phi·lis′tines were ruling over Israel at that time.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p163' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>So Samson went down with his father and mother to Tim′nah. When he reached the vineyards of Tim′nah, why look! a lion<a class='fn'></a> came roaring at him. <span id='dcv_14_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>Then Jehovah’s spirit empowered him,<a class='mr'></a> and he tore it in two, just as someone tears a young goat in two with his bare hands. But he did not tell his father or mother what he had done. <span id='dcv_14_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then he went down and spoke to the woman, and she was still the right one in Samson’s eyes.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p164' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Later when he was going back to take her home,<a class='mr'></a> he turned aside to look at the dead body of the lion, and there in the lion’s carcass was a swarm of bees and honey. <span id='dcv_14_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>So he scraped the honey out into his hands and ate it as he walked along. When he rejoined his father and mother, he gave them some to eat. But he did not tell them that he had scraped the honey out of the carcass of a lion.</p></div><div id='p165' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>His father went down to the woman, and Samson held a banquet there, for that was what the young men used to do. <span id='dcv_14_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>When they saw him, they brought 30 groomsmen to accompany him. <span id='dcv_14_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then Samson said to them: “Please let me tell you a riddle. If during the seven days of the banquet you solve it and tell me the answer, I will have to give you 30 linen garments and 30 outfits of clothing. <span id='dcv_14_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>But if you are unable to tell me the answer, you must give me 30 linen garments and 30 outfits of clothing.” They said: “Tell us your riddle; we want to hear it.” <span id='dcv_14_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>So he said to them:</p></div><div id='p166' class='par'><p class='sz'>“Out of the eater came something to eat,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And out of the strong came something sweet.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p167' class='par'><p class='sb'>They were unable to solve the riddle for three days. <span id='dcv_14_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>On the fourth day, they said to Samson’s wife: “Trick your husband<a class='mr'></a> so that he will tell us the answer to the riddle. Otherwise, we will burn you and your father’s house with fire. Did you invite us here to take our possessions?” <span id='dcv_14_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>So Samson’s wife wept over him and said: “You must hate me; you do not love me.<a class='mr'></a> You told a riddle to my people, but you have not told the answer to me.” At this he said to her: “Why, I have not told it even to my own father and mother! Should I tell it to you?” <span id='dcv_14_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>But she kept weeping over him the rest of the seven-day banquet. He finally told her on the seventh day, because she had pressured him. Then she told her people the answer to the riddle.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_14_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>So on the seventh day before the sun set,<a class='fn'></a> the men of the city said to him:</p></div><div id='p168' class='par'><p class='sz'>“What is sweeter than honey,</p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>And what is stronger than a lion?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p169' class='par'><p class='sz'>He replied to them:</p></div><div id='p170' class='par'><p class='sz'>“If you had not plowed with my young cow,<a class='mr'></a></p><p class='sz'><span class='br'></span>You would not have solved my riddle.”</p></div><div id='p171' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Then Jehovah’s spirit empowered him,<a class='mr'></a> and he went down to Ash′ke·lon<a class='mr'></a> and struck down 30 of their men and took their clothing and gave the outfits to those who had answered the riddle.<a class='mr'></a> He was furious as he went back up to his father’s house.</p></div><div id='p172' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_14_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Samson’s wife<a class='mr'></a> was then given to one of his groomsmen who had accompanied him.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="15"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p173' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_1' class='dc dp'><a>15 </a></span>After a while, in the days of the wheat harvest, Samson went to visit his wife, bringing a young goat. He said: “I wish to go in to my wife in the bedroom.”<a class='fn'></a> But her father did not allow him to go in. <span id='dcv_15_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Her father said: “I thought, ‘You must surely hate her.’<a class='mr'></a> So I gave her to your groomsman.<a class='mr'></a> Is not her younger sister more attractive than she is? Please, take her instead.” <span id='dcv_15_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>However, Samson said to them: “This time I cannot be blamed by the Phi·lis′tines for harming them.”</p></div><div id='p174' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So Samson went and caught 300 foxes. Then he took torches, turned the foxes tail to tail, and put one torch between each pair of tails. <span id='dcv_15_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then he set fire to the torches and sent the foxes out into the fields of standing grain of the Phi·lis′tines. He set on fire everything from sheaf to standing grain, as well as the vineyards and the olive groves.</p></div><div id='p175' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The Phi·lis′tines asked: “Who did this?” They were told: “It was Samson, the son-in-law of the Tim′nite, because he took his wife and gave her to his groomsman.”<a class='mr'></a> At that the Phi·lis′tines went up and burned her and her father with fire.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Then Samson said to them: “If this is how you act, I will not quit until I take revenge on you.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then he struck them down one after the other<a class='fn'></a> with a great slaughter, after which he went down and stayed in a cave<a class='fn'></a> of the crag E′tam.</p></div><div id='p176' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Later the Phi·lis′tines came up and camped in Judah and were tramping about in Le′hi.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then the men of Judah said: “Why have you come up against us?” to which they answered: “We have come up to capture<a class='fn'></a> Samson, to do to him just as he did to us.” <span id='dcv_15_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So 3,000 men of Judah went down to the cave<a class='fn'></a> of the crag E′tam and said to Samson: “Do you not know that the Phi·lis′tines are ruling over us?<a class='mr'></a> So why have you done this to us?” He said to them: “As they did to me, so I did to them.” <span id='dcv_15_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>But they said to him: “We have come to capture<a class='fn'></a> you and to hand you over to the Phi·lis′tines.” Then Samson said: “Swear to me that you yourselves will not assault me.” <span id='dcv_15_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>They said to him: “No, we will only tie you and hand you over to them, but we will not put you to death.”</p></div><div id='p177' class='par'><p class='sb'>So they bound him with two new ropes and brought him up from the crag. <span id='dcv_15_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>When he came to Le′hi, the Phi·lis′tines shouted triumphantly at meeting him. Then Jehovah’s spirit empowered him,<a class='mr'></a> and the ropes on his arms became like linen threads that were scorched with fire, and his fetters melted off his hands.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>He now found a fresh jawbone of a male donkey; he reached out and grabbed it and struck down 1,000 men with it.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Then Samson said:</p></div><div id='p178' class='par'><p class='sz'>“With the jawbone of a donkey—one heap, two heaps!</p></div><div id='p179' class='par'><p class='sb'>With the jawbone of a donkey I struck down 1,000 men.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p180' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>When he finished speaking, he threw the jawbone away and called that place Ra′math-le′hi.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_15_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then he became very thirsty, and he called on Jehovah and said: “It was you who gave this great salvation into the hand of your servant. But now am I to die of thirst and fall into the hands of the uncircumcised?” <span id='dcv_15_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>So God split open a hollow that was in Le′hi, and water flowed from it.<a class='mr'></a> When he drank, his spirit<a class='fn'></a> returned and he revived. That is why he named the place En-hak·kor′e,<a class='fn'></a> which is in Le′hi to this day.</p></div><div id='p181' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_15_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>And he judged Israel in the days of the Phi·lis′tines for 20 years.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="16"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p182' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>One time Samson went to Gaz′a and saw a prostitute there, and he went in to her. <span id='dcv_16_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The Gaz′ites were told: “Samson has come here.” So they surrounded him and lay in ambush for him all night long in the city gate. They stayed quiet the whole night, saying to themselves: “When daylight comes, we will kill him.”</p></div><div id='p183' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>However, Samson kept lying there until midnight. Then he got up at midnight and grabbed the doors of the city gate and the two side posts and pulled them out along with the bar. He put them on his shoulders and carried them up to the top of the mountain that faces Heb′ron.</p></div><div id='p184' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>After that he fell in love with a woman in the Valley<a class='fn'></a> of So′rek whose name was De·li′lah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>So the lords of the Phi·lis′tines approached her and said: “Trick<a class='fn'></a> him<a class='mr'></a> and find out what gives him such great strength and how we can overpower him and tie him and subdue him. For this we will each give you 1,100 silver pieces.”</p></div><div id='p185' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>De·li′lah later said to Samson: “Please tell me where your great power comes from and what can be used to tie you and subdue you.” <span id='dcv_16_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Samson said to her: “If they tie me with seven fresh bowstrings<a class='fn'></a> that have not been dried out, I will grow as weak as an ordinary man.” <span id='dcv_16_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So the lords of the Phi·lis′tines brought up to her seven fresh bowstrings that had not been dried out, and she tied him with them. <span id='dcv_16_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Now they set an ambush in the inner room, and she called out to him: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” At that he tore apart the bowstrings, just as easily as a thread of flax<a class='fn'></a> comes apart when it touches fire.<a class='mr'></a> The secret of his power did not become known.</p></div><div id='p186' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>Then De·li′lah said to Samson: “Look! You have fooled me<a class='fn'></a> and told me lies. Now tell me, please, what can be used to tie you.” <span id='dcv_16_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>So he said to her: “If they tie me up with new ropes that have not been used for work, I will grow as weak as an ordinary man.” <span id='dcv_16_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>So De·li′lah took new ropes and tied him with them and called out: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” (All the while the ambush was set in the inner room.) At that he tore them off his arms like threads.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p187' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>After that De·li′lah said to Samson: “Up until now you have fooled me and told me lies.<a class='mr'></a> Tell me what can be used to tie you.” Then he said to her: “If you weave the seven braids of my head with the warp thread.” <span id='dcv_16_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>So she fixed them with a pin and called out to him: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” So he woke up from his sleep and pulled out the loom pin and the warp thread.</p></div><div id='p188' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>She now said to him: “How can you say, ‘I love you,’<a class='mr'></a> when your heart is not with me? These three times you have fooled me and have not told me the source of your great power.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Because day after day she kept nagging him and pressuring him, he<a class='fn'></a> was weary to the point of dying.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_16_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>So he finally opened his heart to her, saying: “A razor has never touched my head, because I am a Naz′i·rite of God from birth.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> If I am shaved, my power will leave me and I will grow weak and become like all other men.”</p></div><div id='p189' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>When De·li′lah saw that he had opened his heart to her, she immediately summoned the Phi·lis′tine lords,<a class='mr'></a> saying: “Come up this time, for he has opened his heart to me.” So the Phi·lis′tine lords came up to her, bringing the money with them. <span id='dcv_16_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>She made him fall asleep on her knees; then she called the man and had him shave off the seven braids of his head. After that she began to have control over him, for his power was leaving him. <span id='dcv_16_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Now she called out: “The Phi·lis′tines are upon you, Samson!” He woke up from his sleep and said: “I will go out as at other times<a class='mr'></a> and shake myself free.” But he did not know that Jehovah had left him. <span id='dcv_16_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>So the Phi·lis′tines seized him and bored his eyes out. Then they brought him down to Gaz′a and bound him with two copper fetters, and he became a grinder of grain in the prison. <span id='dcv_16_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>But the hair of his head started to grow back again after he had been shaved.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p190' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>The Phi·lis′tine lords gathered together to offer a great sacrifice to Da′gon<a class='mr'></a> their god and to celebrate, for they were saying: “Our god has given Samson our enemy into our hand!” <span id='dcv_16_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>When the people saw him, they praised their god and said: “Our god has given into our hand our enemy, the one who devastated our land<a class='mr'></a> and killed so many of us.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p191' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>Because their heart was cheerful, they said: “Call Samson to provide us some amusement.” So they called Samson out of the prison to entertain them; they made him stand between the pillars. <span id='dcv_16_26' class='dv dx dp'><a>26 </a></span>Then Samson said to the boy holding him by the hand: “Let me feel the pillars that support the house, so that I can lean against them.” <span id='dcv_16_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>(Incidentally, the house was full of men and women. All the Phi·lis′tine lords were there, and on the roof there were about 3,000 men and women who were looking on while Samson provided amusement.)</p></div><div id='p192' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_28' class='dv dx dp'><a>28 </a></span>Samson<a class='mr'></a> now called out to Jehovah: “Sovereign Lord Jehovah, remember me, please, and strengthen me,<a class='mr'></a> please, just this once, O God, and let me take revenge on the Phi·lis′tines for one of my two eyes.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p193' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_29' class='dv dx dp'><a>29 </a></span>Then Samson braced himself against the two middle pillars that supported the house, and he leaned on them with his right hand on one and his left hand on the other. <span id='dcv_16_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>Samson called out: “Let me<a class='fn'></a> die with the Phi·lis′tines!” Then he pushed with all his might, and the house fell on the lords and all the people in it.<a class='mr'></a> So he killed more at his death than he had killed during his life.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p194' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_16_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>Later his brothers and all his father’s family came down to take him back. They brought him up and buried him between Zo′rah<a class='mr'></a> and Esh′ta·ol in the tomb of Ma·no′ah<a class='mr'></a> his father. He had judged Israel for 20 years.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="17"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p195' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_1' class='dc dp'><a>17 </a></span>There was a man of the mountainous region of E′phra·im<a class='mr'></a> named Mi′cah. <span id='dcv_17_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>He said to his mother: “The 1,100 silver pieces that were taken from you about which you pronounced a curse, which I heard—look! the silver is with me. I was the one who took it.” At that his mother said: “May Jehovah bless my son.” <span id='dcv_17_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>So he gave the 1,100 pieces of silver back to his mother, but his mother said: “I will without fail sanctify the silver to Jehovah from my hand for my son to use in making a carved image and a metal statue.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> Now I give it back to you.”</p></div><div id='p196' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>After he returned the silver to his mother, his mother took 200 silver pieces and gave them to the silversmith. He made a carved image and a metal statue;<a class='fn'></a> and they were put in Mi′cah’s house. <span id='dcv_17_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>This man Mi′cah had a house of gods, and he made an eph′od<a class='mr'></a> and teraphim statues<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and installed<a class='fn'></a> one of his sons to serve as priest for him.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>In those days, there was no king in Israel.<a class='mr'></a> Each one was doing what was right in his own eyes.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p197' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_17_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Now there was a young man of Beth′le·hem<a class='mr'></a> in Judah who was of the family of Judah. He was a Levite<a class='mr'></a> who had been living there for a time. <span id='dcv_17_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>The man left the city of Beth′le·hem in Judah to find a place to live. While on his journey, he came to the mountainous region of E′phra·im, to the house of Mi′cah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_17_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then Mi′cah said to him: “Where do you come from?” He replied: “I am a Levite from Beth′le·hem in Judah, and I am on my way to find a place to live.” <span id='dcv_17_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So Mi′cah said to him: “Stay with me and serve as a father<a class='fn'></a> and a priest for me. I will give you ten silver pieces a year and a set of garments and your food.” So the Levite went in. <span id='dcv_17_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Thus the Levite agreed to stay with the man, and the young man became like one of his sons. <span id='dcv_17_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>Furthermore, Mi′cah installed<a class='fn'></a> the Levite to serve as a priest for him,<a class='mr'></a> and he lived in the house of Mi′cah. <span id='dcv_17_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then Mi′cah said: “Now I know that Jehovah will be good to me, for the Levite has become my priest.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="18"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p198' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_1' class='dc dp'><a>18 </a></span>In those days there was no king in Israel.<a class='mr'></a> And in those days the tribe of the Dan′ites<a class='mr'></a> was looking for an inheritance to dwell in, because until then they had not received an inheritance among the tribes of Israel.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p199' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The Dan′ites sent five men from among their family, capable men from Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol,<a class='mr'></a> to spy out the land and to explore it. They said to them: “Go, explore the land.” When they came to the mountainous region of E′phra·im, to the house of Mi′cah,<a class='mr'></a> they spent the night there. <span id='dcv_18_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>While they were near the house of Mi′cah, they recognized the voice<a class='fn'></a> of the young Levite man, so they went over to him and asked: “Who brought you here? What are you doing in this place? What is keeping you here?” <span id='dcv_18_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>He replied to them: “Thus and so Mi′cah did for me, and he hired me to serve as priest for him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then they said to him: “Please ask God whether our journey will be successful.” <span id='dcv_18_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The priest said to them: “Go in peace. Jehovah is with you on your journey.”</p></div><div id='p200' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>So the five men went on and came to La′ish.<a class='mr'></a> They saw how the people in it were dwelling in self-reliance in the manner of the Si·do′ni·ans. They were quiet and unsuspecting,<a class='mr'></a> and no oppressive conqueror was in the land to disturb them. They were far away from the Si·do′ni·ans, and they had no dealings with anyone else.</p></div><div id='p201' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>When they returned to their brothers at Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol,<a class='mr'></a> their brothers said to them: “How did it go?” <span id='dcv_18_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>They replied: “Let us go up against them, for we have seen that the land is very good. Why are you hesitant? Do not delay to go in to take possession of the land. <span id='dcv_18_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>When you arrive, you will find an unsuspecting people,<a class='mr'></a> and the land is spacious. God has given it into your hand, a place where there is no lack of anything on the earth.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p202' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Then 600 men armed for battle from the family of the Dan′ites departed from Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>They went up and camped at Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim<a class='mr'></a> in Judah. That is why that place, which is west of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, is called Ma′ha·neh-dan<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> to this day. <span id='dcv_18_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>They went from there to the mountainous region of E′phra·im and came to the house of Mi′cah.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p203' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then the five men who had gone to spy out the land of La′ish<a class='mr'></a> said to their brothers: “Did you know that there are in these houses an eph′od, teraphim statues,<a class='fn'></a> a carved image, and a metal statue?<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> Think about what you should do.” <span id='dcv_18_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>So they stopped there and came to the house of the young Levite man<a class='mr'></a> at the house of Mi′cah and asked how he was. <span id='dcv_18_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>All the while the 600 men of Dan,<a class='mr'></a> armed for battle, stood at the entrance of the gate. <span id='dcv_18_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>The five men who had gone to spy out the land<a class='mr'></a> went inside to take the carved image, the eph′od,<a class='mr'></a> the teraphim statues,<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> and the metal image.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> (The priest<a class='mr'></a> was standing at the entrance of the gate with the 600 men armed for battle.) <span id='dcv_18_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>They went into the house of Mi′cah and took the carved image, the eph′od, the teraphim statues,<a class='fn'></a> and the metal image.<a class='fn'></a> The priest said to them: “What are you doing?” <span id='dcv_18_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>But they said to him: “Be quiet. Put your hand over your mouth, and come with us to be a father<a class='fn'></a> and a priest for us. Which is better—for you to be a priest to the house of one man<a class='mr'></a> or to become a priest to a tribe and family in Israel?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So the priest was satisfied, and he took the eph′od, the teraphim statues,<a class='fn'></a> and the carved image<a class='mr'></a> and went off with the people.</p></div><div id='p204' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then they turned to go on their way, putting the children, the livestock, and the valuable things ahead of them. <span id='dcv_18_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>They had gone some distance away from the house of Mi′cah when the men who lived in the houses near the house of Mi′cah gathered together and caught up with the Dan′ites. <span id='dcv_18_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>When they cried out to the Dan′ites, they turned to face them and said to Mi′cah: “What is the matter? Why have you been gathered together?” <span id='dcv_18_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>So he said: “You have taken my gods that I made, and you have gone off with the priest too. What do I have left? How, then, can you ask me, ‘What is the matter with you?’” <span id='dcv_18_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>The Dan′ites replied: “Do not raise your voice against us; otherwise, angry men<a class='fn'></a> may assault you, and that would cost you your life<a class='fn'></a> and the lives<a class='fn'></a> of your household.” <span id='dcv_18_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>So the Dan′ites went on their way; and Mi′cah, seeing that they were stronger than he was, turned and went back to his house.</p></div><div id='p205' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_18_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>After they took what Mi′cah had made, as well as his priest, they went to La′ish,<a class='mr'></a> to a people quiet and unsuspecting.<a class='mr'></a> They struck them down with the sword and burned the city with fire. <span id='dcv_18_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>There was no one to rescue it, for it was far from Si′don and they had no dealings with anyone else and it was in the valley plain<a class='fn'></a> that belonged to Beth-re′hob.<a class='mr'></a> Then they rebuilt the city and settled in it. <span id='dcv_18_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Furthermore, they named the city Dan<a class='mr'></a> after the name of their father, Dan, who was born to Israel.<a class='mr'></a> But La′ish was the city’s former name.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_18_30' class='dv dx dp'><a>30 </a></span>After that the Dan′ites set up the carved image<a class='mr'></a> for themselves, and Jon′a·than<a class='mr'></a> the son of Ger′shom,<a class='mr'></a> the son of Moses, and his sons became priests to the tribe of the Dan′ites until the day that the inhabitants of the land went into exile. <span id='dcv_18_31' class='dv dx dp'><a>31 </a></span>And they set up the carved image that Mi′cah had made, and it remained there all the days that the house of the true God was in Shi′loh.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="19"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p206' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>In those days, when there was no king in Israel,<a class='mr'></a> a Levite who was then living in a remote part of the mountainous region of E′phra·im<a class='mr'></a> took a concubine from Beth′le·hem<a class='mr'></a> in Judah as his wife. <span id='dcv_19_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>But his concubine was unfaithful to him, and she left him to go to her father’s house at Beth′le·hem in Judah. She remained there for four months. <span id='dcv_19_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Then her husband went after her to persuade her to come back; he had his male attendant and a couple of donkeys with him. So she brought him into her father’s house. When her father saw him, he was glad to meet him. <span id='dcv_19_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So his father-in-law, the young woman’s father, convinced him to stay with him three days; and they would eat and drink, and he would spend the night there.</p></div><div id='p207' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>On the fourth day, when they got up early in the morning to go, the father of the young woman said to his son-in-law: “Eat something to give you strength,<a class='fn'></a> and then you may go.” <span id='dcv_19_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So they sat down, and they both ate and drank together; after that the father of the young woman said to the man: “Please, stay overnight and enjoy yourself.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_19_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>When the man rose to go, his father-in-law kept begging him, so he stayed overnight again.</p></div><div id='p208' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>When he got up early in the morning on the fifth day to go, the father of the young woman said: “Please, eat something to give you strength.”<a class='fn'></a> And they lingered until it was late in the day, and they both kept eating. <span id='dcv_19_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>When the man rose to go with his concubine and his attendant, his father-in-law, the young woman’s father, said to him: “Look, now! It is almost evening. Please, stay overnight. Here the day is coming to an end. Stay here overnight and enjoy yourself. Tomorrow you can get up early for your journey and go to your home.”<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_19_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>However, the man did not want to stay another night, so he got up and traveled as far as Je′bus, that is, Jerusalem.<a class='mr'></a> He had with him the two saddled donkeys, his concubine, and his attendant.</p></div><div id='p209' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>When they were close to Je′bus, the daylight was nearly gone. So the attendant said to his master: “Should we stop at this city of the Jeb′u·sites and stay overnight here?” <span id='dcv_19_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>But his master said to him: “We should not stop at a city of foreigners who are not Israelites. We will go on as far as Gib′e·ah.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then he said to his attendant: “Come and let us try to reach one of those places; we will stay overnight either in Gib′e·ah or in Ra′mah.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>So they went on their way, and the sun began to set when they were near Gib′e·ah, which belongs to Benjamin.</p></div><div id='p210' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>So they stopped there and went in to stay overnight in Gib′e·ah. Once inside, they sat down in the public square of the city, but nobody took them into his house to stay overnight.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>Eventually that evening, an old man came in from his work in the field. He was from the mountainous region of E′phra·im,<a class='mr'></a> and he was living for a time in Gib′e·ah; but the residents of the city were Ben′ja·min·ites.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>When he looked up and saw the traveler in the public square of the city, the old man said: “Where are you going, and where do you come from?” <span id='dcv_19_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>He replied: “We are traveling from Beth′le·hem in Judah to a remote area of the mountainous region of E′phra·im, where I am from. I went to Beth′le·hem in Judah,<a class='mr'></a> and I am going to the house of Jehovah,<a class='fn'></a> but nobody is taking me into his house. <span id='dcv_19_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>We have enough straw and fodder for our donkeys,<a class='mr'></a> and bread<a class='mr'></a> and wine for me, the woman, and our attendant. There is nothing lacking.” <span id='dcv_19_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>However, the old man said: “May you have peace! Let me take care of anything you need. Just do not stay overnight in the public square.” <span id='dcv_19_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>So he brought him into his house and gave feed<a class='fn'></a> to the donkeys. Then they washed their feet and ate and drank.</p></div><div id='p211' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>While they were enjoying themselves, some worthless men of the city surrounded the house and were pounding on the door, and they kept saying to the old man who owned the house: “Bring out the man who came into your house, so that we may have sex with him.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_19_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>At that the owner of the house went out and said to them: “No, my brothers, do not act wickedly. Please, this man is a guest in my house. Do not commit this disgraceful act. <span id='dcv_19_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>Here are my virgin daughter and this man’s concubine. Let me bring them out, and you can humiliate them if you must.<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> But you must not commit this disgraceful act toward this man.”</p></div><div id='p212' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>But the men refused to listen to him, so the man grabbed hold of his concubine<a class='mr'></a> and brought her outside to them. They raped her and abused her all night long until the morning. Then they sent her away at the break of dawn. <span id='dcv_19_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>Early in the morning, the woman came and fell down at the entrance of the man’s house where her master was and lay there until it was light. <span id='dcv_19_27' class='dv dp'><a>27 </a></span>When her master got up in the morning and opened the doors of the house to go out to resume his journey, he saw the woman, his concubine, lying at the entrance of the house with her hands on the threshold. <span id='dcv_19_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>So he said to her: “Get up; let us go.” But there was no answer. The man then put her on the donkey and set out for his home.</p></div><div id='p213' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_19_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>When he reached his house, he took the slaughtering knife and took hold of his concubine and cut her up limb by limb into 12 pieces and sent one piece into each territory of Israel. <span id='dcv_19_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>All who saw it said: “Such a thing has never happened or been seen from the day that the Israelites went up out of the land of Egypt down to this day. Consider it,<a class='fn'></a> take counsel,<a class='mr'></a> and tell us what to do.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="20"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p214' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Consequently, all the Israelites came out from Dan<a class='mr'></a> down to Be′er-she′ba and from the land of Gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> and the entire assembly gathered unitedly<a class='fn'></a> before Jehovah at Miz′pah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>So the chiefs of the people and all the tribes of Israel took their places in the congregation of God’s people—400,000 foot soldiers armed with swords.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p215' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>The Ben′ja·min·ites heard that the men of Israel had gone up to Miz′pah.</p></div><div id='p216' class='par'><p class='sb'>Then the men of Israel said: “Tell us, how did this terrible thing happen?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>At this the Levite man,<a class='mr'></a> the husband of the murdered woman, said in answer: “I came to Gib′e·ah<a class='mr'></a> of Benjamin with my concubine to stay overnight. <span id='dcv_20_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>And the inhabitants<a class='fn'></a> of Gib′e·ah rose up against me and surrounded the house by night. They meant to kill me, but they raped my concubine instead, and she died.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So I took my concubine’s body and cut it up and sent the pieces into every part of Israel’s inheritance,<a class='mr'></a> because they had committed a shameful and disgraceful act in Israel. <span id='dcv_20_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>Now all you people of Israel, give your advice and counsel<a class='mr'></a> here.”</p></div><div id='p217' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then all the people rose up in unison<a class='fn'></a> and said: “Not one of us will go to his tent or return to his house. <span id='dcv_20_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>Now this is what we will do to Gib′e·ah: We will go up against it by lot.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>We will take 10 men out of 100 from all the tribes of Israel, and 100 out of 1,000 and 1,000 out of 10,000 to collect provisions for the army, so that they may take action against Gib′e·ah of Benjamin, in view of the disgraceful act that they committed in Israel.” <span id='dcv_20_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>Thus all the men of Israel were gathered against the city united<a class='fn'></a> as allies.</p></div><div id='p218' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Then the tribes of Israel sent men to all the tribesmen of Benjamin, saying: “What is this terrible thing that has happened among you? <span id='dcv_20_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Now hand over the worthless men from Gib′e·ah,<a class='mr'></a> so that we may put them to death and clear out what is bad from Israel.”<a class='mr'></a> But the Ben′ja·min·ites refused to listen to their Israelite brothers.</p></div><div id='p219' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then the Ben′ja·min·ites gathered together out of the cities to Gib′e·ah to go out to battle against the men of Israel. <span id='dcv_20_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>That day the Ben′ja·min·ites mustered from their cities 26,000 men armed with swords, apart from the 700 chosen men of Gib′e·ah. <span id='dcv_20_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>In this army were 700 chosen men who were left-handed. Every one of these men could sling a stone to within a hairbreadth and would not miss.</p></div><div id='p220' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>The men of Israel apart from Benjamin mustered 400,000 men armed with swords,<a class='mr'></a> and each one was an experienced warrior. <span id='dcv_20_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>They rose up and went up to Beth′el to inquire of God.<a class='mr'></a> Then the people of Israel said: “Who of us should go up in the lead to the battle against the Ben′ja·min·ites?” Jehovah replied: “Judah is to take the lead.”</p></div><div id='p221' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>After that the Israelites rose up in the morning and camped against Gib′e·ah.</p></div><div id='p222' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>The men of Israel now went out to battle against Benjamin; they drew up in battle formation against them at Gib′e·ah. <span id='dcv_20_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>So the Ben′ja·min·ites came out from Gib′e·ah and struck down 22,000 men of Israel on that day. <span id='dcv_20_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>However, the army of the men of Israel showed themselves courageous and again drew up in battle formation in the same place as on the first day. <span id='dcv_20_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>Then the Israelites went up and wept before Jehovah until the evening and inquired of Jehovah: “Should we again go into battle against our brothers, the people of Benjamin?”<a class='mr'></a> To this Jehovah said: “Go up against them.”</p></div><div id='p223' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>So the Israelites drew near to the Ben′ja·min·ites on the second day. <span id='dcv_20_25' class='dv dp'><a>25 </a></span>In turn Benjamin came out from Gib′e·ah to meet them on the second day and struck down another 18,000 Israelites,<a class='mr'></a> all of them armed with swords. <span id='dcv_20_26' class='dv dp'><a>26 </a></span>At that all the men of Israel went up to Beth′el. They wept and sat there before Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> and they fasted<a class='mr'></a> on that day until the evening and offered up burnt offerings<a class='mr'></a> and communion offerings<a class='mr'></a> before Jehovah. <span id='dcv_20_27' class='dv dx dp'><a>27 </a></span>After that the men of Israel inquired of Jehovah,<a class='mr'></a> for the ark of the covenant of the true God was there in those days. <span id='dcv_20_28' class='dv dp'><a>28 </a></span>Now Phin′e·has<a class='mr'></a> the son of El·e·a′zar, the son of Aaron, was ministering<a class='fn'></a> before it in those days. They asked: “Should we go out yet again to battle against our brothers, the men of Benjamin, or should we stop?”<a class='mr'></a> Jehovah replied: “Go up, because tomorrow I will give them into your hand.” <span id='dcv_20_29' class='dv dp'><a>29 </a></span>Then Israel set men in ambush<a class='mr'></a> all around Gib′e·ah.</p></div><div id='p224' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_30' class='dv dp'><a>30 </a></span>The Israelites went up against the Ben′ja·min·ites on the third day, and they drew up in formation against Gib′e·ah the same as at the other times.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_31' class='dv dp'><a>31 </a></span>When the Ben′ja·min·ites went out to meet the army, they were drawn away from the city.<a class='mr'></a> Then, as at the other times, they started to attack and kill some of the men on the highways, one of which goes up to Beth′el and the other to Gib′e·ah, leaving about 30 men of Israel dead in the open field.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_32' class='dv dp'><a>32 </a></span>So the Ben′ja·min·ites said: “They are suffering defeat before us the same as before.”<a class='mr'></a> But the Israelites said: “We will retreat and draw them away from the city onto the highways.” <span id='dcv_20_33' class='dv dx dp'><a>33 </a></span>So all the men of Israel rose up from their places and drew up in formation at Ba′al-ta′mar while the Israelite ambush charged out of their places in the vicinity of Gib′e·ah. <span id='dcv_20_34' class='dv dp'><a>34 </a></span>Thus 10,000 chosen men out of all Israel came in front of Gib′e·ah, and the fighting was heavy. But the Ben′ja·min·ites did not know that disaster was near at hand.</p></div><div id='p225' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_35' class='dv dp'><a>35 </a></span>Jehovah defeated Benjamin<a class='mr'></a> before Israel, and on that day the Israelites struck down 25,100 men in Benjamin, all of them armed with swords.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p226' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_36' class='dv dp'><a>36 </a></span>However, the Ben′ja·min·ites imagined that the men of Israel would be defeated when they retreated from Benjamin,<a class='mr'></a> but they retreated because they trusted in the ambush that was set against Gib′e·ah.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_37' class='dv dp'><a>37 </a></span>The ambush acted quickly and charged toward Gib′e·ah. Then the ambush spread out and struck down the whole city with the sword.</p></div><div id='p227' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_38' class='dv dp'><a>38 </a></span>Now the men of Israel had arranged that the men who ambushed the city would make a smoke signal go up from there.</p></div><div id='p228' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_39' class='dv dp'><a>39 </a></span>When the Israelites turned around in the battle, the men of Benjamin started by attacking and killing about 30 men of Israel,<a class='mr'></a> and they said: “They are clearly suffering another defeat before us, just as in the previous battle.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_20_40' class='dv dp'><a>40 </a></span>But the signal started to go up from the city as a pillar of smoke. When the men of Benjamin turned to look, they saw the whole city going up in flames to the sky. <span id='dcv_20_41' class='dv dp'><a>41 </a></span>Then the men of Israel made an about-face, and the men of Benjamin were dismayed, for they saw that disaster had overtaken them. <span id='dcv_20_42' class='dv dp'><a>42 </a></span>So they retreated from the men of Israel toward the wilderness, but the battle followed them; the men coming out of the cities joined in striking them down. <span id='dcv_20_43' class='dv dp'><a>43 </a></span>They surrounded the Ben′ja·min·ites and pursued them relentlessly. They trampled them down directly in front of Gib′e·ah toward the east. <span id='dcv_20_44' class='dv dp'><a>44 </a></span>Finally 18,000 men of Benjamin fell, all mighty warriors.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p229' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_45' class='dv dp'><a>45 </a></span>The men of Benjamin turned and fled into the wilderness to the crag of Rim′mon,<a class='mr'></a> and the Israelites killed<a class='fn'></a> 5,000 of them on the highways, and they kept pursuing them as far as Gi′dom; so they struck down 2,000 more men. <span id='dcv_20_46' class='dv dp'><a>46 </a></span>All those of Benjamin who fell on that day amounted to 25,000 men armed with swords,<a class='mr'></a> all mighty warriors. <span id='dcv_20_47' class='dv dp'><a>47 </a></span>But 600 retreated into the wilderness to the crag of Rim′mon, and they stayed on the crag of Rim′mon for four months.</p></div><div id='p230' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_20_48' class='dv dp'><a>48 </a></span>And the men of Israel turned back against the Ben′ja·min·ites and struck those of the city with the sword, from men to livestock, all that remained. Also, they set all the cities in their path on fire.</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="21"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p231' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_1' class='dc dp'><a>21 </a></span>Now the men of Israel had sworn this oath in Miz′pah:<a class='mr'></a> “Not one of us will give his daughter to a man from Benjamin as a wife.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Consequently, the people came to Beth′el<a class='mr'></a> and sat there before the true God until evening, crying out and weeping bitterly. <span id='dcv_21_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>And they were saying: “Why, O Jehovah the God of Israel, has this happened in Israel? Why should one tribe be missing today from Israel?” <span id='dcv_21_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>And the next day the people got up early and built an altar there to offer up burnt offerings and communion offerings.<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p232' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then the people of Israel said: “Who of all the tribes of Israel did not come up to assemble before Jehovah?” for they had taken a great oath that anyone who did not come up to Jehovah at Miz′pah would be put to death without fail. <span id='dcv_21_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>So the people of Israel felt sorrow over what had happened to Benjamin their brother. They said: “Today one tribe has been chopped off from Israel. <span id='dcv_21_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>What should we do to provide wives for those who are left, now that we have sworn by Jehovah<a class='mr'></a> not to give them any of our daughters as wives?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p233' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>They asked: “Who among the tribes of Israel did not come up to Jehovah at Miz′pah?”<a class='mr'></a> It so happened that no one had come from Ja′besh-gil′e·ad into the camp where the congregation was. <span id='dcv_21_9' class='dv dp'><a>9 </a></span>When the people were counted, they saw that none of the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad were there. <span id='dcv_21_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>So the assembly sent there 12,000 of the mightiest men. They commanded them: “Go and strike down the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad with the sword, even the women and the children.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_21_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>This is what you should do: Every male as well as every woman who has had sexual relations with a male, you should devote to destruction.” <span id='dcv_21_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Among the inhabitants of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad, they found 400 girls who were virgins, who had never had sexual relations with a man. So they brought them to the camp at Shi′loh,<a class='mr'></a> which is in the land of Ca′naan.</p></div><div id='p234' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>Then all the assembly sent a message to the Ben′ja·min·ites on the crag of Rim′mon<a class='mr'></a> and offered them peace. <span id='dcv_21_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>So Benjamin came back at that time. They gave them the women whom they had kept alive from the women of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad,<a class='mr'></a> but they did not find enough for them. <span id='dcv_21_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>And the people felt sorrow over what had happened to Benjamin<a class='mr'></a> because Jehovah had made a division among the tribes of Israel. <span id='dcv_21_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>The elders of the assembly said: “What should we do to provide wives for the remaining men, since all the women were annihilated out of Benjamin?” <span id='dcv_21_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>They replied: “There should be an inheritance for the survivors of Benjamin, so that a tribe may not be wiped out of Israel. <span id='dcv_21_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>But we are not allowed to give them wives from our daughters, because the people of Israel have sworn: ‘Cursed is the one who gives a wife to Benjamin.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p235' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Then they said: “Look! There is a festival of Jehovah from year to year in Shi′loh,<a class='mr'></a> which is north of Beth′el and east of the highway that goes up from Beth′el to She′chem and south of Le·bo′nah.” <span id='dcv_21_20' class='dv dp'><a>20 </a></span>So they commanded the men of Benjamin: “Go and set an ambush in the vineyards. <span id='dcv_21_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>And when you see the young women<a class='fn'></a> of Shi′loh come out to join in their circle dances, each of you should come out from the vineyards and seize a wife from the young women of Shi′loh, and you should return to the land of Benjamin. <span id='dcv_21_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>And should their fathers or their brothers come to make a complaint against us, we will then tell them, ‘Show us favor for their sakes, because we could not provide each one a wife by war<a class='mr'></a> and you could not give a wife to them without becoming guilty.’”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p236' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_23' class='dv dp'><a>23 </a></span>So the men of Benjamin did just that, and they each carried off a wife from the women who were dancing. After that they went back to their inheritance and rebuilt their cities<a class='mr'></a> and settled in them.</p></div><div id='p237' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_24' class='dv dp'><a>24 </a></span>And the Israelites dispersed from there at that time, each one to his tribe and his family, and they departed from there, each one to his inheritance.</p></div><div id='p238' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_21_25' class='dv dx dp'><a>25 </a></span>In those days there was no king in Israel.<a class='mr'></a> Each one was doing what was right in his own eyes.<a class='fn'></a></p></div></div></text>
</bible>