<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
<text chap="1"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p1' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>1 </a></span>Now in the days when the judges<a class='mr'></a> administered justice,<a class='fn'></a> a famine occurred in the land; and a man went from Beth′le·hem<a class='mr'></a> in Judah to reside as a foreigner in the fields<a class='fn'></a> of Mo′ab,<a class='mr'></a> he along with his wife and his two sons. <span id='dcv_1_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>The man’s name was E·lim′e·lech,<a class='fn'></a> his wife’s name was Na·o′mi,<a class='fn'></a> and the names of his two sons were Mah′lon<a class='fn'></a> and Chil′i·on.<a class='fn'></a> They were Eph′rath·ites from Beth′le·hem in Judah. And they came to the fields of Mo′ab and remained there.</p></div><div id='p2' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>After some time E·lim′e·lech, Na·o′mi’s husband, died, and she was left with her two sons. <span id='dcv_1_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>The men later married Mo′ab·ite women; one was named Or′pah, and the other was named Ruth.<a class='mr'></a> They remained there for about ten years. <span id='dcv_1_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then the two sons, Mah′lon and Chil′i·on, also died, and the woman was left without her two children and her husband. <span id='dcv_1_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>So she started out with her daughters-in-law to return from the fields of Mo′ab, for she had heard in Mo′ab that Jehovah had turned his attention to his people by giving them food.<a class='fn'></a></p></div><div id='p3' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_7' class='dv dp'><a>7 </a></span>She left the place where she had been living with both of her daughters-in-law. As they were walking on the road to return to the land of Judah, <span id='dcv_1_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>Na·o′mi said to both of her daughters-in-law: “Go, return, each of you to your mother’s home. May Jehovah show loyal love to you,<a class='mr'></a> just as you have shown it to the men who have died and to me. <span id='dcv_1_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>May Jehovah grant<a class='fn'></a> that each of you finds security<a class='fn'></a> in the home of your husband.”<a class='mr'></a> Then she kissed them, and they wept loudly. <span id='dcv_1_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>They kept saying to her: “No, but we will go with you to your people.” <span id='dcv_1_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>But Na·o′mi said: “Return, my daughters. Why should you go with me? Can I still give birth to sons who could become your husbands?<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>Return, my daughters. Go, for I have grown too old to marry. Even if I could hope to find a husband tonight and could also bear sons, <span id='dcv_1_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>would you keep waiting for them until they could grow up? Would you refrain from getting remarried for their sakes? No, my daughters, I feel very bitter for you, because the hand of Jehovah has turned against me.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p4' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Again they wept loudly, after which Or′pah kissed her mother-in-law and departed. But Ruth stuck with her. <span id='dcv_1_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>So Na·o′mi said: “Look! Your widowed sister-in-law has returned to her people and her gods. Return with your sister-in-law.”</p></div><div id='p5' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>But Ruth said: “Do not plead with me to abandon you, to turn back from accompanying you; for where you go I will go, and where you spend the night, I will spend the night. Your people will be my people, and your God my God.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. May Jehovah do so to me and add to it if anything but death should separate me from you.”</p></div><div id='p6' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>When Na·o′mi saw that Ruth insisted on going with her, she stopped trying to convince her. <span id='dcv_1_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>And they both continued on their way until they came to Beth′le·hem.<a class='mr'></a> As soon as they arrived in Beth′le·hem, the whole city became stirred up over them, and women were saying: “Is this Na·o′mi?” <span id='dcv_1_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>She would say to the women: “Do not call me Na·o′mi.<a class='fn'></a> Call me Ma′ra,<a class='fn'></a> for the Almighty has made life very bitter for me.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_1_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>I was full when I went, but Jehovah made me return empty-handed. Why should you call me Na·o′mi, when it is Jehovah who opposed me and the Almighty who caused me calamity?”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p7' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_1_22' class='dv dp'><a>22 </a></span>This is how Na·o′mi returned from the fields of Mo′ab,<a class='mr'></a> along with her Mo′ab·ite daughter-in-law Ruth. They came to Beth′le·hem at the beginning of the barley harvest.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="2"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p8' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_1' class='dc dp'><a>2 </a></span>Now Na·o′mi had a relative on her husband’s side who was very wealthy; his name was Bo′az,<a class='mr'></a> and he was of the family of E·lim′e·lech.</p></div><div id='p9' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_2' class='dv dx dp'><a>2 </a></span>Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess said to Na·o′mi: “Let me go out, please, to the fields and glean<a class='mr'></a> among the ears of grain behind whoever looks on me with favor.” So Na·o′mi said to her: “Go, my daughter.” <span id='dcv_2_3' class='dv dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>At that she went out and began to glean in the field behind the harvesters. By chance she came upon a plot of land belonging to Bo′az,<a class='mr'></a> who was of the family of E·lim′e·lech.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_4' class='dv dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Just then Bo′az arrived from Beth′le·hem and said to the harvesters: “Jehovah be with you.” And they replied: “Jehovah bless you.”</p></div><div id='p10' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Bo′az then asked the young man in charge of the harvesters: “To whom does this young woman belong?” <span id='dcv_2_6' class='dv dp'><a>6 </a></span>The young man in charge of the harvesters answered: “The young woman is a Mo′ab·i·tess<a class='mr'></a> who returned with Na·o′mi from the fields of Mo′ab.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>She asked, ‘Please, may I glean<a class='mr'></a> and gather among the cut-off ears<a class='fn'></a> of grain left behind by the harvesters?’ And she has been on her feet since she came this morning until just now, when she sat in the shelter for a short rest.”</p></div><div id='p11' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>Then Bo′az said to Ruth: “Listen, my daughter. Do not go away to glean in another field, and do not go anywhere else; stay close by my young women.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Keep your eyes on the field that they harvest, and go with them. I have commanded the young men not to touch<a class='fn'></a> you. When you are thirsty, go to the water jars and drink from what the young men have drawn.”</p></div><div id='p12' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_10' class='dv dp'><a>10 </a></span>At that she fell facedown and bowed down to the ground and said to him: “How have I found favor in your eyes, and why have you taken notice of me, when I am a foreigner?”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>Bo′az answered her: “A full report was made to me of all you have done for your mother-in-law after the death of your husband and how you left your father and your mother and the land of your relatives to go to a people whom you had not known before.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>May Jehovah reward you for what you have done,<a class='mr'></a> and may there be a perfect wage<a class='fn'></a> for you from Jehovah the God of Israel, under whose wings you have come to seek refuge.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>To this she said: “Let me find favor in your eyes, my lord, because you have comforted me and spoken reassuringly to<a class='fn'></a> your servant, although I am not even one of your servants.”</p></div><div id='p13' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>Bo′az said to her at mealtime: “Come here, eat some of the bread, and dip your piece in the vinegar.” So she sat down beside the harvesters. He then handed her some roasted grain, and she ate and was satisfied, and she had something left over. <span id='dcv_2_15' class='dv dp'><a>15 </a></span>When she got up to glean,<a class='mr'></a> Bo′az commanded his young men: “Let her glean even among the cut-off ears<a class='fn'></a> of grain, and do not mistreat her.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_16' class='dv dp'><a>16 </a></span>You should also be sure to pull out some ears of grain from the bundles for her and leave them behind for her to glean, and do not say anything to stop her.”</p></div><div id='p14' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>So she continued to glean in the field until evening.<a class='mr'></a> When she beat out what she had gleaned, it came to about an e′phah<a class='fn'></a> of barley. <span id='dcv_2_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>Then she took it and went into the city, and her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned. Ruth also took out and gave to her the food that was left over<a class='mr'></a> after she had eaten her fill.</p></div><div id='p15' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_19' class='dv dx dp'><a>19 </a></span>Her mother-in-law then said to her: “Where did you glean today? Where did you work? May the one who took notice of you be blessed.”<a class='mr'></a> So she told her mother-in-law about whom she had worked with, saying: “The name of the man I worked with today is Bo′az.” <span id='dcv_2_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>At that Na·o′mi said to her daughter-in-law: “May he be blessed by Jehovah, who has not failed in his loyal love toward the living and the dead.”<a class='mr'></a> Na·o′mi continued: “The man is related to us.<a class='mr'></a> He is one of our repurchasers.”<a class='fn'></a><a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_21' class='dv dp'><a>21 </a></span>Then Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess said: “He also told me, ‘Stay close by my young people until they have finished my entire harvest.’”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_2_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>Na·o′mi said to her daughter-in-law Ruth: “It is better, my daughter, for you to go out with his young women than to be harassed in another field.”</p></div><div id='p16' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_2_23' class='dv dx dp'><a>23 </a></span>So she stayed close to the young women of Bo′az and gleaned until the barley harvest<a class='mr'></a> and the wheat harvest came to an end. And she kept dwelling with her mother-in-law.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
<text chap="3"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p17' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>3 </a></span>Na·o′mi, her mother-in-law, now said to her: “My daughter, should I not look for a home<a class='fn'></a> for you,<a class='mr'></a> so that it may go well with you? <span id='dcv_3_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Is not Bo′az our relative?<a class='mr'></a> He is the one whose young women you were with. Tonight he is winnowing barley at the threshing floor. <span id='dcv_3_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>So wash yourself and rub on some perfumed oil; then dress up<a class='fn'></a> and go down to the threshing floor. Do not make your presence known to the man until he has finished eating and drinking. <span id='dcv_3_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>When he lies down, take note of the place where he lies down; then go and uncover his feet and lie down. He will tell you what you should do.”</p></div><div id='p18' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_5' class='dv dx dp'><a>5 </a></span>At that she replied: “All that you say to me I will do.” <span id='dcv_3_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>So she went down to the threshing floor and did all that her mother-in-law had instructed her to do. <span id='dcv_3_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Meanwhile, Bo′az ate and drank and was feeling good at heart. Then he went to lie down at the end of the grain heap. After that she quietly came and uncovered his feet and lay down. <span id='dcv_3_8' class='dv dx dp'><a>8 </a></span>At midnight the man began to shiver, and he leaned forward and saw a woman lying at his feet. <span id='dcv_3_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>He said: “Who are you?” She replied: “I am Ruth, your servant. Spread out your garment<a class='fn'></a> over your servant, for you are a repurchaser.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>At that he said: “May Jehovah bless you, my daughter. You have shown your loyal love more in this last instance than in the first instance,<a class='mr'></a> by not going after the young men, whether poor or rich. <span id='dcv_3_11' class='dv dx dp'><a>11 </a></span>And now, my daughter, have no fear. I will do for you everything that you say,<a class='mr'></a> for everyone in the city<a class='fn'></a> knows that you are an excellent woman. <span id='dcv_3_12' class='dv dx dp'><a>12 </a></span>While it is true that I am a repurchaser,<a class='mr'></a> there is a repurchaser more closely related than I am.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_3_13' class='dv dx dp'><a>13 </a></span>Stay here tonight, and if he will repurchase you in the morning, fine! Let him repurchase you.<a class='mr'></a> But if he does not want to repurchase you, I will then repurchase you myself, as surely as Jehovah lives. Lie down here until the morning.”</p></div><div id='p19' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_14' class='dv dx dp'><a>14 </a></span>So she lay at his feet until the morning and then got up before it was light enough for anyone to be recognized. He then said: “Do not let it be known that a woman came to the threshing floor.” <span id='dcv_3_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He also said: “Bring the cloak that you are wearing, and hold it out.” So she held it out, and he put six measures<a class='fn'></a> of barley in it and put it on her, after which he went into the city.</p></div><div id='p20' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_3_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>She went her way to her mother-in-law, who now said: “How did it go for you,<a class='fn'></a> my daughter?” She told her everything that the man had done for her. <span id='dcv_3_17' class='dv dx dp'><a>17 </a></span>She added: “He gave me these six measures of barley and said to me, ‘Do not go empty-handed to your mother-in-law.’” <span id='dcv_3_18' class='dv dx dp'><a>18 </a></span>At that she said: “Sit here, my daughter, until you learn how the matter will turn out, for the man will not rest until he settles the matter today.”</p></div></div></text>
<text chap="4"><div class='document bible' dir='ltr'><div id='p21' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_1' class='dc dx dp'><a>4 </a></span>Now Bo′az went up to the city gate<a class='mr'></a> and sat there. And look! the repurchaser whom Bo′az had mentioned<a class='mr'></a> passed by. At that Bo′az said: “Come here and sit down, So-and-so.” And he went over and sat down. <span id='dcv_4_2' class='dv dp'><a>2 </a></span>Then Bo′az took ten of the city elders<a class='mr'></a> and said: “Sit down here.” So they sat down.</p></div><div id='p22' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_3' class='dv dp'><a>3 </a></span>Boaz now said to the repurchaser:<a class='mr'></a> “Na·o′mi, who has returned from the fields of Mo′ab,<a class='mr'></a> must sell the plot of land that belonged to our brother E·lim′e·lech.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_4' class='dv dp'><a>4 </a></span>So I thought I should disclose it to you and say, ‘Buy it in front of the inhabitants and the elders of my people.<a class='mr'></a> If you will repurchase it, repurchase it. But if you will not repurchase it, tell me so that I will know, for you have the claim to repurchase it, and I am next in line after you.’” He replied: “I am willing to repurchase it.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_5' class='dv dp'><a>5 </a></span>Then Bo′az said: “On the day you buy the field from Na·o′mi, you must also buy it from Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess, the wife of the dead man, in order to restore the name of the dead man to his inheritance.”<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_6' class='dv dx dp'><a>6 </a></span>To this the repurchaser said: “I am unable to repurchase it, for I may ruin my own inheritance. Repurchase it for yourself with my right of repurchase, because I am not able to repurchase it.”</p></div><div id='p23' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_7' class='dv dx dp'><a>7 </a></span>Now this was the custom of former times in Israel concerning the right of repurchase and exchange to validate every sort of transaction: A man had to remove his sandal<a class='mr'></a> and give it to the other party, and this was the manner of confirming an agreement<a class='fn'></a> in Israel. <span id='dcv_4_8' class='dv dp'><a>8 </a></span>So when the repurchaser said to Bo′az, “Buy it for yourself,” he removed his sandal. <span id='dcv_4_9' class='dv dx dp'><a>9 </a></span>Then Bo′az said to the elders and all the people: “You are witnesses<a class='mr'></a> today that I am buying from Na·o′mi all that belonged to E·lim′e·lech and all that belonged to Chil′i·on and Mah′lon. <span id='dcv_4_10' class='dv dx dp'><a>10 </a></span>I am also acquiring Ruth the Mo′ab·i·tess, the wife of Mah′lon, as a wife to restore the name of the dead man to his inheritance,<a class='mr'></a> so that the name of the dead man will not be cut off from among his brothers and from the city gate of his home. You are witnesses today.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p24' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_11' class='dv dp'><a>11 </a></span>At this all the people who were in the city gate and the elders said: “We are witnesses! May Jehovah grant the wife who is entering your house to be like Rachel and like Le′ah, both of whom built the house of Israel.<a class='mr'></a> May you prosper in Eph′ra·thah<a class='mr'></a> and make a good name<a class='fn'></a> in Beth′le·hem.<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_12' class='dv dp'><a>12 </a></span>May your house become like the house of Pe′rez,<a class='mr'></a> whom Ta′mar bore to Judah, through the offspring that Jehovah will give you by this young woman.”<a class='mr'></a></p></div><div id='p25' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_13' class='dv dp'><a>13 </a></span>So Bo′az took Ruth and she became his wife. He had relations with her, and Jehovah let her conceive and she gave birth to a son. <span id='dcv_4_14' class='dv dp'><a>14 </a></span>Then the women said to Na·o′mi: “Praised be Jehovah, who has not left you without a repurchaser today. May his name be proclaimed in Israel! <span id='dcv_4_15' class='dv dx dp'><a>15 </a></span>He<a class='fn'></a> has restored<a class='fn'></a> your life<a class='fn'></a> and will sustain you in your old age, because he has been born to your daughter-in-law, who loves you<a class='mr'></a> and is better to you than seven sons.” <span id='dcv_4_16' class='dv dx dp'><a>16 </a></span>Na·o′mi took the child and held him to her bosom, and she cared for him.<a class='fn'></a> <span id='dcv_4_17' class='dv dp'><a>17 </a></span>Then the neighbor women gave him a name. They said, “A son has been born to Na·o′mi,” and they named him O′bed.<a class='mr'></a> He is the father of Jes′se,<a class='mr'></a> David’s father.</p></div><div id='p26' class='par'><p class='sb'><span id='dcv_4_18' class='dv dp'><a>18 </a></span>Now this is the family line<a class='fn'></a> of Pe′rez:<a class='mr'></a> Pe′rez became father to Hez′ron;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_19' class='dv dp'><a>19 </a></span>Hez′ron became father to Ram; Ram became father to Am·min′a·dab;<a class='mr'></a> <span id='dcv_4_20' class='dv dx dp'><a>20 </a></span>Am·min′a·dab<a class='mr'></a> became father to Nah′shon; Nah′shon became father to Sal′mon; <span id='dcv_4_21' class='dv dx dp'><a>21 </a></span>Sal′mon became father to Bo′az; Bo′az became father to O′bed; <span id='dcv_4_22' class='dv dx dp'><a>22 </a></span>O′bed became father to Jes′se;<a class='mr'></a> and Jes′se became father to David.<a class='mr'></a></p></div></div></text>
</bible>